Recording in progress.
Good evening, ladies and gentlemen, and
welcome to the July 13th meeting of the
governing body. I'd ask the clerk to
take role, please.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> Mr. Moody,
>> present.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> Mr. Crave,
>> present.
>> Mr. White,
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> here.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> present. Mayor Collins
>> present.
>> Dr. Emmens
>> Mr. Esbel
>> present.
>> One member is absent. We do have a
quorum.
>> Will you please join me in the pledge of
allegiance?
>> I pledge algiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands. One nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
>> Proclamation recognizing members of the
Cheyenne Laramie County America 250
Commission.
Folks, I know we have a long meeting in
front of us tonight, but I wanted to
spend just a few minutes to say thank
you to a special group of volunteers and
to our city staff. As we all know, the
4th of July was our semiquincentennial
or our 250th birthday of our great
nation. For the past two years, our
America 250 committee has worked hard to
plan the events that took place over the
summer. The goal was to celebrate the
birthday, educate the kids in school,
bring our community together, and leave
something behind for future generations.
I believe our committee met that goal,
and went far beyond.
They went into schools and did
programming to help our school age kids
understand that the Fourth of July is
not just about fireworks, but was a
result of a great amount of work and
compromise that helped create our great
nation. It brought about
It brought [clears throat] our community
together to celebrate in numbers I
couldn't believe. At the civic center
for the play 1776 that showed the
struggle that the 13 colonies faced in
finding language they could all support
in the Declaration of Independence. It
was one of the largest parade crowds
I've ever seen and then an afternoon of
music in front of the Capitol that
culminated in a patriotic concert played
by Cheyenne Symphony Orchestra and
almost 70 people who made up the Wyoming
celebration choir. The evening ended
with fireworks choreographed to music.
A few days before we dedicated the
Echoes Wyoming at 250 bronze panels on
Capitol Avenue. It's a lasting monument
celebrating Wyoming that will be here
when we celebrate our 300th birthday.
I want to thank those folks and uh I
want to thank Shan Sean Ambrose, our
artistic director for the soldout
performance of 1776.
That show was amazing. Ruth Anne Huard
who used her CFD parade committee
expertise, years of expertise uh to
manage our patriotic parade that was
held downtown. The crowds were amazing
and they were so energetic. To Tom Bass,
my leadership Cheyenne classmate who led
the fundraising and the media outreach.
Folks, this committee raised hundreds of
thousands of private dollars to make
this week happen. to Randy Rhodess,
another CFD veteran who helped lead the
fireworks show that combined with the
science symphony to create an
unforgettable performance. To Dian
Prunty who led our efforts in the
schools to educate kids about the
miracle of the American exper
experiment. I also want to thank our
city staff for all their contributions.
We had hundreds of city staff out that
whole day from every department making
sure the day was perfect. Jason and our
CRA team rocked. Lieutenant Hickerson
and every first responder made sure the
day went off safely and I want to thank
all of them and I need to thank one
staff member personally. Others duty
other duties as assigned is sometimes
not a fair thing but they do happen and
it happens often for our chief of staff
Amber Ash. She was the lison between all
the different agencies in the county and
work so hard to make the day perfect and
I just want to say thank you personally
to Amber.
Last, I want to thank Nathaniel Trissiz.
This is the second time Nathaniel
stepped up to help the city. The first
time was the commissioner of our capital
city bronze project. It was a project
that I hoped would see 28 bronzes in
eight years and today we have over 90
and soon we're going to hit a hundred
and we still have two and a half years
left to go.
Second is chairman of the America's 250
committee. Nathaniel has definite ideas
of how things should go and how they
should be done and he brought together a
great team over the past two years to
make that happen. I know how much time
he and the entire committee gave to this
effort and I'm so proud of how it all
turned out. Now, I'd like to uh read a
proclamation from the city of Cheyenne.
says, "Whereas in the year 1776,
the Continental Congress adopted the
Declaration of Independence, asserting
the right of 13 colonies to
self-governance and freedom from British
rule." And whereas the Bold Declaration
laid the foundation for a new nation
built on the principles of liberty,
democracy, and justice. And whereas over
the past 250 years, the United States of
America has grown from a fledging
republic to a global superstar,
continually striving to uphold these
foundational ideals. And whereas in the
year 2026, the United States will
commemorate its 250th anniversary, also
know known as the semiquincentennial.
And whereas this occasion offers a
unique opportunity to reflect on the
nation's journey, celebrate its
achievements, and envision its future.
And whereas as a as we commemorate the
significant milestone, Americans should
work together in addressing the
challenges of the 21st century and
building more equitable and prosperous
society. And whereas nationwide
celebration events were organized to
engage and inspire citizens from all
walks of life, these activities included
parades and festivals. And whereas the
city's present- day citizens undertook
an initiative to plan, organize, and
execute a celebration of the recent
semi-quincentennial anniversary. And
these individuals deserve a formal full
measure recognition from this governing
body for the efforts and the fruit
thereof. And whereas the Cheyenne Larmy
County 250 commission consists of the
following civic-minded, truly dedicated
individuals whom the city owns a great
deal of gratitude.
Commission Chairman Nathaniel Trulliz,
member Sean Ambrose, Member Tom Bass,
Member Ruth Anne Hubard, Member Diane
Prunty, and member Randy Rhodess. And
whereas these individuals sacrificed
many hours and devoted extraordinary
effort to orchestrate the city's America
250 celebration, and thus they all
deserve significant praise and
commendation for their diligence and
dedication. Now therefore, be it
resolved by the governing body of the
city of Cheyenne, Wyoming, that the city
formally thanks those named members of
the Cheyenne Larmy County America 250
commission in hopes that generations
hence model their conduct and community
dedication upon these individuals and
plan to celebrate future anniversaries
with the same passion, zeal, and honor
as those named here have done today.
[applause]
>> [applause]
>> So you guys, I have a small gift um for
the committee to say thank you for your
commitment to the American 250
celebration. And uh I also have a
special city recognition for Nathaniel
Triliz. I struggled to find a way to
thank him for his service for our
community and I want to give Nathaniel
the key to the city as a way to express
our community's gratitude for his almost
5 years of constant effort to improve
the curb appeal of the city u with our
downtown art and for chairing our
America's 250 celebration
[applause]
Sure.
>> [applause]
[applause]
>> And now it's time to go to work.
Consent agenda. All agenda items listed
with the designation of CA are
considered to be routine items by the
governing body and will be enacted by
one motion. There will be no separate
discussion on these items unless a
member of the governing body so requests
and support by two other members is
received. Any item removed from the
consent agenda will be considered in its
normal sequence on the agenda.
>> All right. Is there an item or any items
that a member of this governing body
would like to remove from the consent
agenda?
I think we need to have 22 and 26B
removed. If I could get a motion to do
that, please.
>> So move.
Is there another concurrence?
>> Okay. Um, so 22 and 22 or 26B have been
removed. Uh, they're being removed
because they need to be in a certain
sequence on the agenda and, uh, has to
happen that way. Anybody else? Hearing
none, I would entertain a motion.
>> So move.
>> Second.
>> Moved by Mr. C. Graves, seconded by Dr.
Aldridge. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The consent agenda is
approved with 22 and 26B removed.
They'll be considered in their normal
sequence on the agenda.
>> Number 7A, public hearing for a bar and
grill liquor license application filed
with the city clerk's office for
Cheyenne Railard LLC doing business as
the Railard Cheyenne one 1115 West 15th
Street, Cheyenne, Wyoming.
>> It's always exciting to have a new
restaurant in our community and uh so
now we have a public hearing so they can
u get a bar and grill liquor license.
This is the opportunity then for anybody
who wants to uh comment about that
application.
Anybody?
Madame clerk, do you have anything that
you want to add?
Mayor through you Soden, city clerk, the
application before you this evening for
a public hearing is for the Cheyenne
Railard. Um it's for a bar and grill
liquor license and um the pertinent city
departments have reviewed the
application and it meets all
requirements. Thank you very much.
Anybody else in the audience want to
speak under this public hearing?
All right. Hearing none, the purpose of
the public hearing has been met and
we'll assign this item to the finance
committee.
Public hearing to determine whether
compliance of annexation conditions
required by Wyoming statute 15-1-42
exist for about 34.46 acres of land
located west of Roundtop Road and south
of Happy Jack Road.
Okay, we have uh a public hearing, but
before we go there, we'll go for a quick
staff report. Connor, it's all yours.
>> Mayor, members of council, Connor White,
Planning and Development Department. The
annexation is for roughly 34.46 acres of
land generally located west of Roundtop
Road, south of HappyJack Road. The city
received a petition to annex this land
from the owners, which was filed with
the city clerk on May 19th, 2026. This
petition was certified by the city clerk
containing all necessary signatures
according to state statute on May 21st,
2026. Uh, this public hearing is being
held in accordance with Wyoming state
statute 15142A.
Pursuant to fulfilling the requirements
in state statute, staff asks the
governing body to consider the
following.
The land proposed to be annexed is
contiguous to city limits. Specifically,
the property is 60.35%
contiguous.
The uh all city services and utilities
currently available to all properties
within the city will be provided to the
annexed land. Extending water and sewer
will increase the health and safety of
individuals living and working in this
area of the community.
The area to be annexed is inside the
urban service boundary and designated
with mixed use employment by the future
land use map. This type of development
is best support by being within city
limits.
Certified mailing was sent to all land
owners and utilities within the annexed
area not less than 20 business days
prior to the public hearing according to
the calendar 20 business days prior to
today's hearing was June 11th. Uh the
certified mailing went out on June 10th
and the earliest confirmed receipt was
June 12th. Property owners within 300
feet of the subject property were also
mailed notice.
Uh, two notes I do want to add. Uh, an
outside user agreement for this property
was approved by city council on June
22nd of this year. So, it already has an
outside water user agreement. And this
property already has an approved site
plan in the county for development
uh for an industrial staging area for uh
with office trailers, a parking lot, and
a layown yard. And the site is already
under development. So, this is just an
annexation of basically a property that
has county approvals and has a water
outside water agreement. Uh, they've
requested annexation and this
application does have an assigned zoning
that follows it. I am available for any
questions.
>> Thank you, Connor. Any questions from
staff?
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. Connor, can you
remind me, please? Is I believe that
when we approved this outside user
agreement that it was um we were under
the impression or told or had the
understanding that they were wanting to
come on to um city water and sewer. It
was just a timing issue of this. So that
outside user agreement is a temporary
solution but they will be moving towards
um connecting to our system.
>> Mayor through you that is correct. So
the outside user agreement is basically
it was their kind of temporary use to
get the construction going quicker. Um,
and then it basically we even said at
that basically the public hearing for
that or the meetings for that that they
were going to be coming in with an
annexation right after.
>> Mr. Wolf, did you have a question, sir?
>> I do, Mr. Mayor. Thank you. Through you.
Um, Mr. White, who's the applicant on
this?
>> Uh, mayor, through you. The applicant
requesting that is petitioned is Kings
Ranch LLC.
>> Okay. Um, that's Mark Eiffley's
operation.
Okay. Um, And and actually, Mr. Mayor,
this this is just sort of a suggestion
that um and just for the benefit of the
public, um when you read our agendas,
you don't know who the applicant is on
any of these. They're all listed just by
the property and where it's near. And
I'd like to suggest to the council and
to the clerk that when we list these
things, they ought to carry the
identifier of the applicant. Thank you,
Mr. Mayor.
Anybody else from governing body?
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Mayor Collins through you. I just would
like to remind everyone that um when the
agendas are made public that the
supporting documentation is available
and that does always have that
information. Um it's just not printed on
the actual agenda. So the supporting
documentation is there and does show
that um when people access those um
online.
>> Thank you.
>> Mr. Mayor, one one further question I
might is this in the North Range
Business Park?
>> Uh, mayor through you. This is adjacent
to North Range Business Park.
>> And is there any plan, Mr. Mayor,
through you, are there any plans for
that to become part of the business
park?
>> Mayor, through you. Um, I believe so. I
don't have the exact
right behind you. We can ask the
applicant.
>> Can ask the applicant.
>> Mr. Emmens,
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, city council members,
Brad Emmens, AVI agent for the applicant
uh and owner at the time uh of the uh
submitt. Uh yes, it's to be brought into
the North Range Business Park Commercial
Association. Um as soon as this is uh
completed, that that will be the next
process.
>> Thank you, sir. All right, we'll go out
to the audience. Does anybody in the
audience want to speak under this public
hearing uh on the annexation of these 34
acres?
Hello sir.
>> Hi David Nicely 200 Waltersh.
>> Um wait a second. Can we uh we need to
get our our threeminute clock started
here and now that the map so give me
just a second so Connor can can do that.
And folks, uh, the city council's asked
when you come up to identify yourself if
you could let us know what ward you live
in. Uh, they would appreciate that.
>> David Nicely 200 Wershed. Thankfully, I
don't live in the city.
I rise reluctantly to urge you to vote
no on annexation
because this city administration has
lost the confidence of the city people
and all addition to city via annexations
should be put off until the mayor, the
chief of staff and the planning director
Bloom are replaced. Resign, Mr. Mayor.
You've lost our trust. You should have
told us that the meta contamination
happened. that you didn't proves that
you are either crooked or incompetent.
Thank you.
>> Anybody else would like to speak this
evening?
>> Miss Madrid, welcome.
>> Thank you. Heather Madrid, I live in
Ward One. Um I'm just I more I have a
couple of questions. I wonder if the
county has or I mean I'm sorry the
council has seen the county plan
and if anything other than a planner
saying that that this does in fact meet
the health, safety and welfare of the
community is required or is just a
planner stating that and that's a and
that's enough
like is there any evidence?
>> I think uh we approved a outside user
agreement a number of months ago. I
don't remember when we did that. uh and
and they shared with us the plan um for
this development back at that time and
so
>> Okay.
>> So I I think this governing body is
aware of of what's going on in that
area.
>> Okay. So is anything other than a
planner for this annexation and it seems
like for all the annexation seems like
it's kind of just copy paste that
um
this is for the health, safety and
welfare of the citizens etc etc. It kind
of just ticks off the criteria but
doesn't really there's no real evidence.
I'm just wondering if there is evidence
because I can't find it for the life of
me
and I've tried I've tried hard.
>> Mr. Secret, if you want to answer.
>> Mr. Mayor, I I would just like to point
out that the um caption for that item
actually says an annexation of the area
is for the protection of the health,
safety, and welfare of the persons
residing in that area and in the city
and town.
>> So, it's for the person who owns it. Is
it for their health, safety, and welfare
as well as the city and town?
>> Okay.
>> So, it's obviously for their
>> benefit
>> because they asked for it.
>> Correct.
>> And they wanted city water and sewer for
that project.
>> Yeah. I don't I really honestly don't
have a problem with this particular
annexation. I'm just wondering if
there's
evidence submitted because as you said,
it's clear that the applicant wants
this. Um, but also part of the criteria
is that it has to be protecting the
health, safety, and welfare of the
citizens of the city. And I don't see
how this is. I'm not saying that it
isn't, but where is there evidence that
says one way or the other? I'm just
wondering.
>> Well, first of all, it's for the person
residing in the area. That's the first
thing in the state statute, and then
it's the city and town. So clearly, in
this case anyway, that person believes
it's in their benefit. And that's true
for most annexations. They believe that
city water, sewer, police, fire
planning, um, contributes to their
health, safety, and welfare. So, it's I
don't know. I don't know what other
source you're looking for.
>> Well, so you're saying that the only
person that matters when requesting
annexation is the property owner.
>> I'm not saying that. But I'm saying the
first person named is for the persons
I'm going to quote it welfare of the
persons residing in the area and in the
city and town.
>> Mhm.
>> So
>> not and
>> it is it is and I think that in this
case it's the benefit of the city and
town to have that area serviced by
water, sewer, fire, police, planning.
>> Okay.
>> Utilities.
>> Yeah. I'm I'm not necessarily
disagreeing with that. I'm just
wondering how do you know that? you feel
that way or is there evidence supporting
that is in fact the case?
>> I don't know what outside evidence
you're looking for. Do we need an expert
for that to to say that this 34 acres?
>> Maybe. I mean, I think we need more than
a feeling.
>> Well, I all I can say is it's obvious to
me that this area next to a business
park and this is a construction layown
yard and a parking lot is probably
beneficial by receiving public
utilities.
I don't I don't know what other expert I
can ask for that.
>> Well, typically according to this
statute, um there are studies that are
supposed to be done before annexation,
not just saying, you know, checking some
boxes, the property is annexed and then
the studies are done. That's not how
it's supposed to work, but that's how
annexations are happening.
>> I disagree. I disagree. I think the
applicant
>> Have there been studies done?
>> I'm sorry.
>> Have there been any studies? What kind
of studies are you talking about for a
34 acre annexation in a in a that's a
parking lot?
>> Well, as we've
like relentlessly gone over, there
apparently is no difference between a 2
acre annexation and a 3,500 acre
annexation. So, so I think what you're
saying about how big this property is is
irrelevant.
>> I'm I'm I guess I'm asking you what
other source of information are you
asking us to look at? Well, typically
according to the statute, there's
traffic studies, there's water draw down
studies, there's all kinds of studies
that are supposed to be happening before
a property is annexed, but that's not
happening. That's happening afterwards
currently.
Every annexation on this agenda is
happening that way. Well, I guess I
guess the way I look at this particular
annexation, the one we're talking about,
is that the owner has has asked for
these benefits and in their mind, and I
believe it's a benefit for the city and
town to have services provided to that
property since it's a joining existing
city property. I don't know what other
study I could do.
>> Well, any study, there's been none is
what I'm saying. And that's what the
statute requires. No matter who
initiates the annexation, these criteria
have to be met. That's what's in the
statute.
>> Okay. I'm not going to anymore.
>> Thank you, Heather.
>> Good evening, ma'am.
>> Good evening, K. McAdams. Um, I'm just
have a question. Is this land, this 34
acres contingent to item number 17,
um, Round Top Road? Is it right next to
that one?
>> Yes, ma'am. I believe that's the
followup, um, ordinance for the after
the public hearing.
>> So, this land that we're talking about
right now is contingent to that land.
>> Contingent
>> meaning right next to it.
>> No, continuous.
>> I'm sorry. Contiguous.
>> It's contiguous to the North Range
Business Park. Okay. and the land on
number 17 is the land that we're doing
the public hearing on today.
>> Right. But I'm wondering if it's next to
it. What I'm worried about is the the
keyhole idea. You start annexing land
and there's just a little bit of chunk
that's right next to Cheyenne that you
just bring in all these large acres. I'm
just here to say this. It happened when
Mayor Spiker to me next door at Thomas
Heights and there were many, many
promises. Now, I don't ever want to hear
from this community ever again that
somehow something slipped by and oh,
we're sorry and we fixed it because when
it gets fixed to the tune of $350,000
up by Thomas Heights, it's not out of
you guys' pockets. It's out of these
guys' pockets, the taxpayers. And I
really, really want people to be aware
of these annexations and they're done
legitimately.
So, I'm going to be on this all night
long. So, please let's think about this.
Thank you.
>> And ma'am, I would remind you one thing,
and that is it's not the city who's
annexing the property. It's Well, I
guess we are, but it's the owner who
asked for it, not the city who asked for
it. Right.
>> You're calling.
>> Well, then we'll talk about owner rights
because I'm right next to the city that
people jumped zones and so we have trash
constantly blowing on our place. That's
not conducive to my lifestyle. So, I'm
very worried about these these people,
our citizens, and their rights, too. So,
when we talk about owner's rights, if I
don't want to get annexed, I'll be up
here again and saying I have an owner's
right not to go into the city. I
guarantee it. So, let's just really play
fair here.
>> Thank you, ma'am. Mayor
>> Collins. Yes. Do we know what ward uh
Miss McAdams is from?
>> She's not in the city.
>> Okay. And just a reminder, mayor, that
we um as a council, all are taxpayers as
well.
Jimmy, did you want to speak?
>> Evening, mayor. Jimmy Churro, Ward One
candidate. I would recommend not
annexing it. Even the own your own
attorney has said that you may annex and
it seems to piggyback on what she was
saying earlier. It's like a it's it's
like a cookie cutter just because they
meet the requirement. There's nobody
there. What is the benefit of a parking
lot? How is that improving the safety
and and welfare with water and sewer on
the parking lot? It It's not. Remember
what I told you about several months
ago? We talked about Sim City.
Appreciate Tom taking care of Frontier
Days and getting the sidewalks all
repaired on Lincoln and uh Central, but
you're you're expanding out too far. And
just because they want to make it
continuous with another part of the
business park and we all know who it's
for, I recommend now on this annexation.
Thank you.
>> We're trying to uh have a public hearing
on a 34.4 acre piece of land contiguous
to the North Range Business Park.
Anybody else want to speak to this?
>> I see you, Jennifer. We'll get there.
Yes, ma'am. Please come forward.
>> Welcome.
>> Hi.
>> You need to push the button. Turn the
microphone on.
>> Okay.
>> And tell us your name and what word you
live in.
>> Donna Dundan. Word one.
>> Welcome.
>> Um, my question tonight,
um, I was inspired by your speech
earlier about the 250ear celebration.
You said you want to leave Cheyenne for
the future generations to come. So, I
was wondering when I look at this
agenda, do we have a total of acreage or
square area of land surrounding the city
that you all want to annex tonight?
Can you tell me how much this
encompasses around Cheyenne and into the
county?
>> I didn't add them up, but we have a
3,400 acre annexation. We have this one.
So, it's just I think just short of
4,000 acres.
>> All of
>> And that's including all items from 7
all the way through 17 18
>> I think. So, everything that's either on
a public hearing in process or going
into the process.
>> Okay.
Okay. Thank you very much
>> for being here this evening. Anyone else
on this public hearing?
All right. Hearing none. The purpose of
the public hearing has been met and
we'll go on to the next item.
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Oh, I apologize, Jennifer. You did say
that. I apologize.
>> I'm sorry.
>> Go ahead. Who is it?
>> Go ahead. I'll let you speak.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Okay.
>> Hang on a second. We got a guy on the
phone.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you, Mr. Miller.
Um
U mayor, members of the city council for
the permanent administrative record,
Charles Miller,
this public hearing is supposed to
determine whether the annexation
conditions required by Wyoming statute
are satisfied.
Um this is for a parking lot. Is that
what you guys said?
It's for a lay down yard and uh um
parking and other facilities. Yes.
>> Okay. Um so
and and I'm going to continue to try to
get this point through this evening, but
the is is your guys' attorney present?
>> Yes.
Um, is there any way that uh he you guys
might be able to state for the record
the difference between a legislative act
and a quasi judicial act? Uh, in terms
of um this annexation
uh and and what uh status that you guys
are are acting under during this this
annexation. And I'm [clears throat]
going to be asking the same thing for
the for the reasonzoning as well.
Mr. Brody, do you have a comment?
>> Uh, Mr. Mayor, I would just say that our
office has done the research to look
into um legislative versus quasi
judicial when a city council is acting.
Case law is pretty clearly um shows that
annexation, zonings are legislative
decisions made by the city council.
That's pretty much all I want to comment
about that.
>> Mr.
Um, and uh, members of the city council,
are are you guys aware of of what I'm
talking about or or what your attorney's
talking about? Is is this something that
you guys are already familiarized with?
>> Go ahead and continue. Mr.
I'm I'm just wondering if if if I could
get like an answer from the council
members in terms of if they are uh um
aware of the difference between
legislative acts and u quasi judicial
acts in terms of how you guys uh have to
conduct your your uh hearings.
>> Mr. Miller, we've been informed by our
attorney that this is a legislative act
and we're I think addressing it that
way.
>> And then maybe could could you guys
describe what the difference is? uh
because I I have kind of an issue uh
with my research anyways. Uh I've been
led to uh to to believe that the uh
annexation
may be uh a legislative
uh act if it is um
if but the but the reasoning
uh especially and maybe let me just pull
up I don't know how much time I have
left here but uh let me see here let me
just pull up something really quick.
>> Mr. Mayor
Uh
I'm going to go ahead and and catch you
guys on the uh on the resoning for this
one, but uh but definitely if if I could
get some time,
>> Mr. Miller, thank you,
>> sir.
>> Hello. My name is Brian Brian Pixley. I
live off of uh Treyway Trail and Round
Top in uh Heavy Jack area. And uh I'm
totally against this guys, you know. I I
said once, twice, I'm against this
annexations, you know, because it's like
I I have a heart condition and and I've
been through I have anxiety and all that
and everything else. And then it's like
uh a couple days ago, you get you talk
about the water, the energy and all
that. Uh matter of fact, uh over by the
FB Warren Air Force Base, the their
transformer blew and so how is that
accommodating to the uh electricity,
water and all that, you know? So I I'm
totally against this and and seems like
you guys are listening to your
powerpoints and all that other sales
pitches, you know. I don't want it, you
know. I'm put against it. So I spoken
and this is my final tone. So I spoke.
So, um, no.
>> Thank you for being here.
All right. Anybody else? Oh, thank you,
ma'am. I didn't see you over there.
>> I'm Janet Tolman. I'm in Ward three.
>> Welcome.
>> And, um,
how much acreage is Cheyenne,
>> Connor? Do you know the number? I know
the square miles, but
>> I hear 20,000 acres is what I'm I just
heard.
>> They googled 20,000.
>> Okay.
So, you're looking at 4,000 being added
on.
Okay.
um
from the year 2000. Do you have any idea
how much was added on
>> in the last 20 years?
>> I think that number is around 25%.
>> Okay.
Um was that mostly for business or was
that mostly for residential? Um, it's
been a little bit of both actually. You
know, we've had like the big big uh
residential like sweet grass that came
into the city limits. We've had uh uh a
number of data center or business park
uh developments that have happened. Uh
it's a little bit of both.
>> Saddle Ridge.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Saddle Ridge is a big one, you
know, that's on the east part of town.
Whitney Whitney Ranch is a big
residential area that's been growing uh
on that part of town. the area behind
the mall that will be developed into uh
there's over a thousand acres there that
was just recently annexed into the city
that will become uh both commercial and
residential um where the apartment
buildings are being built currently.
It's been it's been a mixture of both.
>> Okay. And this land that's going to be
annexed in around 4,000 acres, is that
going to be both residential and
business or mostly business?
>> I think most of the land that that I see
on here is mostly going to be uh
business, commercial, industrial
property, mostly in business parks.
>> Okay. My concern is that many of the
people living on the outskirts of town
are there for because they like the wide
open spaces,
but it's encroaching on their property
in many of these areas. Maybe not
specifically this one, but what's to say
that
a ranch next door to one of the
properties that wants to be annexed may
have no choice in the future but to be
annexed because
there's a business park right next to it
or there's a business next to it. So,
have you looked into the planning in the
future of
how much it's going to cost taxpayers
to add on this extra
because I've, you know, doing research
and looking at when
a city grows and expands, usually the
expenses are greater. That's why a lot
of people live here in Cheyenne. Um, you
know, that's why I ret decided to retire
in Cheyenne. But is it going to be I
mean how would I say would I be able to
afford to live here after these
businesses come in?
>> Ma'am your time is up but just to
quickly answer your question you know
that is definitely the hope right that
the businesses that we're bringing are
going to bring above average wages.
They'll they'll uh they'll pay more than
maybe uh a regular business where an
average business would pay in in
revenue. that will help um the city be
able to afford our cost of living and
maybe improve the quality of life um so
that it'll be more enjoyable for all of
us. I mean, I think that's the hope for
at least this governing body.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Mr. White, welcome.
>> How you doing?
>> It's good to see you again.
>> Yeah, I got a question here. You know,
like that property you're talking about
that 34.46 46 acres and I was reading on
here by that statue 15402.
Did you guys send out letters to the
people that live next to that area
>> because it says right here, you know,
signs town less than 20 business days.
You're supposed to send a letter to the
people that are living around that area
to so they know that they're going to be
anized. Did you do that,
>> Mr. White? They said earlier um that
they did that. Not only did they do that
to everybody that lives in the area, but
also 300 ft around the area, uh, they
sent a letter to everyone within that
radius according to state statute.
>> Okay. I just wondering, I'm just
checking.
>> Yep.
>> Okay. That's all I got to say for right
now.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> It's good to see you again. Anybody
else?
>> All right. The purpose of the public
hearing has been met and we'll move on
to the next item.
Number eight, ordinance, third reading,
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, land located south of Charles
Street, east of Wanandi Avenue and west
of McKinley Avenue.
>> All right. This is an owner initiated or
owner asked for annexation of 2.69 acres
that will become a residential
development. Is there anybody in the
audience wants to speak to this uh
annexation on third reading?
>> All right, Dr. Aldridge, may I have a
motion, please?
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Been seconded by Dr. Emmens. Any
questions or comments for members of the
governing body?
>> Hearing none. Madam clerk, would you
take the vote?
>> Mr. Esel,
>> I.
>> Mr. Lebornne,
>> Mr. Moody,
>> I.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> hi.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> Dr. Emma,
>> yes. Your annexation is approved on
third and final reading.
>> Number nine, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of AR agricultural
residential for land annex to the city
of Cheyenne located south of Charles
Street, east of Wanandi Avenue and west
of McKinley Avenue.
>> All right. When you annex a piece of
property, you have to give it a city
zone. And the way we do that to start
with is we try to establish whatever the
zone is that was closest to what it was
in the county. And uh so in this
situation that would be agricultural
residential and we'll go out to the
audience if anybody wants to talk about
the city's uh establishment of AR as his
own district.
Mr. Miller
>> Mr. Miller you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you, Mr. Miller.
[clears throat] Mayor Collins, members
of the city council, Charles Miller.
Um, this and so this is just for one
particular owner. Is that correct?
>> I believe so.
>> Oh, okay. Um, so this so this is a uh a
sightspecific reasoning for one
particular owner
um using a specific legal description.
Is is that safe to say that that is
true?
>> I believe so.
>> Um is uh that's something that your
attorney might be able to verify
officially.
>> Mr. Mayor, John Brody, city attorney. Um
I would say that the item on the agenda
speaks for itself and Mr. Miller can
take what he wants from it.
>> Well, um, basically what the reason I'm
asking is, um, because a sightspecific
reasoning for a named individual,
property owner using a specific legal
description is the textbook definition
of a quasi judicial act. In this
capacity, you do not have maximum
political discretion. You are strictly
constrained by facts and statutes and
your actions are subject to denovo
judicial scrutiny under Wyoming statute
section 163114C.
Um the the controlling authority here is
found in Wyoming Supreme Court president
specifically the standard established in
P3D158.
The court formally held that when a
Cheyenne municipal board makes sightsp
specific determinations, it is acting in
a quasi judicial capacity under the
Wyoming Administrative Procedure Act. Uh
the court further mandated that quasi
judicial decisions made by Cheyenne
municipal bodies must include separately
stated findings of fact and conclusions
of law. This is not an optional theory.
It is the legally settled standard under
Wyoming law as applied to the city of
Cheyenne itself. If this council fails
to explicitly state its findings of fact
and conclusions of law on the permanent
record tonight, it is acting outside its
legal authority. Every procedural
failure committed by this body while
acting as a quasi quasi judicial
administrative tribunal is reviewable
and reversible by a district court under
Wyoming statute section 163114C.
I urge you to fulfill your mandatory
obligations under the law.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes, ma'am. Welcome.
>> Hey, McAdams. I'm just trying to clarify
this zone um AR.
What is next to this property? Just
multi-residential.
Do does anybody know what that is next
to it?
Nobody.
I guess the reason I'm asking is when
again I have to only refer to Thomas
Heights and what has happened because
somebody wanted to be placated during
Thomas Heights a piece of property went
in as AR. Now that could mean horses,
pigs, cows, whatever you want on that
property. So, I don't have a problem
with the AR, but you just have to be
careful of the jumping of zones and very
very nervous about all this land getting
annexed without really proper
consideration as to what exactly happens
to city residents versus county.
>> Ma'am, the area to the north of it looks
like it's a normal I would say urban
residential.
>> Okay. Okay.
>> It looks to me like on the on the east
and the west of this uh across McKinley
and Winandi looks to me like maybe a 5
acre type residential. Uh
>> is that going to be city that five
acres? Do you know?
>> No, I they look to me like they're in
the county, but um I don't have that
>> and
>> I can tell you here.
>> And is I guess
>> south, east, and west are in the county.
The subject site is in the county now.
North is uh in the city and it's it's a
medium density residential. Okay. So, I
assume then the person who's getting
this annexed really wants to come into
the city.
>> I would guess if you ask for annexation,
you want to come in the city.
>> Yeah. But there's been properties here
in this city that people haven't wanted.
So, I'm just checking.
>> Yep.
>> Okay. Thank you,
>> Mr. Nicely.
>> David Nicely. 200 Wershide. Still not a
resident of the city. Um,
our Declaration of Independence, which
we celebrated at the 250th anniversary,
asserts that all just power u for
government is derived from the consent
of the governed.
What we're seeing here tonight is
this city council has lost the trust of
the people
and because of that every action of the
city will be scrutinized.
Every action will be considered
everything will be mistrusted.
Um, so I rise to urge you to vote no on
all annexation matters because of that
the city administration has no just
power because it's lost the consent of
the governed and that this council
pursue
rebuilding that trust.
Miss Madrid has asked you for records
related to annexations and has been told
that it will cost an exorbitant amount
of money because the records must be
redacted. What is it that's in the
records that needs to be redacted? And
how do we know that the things that are
left out were correctly left out? I urge
you to give her the record, she asks
without redaction. Mr. Exie Brown has
asked for records. He's been told that
it will cost an exorbitant amount. I've
told him that as a future member of the
legislature, he should vote no on all
requests from the city of Cheyenne for
money because to do due diligence to
give you the money, he has to have the
records. So, you've lost the consent of
the government. Get it back. stop doing
anything besides a consent an agenda
that is a caretaker government and ask
for the resignation of the people that
are holding this trust back. We should
have been told about the meta
contamination. The fact that we are not
urg leads me to say no and to speak in
opposition to every annexation
and I will be happily rallying the
people of Cheyenne to do that until you
have the consent of the governed again.
That's what the declaration was about.
Whenever the King John lost the consent
of the English people, we got armies and
we got Magna Carta.
When King Charles I lost the consent of
the English people, we got a trial for
tyranny and the execution of the king.
Whenever King George III lost the
consent of the people, we got the
American Revolution.
And what the declaration says is in
extreme times is a time for extreme
action.
You can say no. You can act. You can do
dump tea. It's justified. Dump tea.
Anybody else?
[applause]
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> what's that?
>> Order, please.
>> Anybody else want to speak? Sir,
welcome.
Uh, Dakota Titus, Ward One. Um, through
you, Mr. Mayor. I I think that there's a
disconnect um between our council and
our and our people right now. Um,
the issue isn't who wants the
annexations. The issue is things that
you've brought up in the past. um such
as when we spoke about annexing WFresh,
you were doing those under under the the
guise of the amount of city land that's
around it, right? So So if we're going
to allow annexation in other parts of
our community, is that going to create
more pockets and give you more
opportunity to take more land?
My my my second thing here,
sorry I'm frustrated.
My second thing here is
this council has has lost the confidence
of its people 100%. They have a
predisposition
of
not voting and not doing the things that
[clears throat] have been made very
clear by their constituents that we want
or that we need. you guys kind of go by
your own playbook
um and and don't really listen to your
people. And I think that's the problem.
I don't think the problem is annexing a
parking lot. I think the problem is what
you might choose to do with that later.
I'm going to leave that be because
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Good evening. My name is Linda Camp. I
live in Rolling Hills on the other side
of
>> Miss Campy, if I could get you to pull
that microphone down and talk into it so
people can hear you. Thank you so much.
>> Is this better?
>> It's so much better. Thank you.
>> Um, obviously I'm a county resident and
I don't know any of you people because I
can't vote for you, but you are sitting
here making decisions about property
that is right next door to me. It
affects my water. It affects everything
about that area out there. And you may
have lost the confidence of the city of
Cheyenne. I don't know. But certainly
the county residents don't have any say
in this to you. You're not interested in
it. And it's very frustrating. And from
listening to the questions and answers,
not that there's been many answers, but
um it seems like you, some of you don't
seem to be really aware of what actually
you're doing, what you're annexing, what
you're zoning, what it's going to be
used for, and how it affects the rest of
the citizens. And that's my opinion. And
oh, by the way, you're anxious to build
parking lots out next door to me and
data centers, but there's not a grocery
store close to me within 10 miles.
Safeway, Albert, all those are clear
over there. And I have to drive all the
way over there. Why can't you
accommodate some businesses that are
useful to the people that live west of
Cheyenne? That's all I have.
Anyone else? May
>> Collins.
>> Yes.
>> Uh, Mayor Collins, I just wanted to
remind everyone that we the property
we're talking about right now is south
of Charles Street, east of Winandi and
west of McKinley Avenue. Um, so I don't
believe this is um I believe that this
is basically on the east side of town
rather than out towards Rolling Hills.
So
>> it is. Anyone else want to speak on this
uh this zone change for the 2.69
establishing zone for 2.69 acres? Yes,
ma'am.
>> Yes. My name is Janet Tolman and I live
in Ward 3. And even though these
properties aren't
next to mine or close to mine, I still
have a concern just like the others have
expressed that okay, we're we're just
zoning this property in to the city.
we're just making it into agriculture.
What I've seen by the few meetings that
I've been to is that first we zone it
into the city as agricultural, then we
zone it in as business and so and then
that's that can be all done in one
meeting and it's I don't know I just
feel like it's too quick of a process. I
know that people have asked for a
moratorum so that they could have an
opportunity to look more into the
planning
and I think if I were doing some sort of
planning if I was a city manager and I
I'd want to get everybody in Cheyenne on
board
and I would like like not just a
hodgepodge. Okay, we're doing this here
and we're doing this there. We're doing
that there. Oh, great. Yeah, we're
providing jobs here. We're providing
jobs there, you know, but in reality,
looking at it as a city that we want to
be proud of, it's a city that we feel
we're a part of. It's a city that we
feel we're part of the planning of and
not just a city, well, oh, okay, well,
that got torn down. Oh, well, that's
being built in. but not really having a
say so or not really being aware of all
that's involved until it actually
happens. Um my concern once again is the
water and the electricity that will be
involved and it may not be involved in a
parking lot but then who's to say then
once again going for the other areas to
annex into the city to make it a bigger
city.
>> Ma'am, I'll remind you this is for two
2.6 six acres to build some houses on.
Are you concerned about the water and
electricity for that?
>> No, I'm just concerned about
>> just as a general statement.
>> This is just a general this is what I'm
just trying to and and maybe I'm not
always real clear at what I'm wanting to
know, but when you're asking for the
annexation, we don't know
what the plan is for it completely. We
don't know who the owner is, who is
going to be developing the property
um and how it is going to affect the
community around it.
You know, we're just voting for, oh,
we're zoning for this, we're zoning for
that, and I'm sitting here, okay, I have
no idea, you know, what we're doing. And
I
and I don't know just
as somebody who's not really voiced in
lawyer procedures or city and council
procedures and stuff, it would just be
nice, like Mr. Wolf said, if there's
more clarification on what's being voted
for.
>> Thank you, ma'am. Miss Madrid,
[clears throat]
>> Heather Madre, Ward One. Um, just just
want to say that inval trying to
invalidate people's concerns by arguing
that no one complains about houses or no
one complains about golf courses um is
kind of it's a fallacy. It's a bad
argument. Um, just because golf courses
use
a disgusting amount of water doesn't
mean that the impact of all the other
water usage is nothing. Um, and it
doesn't mean that people can't still
come up and share their concerns about
what these properties are being used
for. Um, housing takes a lot of water,
yes, but we're people live there. It's
not a dead zone like a parking lot or
who knows what's going to be on this
property. So, I just don't think that
invalidating concerns with fallacies is
helping to restore the trust that Mr.
Nisley is talking about. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Who do you have?
>> Uh, Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Has already spoken on this issue.
>> Shar, can you hear me?
>> Has he already spoken on this issue?
>> Yeah, we can hear you.
Um
the uh Mayor Collins, members of the
city council, Charles Miller for the
administrative record. Um I'm speaking
on the ordinance on third reading to
amend the official zoning map to AR
agricultural residential for the 2.69
acres located south of Charles Street
east of Winandi Avenue and west of
McKinley Avenue. Is is that am I in the
correct item here?
>> You are, sir.
>> Okay. While this owner initiated
annexation for a residential property
may seem like a routine administrative
housekeeping item, I'm stepping to the
microphone to lock in a critical legal
precedent before you vote. I need this
governing body and specifically the city
attorney to acknowledge exactly what
type of action is taking place here.
This is a sight specific reasoning for a
named individual property owner
utilizing a specific legal description.
Let the permanent record reflect that
this is the textbook definition of a
quasi judicial act. When you act in a
quasi judicial capacity, you do not have
the maximum political discretion that
you enjoy during purely legislative
actions. You are strictly constrained by
facts. You are bound by statutory
criteria and your actions are subject to
denovo judicial scrutiny under Wyoming
statute. A quasi judicial decision
legally requires you to produce
separately stated findings of fact. The
reason I am placing this constructive
notice on the record for a 2.6 acre
residential parcel is because of what is
coming next. If this governing body
operates under the false legally fatal
assumption that spite sight specific
reasonzonings are purely legislative
acts, you are establishing a terminal
precedent. If you apply a flawed
legislative shield to the to this 2.6
acre parcel, you will inevitably apply
that same flawed shield to the thousands
of acres of business park resonings tied
to the Highlands project later on
tonight's agenda. You cannot have it
both ways. Sight specific zoning is
quasi judicial. If you fail to
acknowledge this standard and failed to
produce the required findings of fact,
you are intentionally rendering your
zoning decisions tonight structurally
void and fully reversible upon appeal.
The standard you are apply you apply to
this 2.6 acre vote will be cited in the
appellet record for the 30,000 acre
votes. Govern yourselves accordingly.
>> Kathy Ciganiano, um I'm going to unmute
you.
You can go ahead,
>> Kathy. Are you there?
>> Hello. Good evening. Um, I just wanted I
guess clarification for sure. This um
2.69 acres is being zoned agricultural
residential. Is that correct?
>> Yes, ma'am. That's the underlying zone
that's already in the county. And so
when we bring a property in, what we do
is we give it the the the closest zone
in the city that matches what it was in
the county when we annexed it into the
city. and that is agricultural
residential.
>> Perfect. So, I was just curious um is
there a guarantee that homes will be
built here? Because it's my
understanding that the property over off
of College by LC was also zoned for
residential but is now being considered
for data center. And I know while 2.69
69 is obviously too small for a data
center. I'm just curious, can it be
guaranteed that these will be homes
built or will something later down the
line be reszoned to make it something
different?
>> Kathy, I have no idea what the future u
owner of the property or future
governing body would do. Right now it's
agricultural. If they want to change the
use from agricultural residential, they
would have to come back through a public
process and everybody in the community
would have an opportunity to discuss
that.
>> Okay. Okay, thank you so much.
>> Yep.
Anybody else?
>> I have Chris Kamargo. You should be able
to unmute yourself.
>> Chris, welcome
Chris.
He can unmute himself whenever he's
ready.
>> Chris, can you unmute yourself, please?
>> All right, let's move on. Anybody else
in the audience or online?
All right, hearing none, we're going to
go to Dr. Aldridge for a motion.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second. [clears throat]
>> Seconded by Dr. Emmens.
>> Comments from members of the governing
body on the uh establishment of this
zone district.
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you. Um I
just wanted to address Mr. Miller's
issue about the quasi judicial versus
legislative.
Several months ago in a meeting I asked
um Mr. Miller about his professional
background and if he was an attorney and
he stated that no he is not an attorney.
So I think the responsible thing at this
point is to follow the advice given by
our licensed educated attorney. Um so I
just wanted to make that point to Mr.
Miller that I think that's why we're all
following the the um concept that this
is a legislative function that has been
vetted through our attorney. Um so just
wanted to say that.
>> Thank you. Anybody else in the governing
body?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Escoel.
>> So I believe in Wyoming property rights
laws that kind of is the threshold the
top of the line law. So when an owner
annexed property comes to us,
it's uh his right to do it when he wants
to do with his property. That's what I
believe. But if someone came to you and
offered you four times the amount of
money for your house, would you want us
to say no, you can't do that?
I don't think you would.
Anyone else in the governing body? All
right, Madam Clerk, would you take the
vote, please?
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Esel,
>> hi.
>> Mr. Lebornne,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> hi.
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> hi.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> The established zone district is
approved unanimously on third and final
reading. Number 10, ordinance, third
reading, annexing to the city of
Cheyenne, Wyoming, land northwest of the
intersection of Clear Creek Parkway and
Ganet Peak Drive.
>> All right, we have before us another
owner initiated annexation of 26.29
acres in the Swan Ranch Business Park
and we'll go out to the audience. Mr.
Nicely,
>> it seems David Nicely 200 Walters still
not a member of the city. Um, it seems
that you're all amendable to answering
questions tonight. Um, thank you for
that. Um, goes a long way to
reestablishing trust.
Um, Mr. Craves, do you believe my
property rights uh trump um other
matters and have any significance with
respect to whether my property should be
annexed?
>> Mr. We've given you quite a bit of uude
>> latitude today already. What were I
talking about?
>> You've given me no latitude. I have
spoken less than three minutes. I've
spoken to the topic of order.
>> This is with respect to the topic.
>> Point of order, [snorts]
>> Mr. It's about the
>> I'm not out of order. What's your point
of order?
>> Your point of My point of order is that
you're not talking about the topic that
we're on. You're talking about your
grievance, which I appreciate. And
you've shared with us at least twice
now. So, it would be great for the rest
of the people. I'll reserve the balance
of my time and answer your point of
order.
>> Agreements, please.
>> I'll be happy to answer the point of
order.
>> Mr. Nicely,
>> give me a chance to answer the point of
order.
>> That that's the point of order directed
to me, not you, sir. Okay. And what we
have before us right now is the
annexation of 26.29 acres. And we're
looking for comments about that
annexation. We'd love to hear your
comments on that annexation.
>> Absolutely. Absolutely.
Um,
property rights are significant. If the
property rights of a requesttor for
annexation are significant in
establishing or a reason for giving
annexation,
then the denial of a desire for
annexation should be determinative. If
it's determinative in one, it should be
determinative in the other. You've lost
the trust of the city because at least
in part of the way you've treated our
farm. Um, you've lost the trust of the
city. You continue to act in ways that
destroy the trust in the city because
you are unwilling to plan
and and I when we first met with the
city about annexation, the city planner
who's here tonight told us that the city
doesn't plan. It's entirely reactive.
City planning has created a situation of
ex of a boom by prompting and promoting
growth that it wasn't ready for that
it's not still not ready to for all ex
annexations should be stopped until the
trust of the city is restored until the
mayor and his planning director are
replaced and until such time as we can
establish a plan to deal with the growth
that we already have.
um property rights are significant,
but you've invited the public to come in
and talk about these matters because
you've used public funds to cause this
boom that's happening. So
I caucused for Ron Paul in 2012. I'm as
layer as they come.
>> Mr. Nyley, thank you. Your time's up.
Thank you.
>> And you used a significant amount of my
time.
Somebody else on the uh annexation. Yes,
ma'am.
>> Heather Madrid, Ward One. Um,
>> as far as this annexation, um, I can see
and others can see this gradual piecing
together of a business park exactly for
what it is, even though it has not been
publicly stated and maybe isn't even
planned to be a data center at this
time. The fact that it is going to be a
business park means that if and when
that does happen,
um it will be an administrative decision
and
we the public won't get to know about it
and probably most of you won't even know
about it. Um there will be no oversight
and this decision will mostly be most
likely be made by Cheyenne Leadeds. Um
for that reason, I oppose this
annexation. I have internally opposed
this particular ordinance every time it
has come up, but I can't fight every
battle. Um, nor do I find it to be a
good strategy to oppose every single
thing this council does, even if I can
find inconsequential flaws. Um,
regarding property rights,
to answer your question, yeah, if
somebody tried to sell me or buy my
house for four times what it's worth, I
would do that and that is my right.
That's a real estate decision. That
wouldn't be happening before the
council. That would be happening in a
real estate office. So, there's the kind
of stark difference between property
rights and public processes.
>> Jimmy, welcome back.
>> Jimmy Cheryl, candidate for Ward One.
I'm not against the property rights of
folks, but you got to consider the folks
that are around these larger
annexations.
Uh, in the interest of time and and just
play devil's advocate, I know you guys
are going to vote on it already. Let's
move on. Vote on it so we can get on to
13 and 14. I don't want to be here till
midnight again like the last time.
That's it.
>> Sir,
welcome back.
>> I reorganized a little bit because I'm
trying not to be frustrated. I I I think
a worry with with a lot of these
annexations is and it has been brought
up tonight um and you even acknowledged,
Mr. Mayor, that the city grew by 25%
roughly in the last 20 years. And I just
would like everybody in the room to
acknowledge that you're trying to grow
the city by another 25% in a single
meeting. Um and I think that is what's
raised a lot of concerns from people
around here. Um, I I I do not believe
through you, Mr. Mayor, that
that there's a a that the majority of
the council does have our constituents
best interests at heart. I mean, we sat
here and were told that we cannot be
trusted by city council members in a
meeting. That happened.
Councilmen
continuously sit and shake their heads
when people are trying to convey
[clears throat] their messages and and
voice their concerns. And I believe,
sir, that that's disrespectful. Your
city attorney tonight showed an
unwillingness to give a straight answer
and told somebody to take it as he will.
I that is astonishing to me. That is
absolutely astonishing to me. And it it
is obvious that annexation is a danger
to the property rights of the people
around those properties regardless of
how the property owners of those
specific properties feel. And you guys
have made it a point time and time and
time again to t your statutes about how
you can encompass other properties
around these once you get these in your
clutches.
And and I think that's what people are
concerned about. I don't think that
people are concerned about parking lots.
I don't think that people are concerned
about farmland. I think people are
concerned about you guys' lack of
willingness
to actually govern your constituents the
way that they have given you consent to
govern them. And I will uh I'll leave it
at that.
>> Jennifer, do you have someone?
>> Yep. Kathy Sigaliano, you can go ahead.
>> Hello. Good evening again. Um, I'm just
curious regarding this 26 point I guess
29 acres. I'm not positive. Um, have any
NDAs been signed in regards to this
property as to what kind of businesses
are interested in it or have any been
suggested to be signed in regards to
this annexation of this property?
>> Kathy, are you asking if any member of
this governing body has signed an NDA? I
I don't know. I don't know about any of
the u the the private individuals that
own the property or are talking with
businesses. I can assure you no one on
this governing body has signed an NDA.
>> Okay, great. Um, also I guess in regards
to annexation and property rights, um,
as Councilman Escoel talked about, um,
I'm just curious, how do you pick whose
property rights have precedent over each
other? because you're talking about
property rights of the people who are
asking to be annexed, but as we just
heard the last gentleman speak, you're
ignoring the property rights of the
people who surround these annexations.
So, I'm just curious who takes precedent
when you're determining whose property
rights are greater than each others.
>> Mr. Leiano, I think the people who own
the property around this are are either
the same or business partners of the
land that's being annexed. So, in this
situation, I don't know that there is a
uh a conflict of any kind.
>> Well, I'm not talking about just this
property. I mean, I'm talking about his
comment in general because he made it a
general statement. So, that's what I was
kind of asking.
>> Understood.
>> Thank you.
>> Anyone else?
>> Jennifer.
>> Um, I'm gonna go back to Chris Kamargo.
You should be able to unmute yourself.
Chris, are you there?
>> Can you guys hear me?
>> We sure can, sir.
>> Alrighty, sounds good. Uh, Christopher
Kamargo, Ward Two. Uh, just a couple
questions that I am curious about.
Um,
all these annex properties, who is going
to be paying for all the added
infrastructure that needs to go into
them? You know, the water, the the city
water, the city sewers. I mean, who does
that expense fall on? Is it going to
fall on the c us taxpayers?
>> Mr. Kamargo, I can answer that question
for you. The way the city does
development is the developer pays for
the infrastructure and then the taxes or
the fees we get from those folks help
maintain that infrastructure once it's
built.
>> Okay. And then the second question is
um with all this added infrastructure, I
mean where are we going? Is the city
gonna um update the roads, the storm
water preventions?
Because I mean there's a lot of there's
a lot of infrastructure that goes up in
Cheyenne where the roads storm waters
have not been updated. And I I uh give
an example of uh along Hilltop Avenue to
Plains View Avenue. It still floods
there non-stop
and there's been no added uh storm water
or additional road maintenance from all
the added infrastructure up on the hill
there. So I mean I mean I mean we need
to start thinking about this instead of
just adding
uh building after building after
building. I mean what what are we doing
to on our end to upkeep it? I would just
tell you if you look at the end of our
agenda today, you're going to see over
almost $5 million just in road
maintenance contracts that are going to
be approved tonight uh to do exactly
what you're asking for, sir. We
recognize that uh our 370 mi of roads is
a lot and we're trying to get to at
least 10% of them every year for major
maintenance. So, your points well taken.
>> That's all I got. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Yes, ma'am. Welcome.
>> Hi, Stacy Leech. I am W. Just to
clarify, when you said there were no
NDAs signed by this board, can you tell
me if Leads signed an NDA for this
property?
>> I have no idea. I'm not a I don't know.
>> I'm not
>> Are you not a member of leads?
>> I am, but I don't know if they signed an
NDA or not, but Betsie's right here.
>> I'll take that as a
>> She's She's coming.
>> You're going to take that as what,
Stacy?
>> Probably.
>> No, no. We No, there's been no NDA.
Would you identify yourself for the
record?
>> Mr. Mayor, um Betsy Hail, CEO of
Cheyenne Leads. I live at 17503 Anonal
Loop Cheyenne. Um there have been no
NDAs executed for this project.
>> Thank you.
>> Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
Um members of the council, Charles
Miller for the permanent administrative
record. I'm This is item number 10,
correct?
>> Yes, sir, it is.
>> Um I'm speaking then on item number 10,
the third and final reading for the
annexation
of land northwest of Clear Creek
Parkway. Is that correct?
>> Yes.
>> And it's petitioned by two R
Investments.
Um, earlier this evening during the
hearing for a separate 34 acre
annexation, this governing body made a
staggering admission on the live
microphone. When pressed by a resident
for actual empirical evidence or utility
studies to justify an annexation, the
city's response was that the applicant
believes it is a benefit and that it is
simply obvious to the city. Um, the
resident correctly warned you, I think
we need more than a feeling. I'm
stepping to the microphone on item 10 to
place you on constructive notice that
you are compounding that exact statutory
failure right now. Wyoming statute
151402 requires empirical factual
determinations regarding the health,
safety, and welfare of the community
before an annexation can proceed. A
developer's desire to access city's city
utilities is not a substitute for a
municipal engineering study. By
advancing this third reading for to our
investments without putting independent
baseline utility load data on the
record, you're continuing to substitute
feelings for findings of fact. The
reason this matters right now is because
of the massive scale of what of what is
coming next on this agenda. If your
standard of evidence for item number 10
is simply that the applicant requested
it, you are establishing an arbitrary
and capricious baseline. You're
confirming that the city of Cheyenne is
running its entire annexation pipeline
on autopilot without any actual systemic
auditing of our infrastructure. You
cannot blindly pass these third readings
on a feeling. If you vote yes on item 10
without independent infrastructural
data, you are actively laying the
groundwork for the appellet reversal of
every major land use decision you make
tonight.
I demand a no vote. Thank you. Mayor
Collins, can you have him uh Charles
Miller identify his ward, please? Mr.
Miller, what ward do you live in?
I think he's gone.
>> I'm guessing we'll get to hear from Mr.
Miller yet again tonight. We'll ask him
then.
Anybody else?
Jennifer.
>> Um, Sawyer, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Good evening, Sawyer.
>> Can you guys hear me?
>> We can hear you, sir. Thank you.
>> Yeah. um here to say to vote against any
annexations for data centers because
mayor I'm pretty certain you have said
in the past that you guys have signed
and I think they're probably find it on
Cap City News or something like that
that you can't talk about developments
because of NDAs being signed but now
we're hushing up now that we got outed.
So, two things. You need to vote against
no. I also believe that the city council
needs to investigate you for corruption
and you need to resign.
Very good. All right.
Who else?
>> Anyone else?
All right.
Hearing none, we'll go to Dr. Aldrich
for a motion.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and ISO move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Emmens. All right.
Comments from members of the governing
body on the Clear Creek and Granite Peak
Drive
>> annexation.
>> Mayor.
>> Yes. And [snorts] annexations are real
estate deals because at one point or
another it was a buyer and a seller and
that's makes it a real estate deal. So
we should use property right laws. When
someone buys a property they have a
right to do with that property what they
want.
I made that comment.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Crave,
we're dealing with an annexation.
When someone applies for an annexation,
we do not necessarily know what they're
going to do with that property,
they could they will assign it an
agricultural zone or or whatever the
most equivalent is and it could sit
there for 20 years. They may want to
sell the property. They may want to
investigate
investors etc. We the annexation does
not require knowledge of what that
property is going to be developed as.
that comes as part of the zoning. If
they don't apply for zoning right after
the annexation,
uh it sits there in its current state.
So what we are told by state statute is
there's basically five questions we have
to answer during annexation.
Is it for the health, safety, and
welfare?
Typically, I think that if it's meets
all the other requirements,
having city water and sewer, city fire
department,
uh life safety codes,
um
coordinated police and fire responses,
um potentially down the road, city
zoning, which is very definitive. To me,
those are part of the health, safety,
and welfare. Then we ask ourselves uh is
this area um a natural geographic and
economic and social part of the annexing
city or town.
If it's land next to a business center,
there's a chance that it could be part
of a business center. If it's land in
the middle of a residential area, very
good chance it's going to be a
residential area. So that question to me
is is much easier than some of the other
questions. Then we get on to
is it logical and feasible?
We're not extending water out 20 miles.
You know, we're not doing those kind of
things. It is a logical and feasible
addition to the city. Um, typically
that's a relatively easy answer as well.
The next question is, is the uh the area
sought to be annexed, is it contiguous?
Is it touching? That's pretty easy to
determine as well. And does it have
access to utilities?
Those are the five questions that we ask
ourselves for annexation.
So,
we can we can all speculate about what's
going to go in
this land or that land, but from my
perspective, those are the five
questions that I have to answer. So, I
just wanted to make sure we were all on
the same page. Thank you very much.
Dr.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you, um, I
want to be clear that while I get that
there are people that are upset with our
decisions.
I I want to be clear though that we have
people who have come here, who have
emailed us, who have called us, who have
visited with us that are in favor of
these annexations. So please recognize
you are not the only people that are our
constituents.
>> Lad ladies and gentlemen please please
>> ladies and gentlemen please.
>> They have written us. They have called
us. They have visited with us. They have
been in this room. So all I'm saying is
I get that you feel very passionately on
one side of this issue or the other, but
there are people on the other side too
that we have to listen to because there
are constituents just as much as the
people in this room.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, I'll talk
about this a little later when we
actually get to the really big set of
issues uh involving the Microsoft
annexation, but I want to put to bed
this notion that this is a private
property rights issue. It is not. There
is no private property right to be
annexed.
You are conflating the interests of the
land owner with the decisions that we
the council are required to make as
president Seagrave just annunciated.
And those are in fact statutory
requirements that we have to examine and
they have to have some factual basis. So
somebody comes and says I want my land
annexed.
We our response is of course we'll annex
it. That's not the right response. The
response is are we meeting these
statutory requirements
and if they can establish that then we
decide to annex them. And the problem
that we have, the problem as Miss Madrid
and others have pointed out is that we
have now a default
policy to annex everything.
I call it and I'm going to call it when
I speak later. That's our AAA policy.
We'll annex any piece of land at any
time for any purpose.
And while Mr. President, you may talk
about you want to make sure we're all on
the same page.
We are all on the same statute.
How we apply that statute is in fact the
key questions that we have to answer.
And it's important
for these small parcels, but far less
important than what we're going to do in
a little bit when we're going to ask to
be annexed annexed 3500
acres. So, and back to the question that
was asked earlier in the evening about
how many acres we've annexed that um you
asked, ma'am. Um, so 4,000 in this
discussion tonight, but we're also
discussing the Reed parcel which has
already been annexed. That's another
Microsoft parcel for 386
acres or something like that. Um, so
we're going to do the zoning again. But
as we talk about it at this meeting and
from our perspective, the private
property rights argument I keep hearing
from my fellow council members is
absolutely unsupported in the law and I
really really don't want to hear it
announced again as the basis for a
council decision on annexation. Thank
you, Mr. Mayor.
>> Dr. for Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. I just wanted it.
It's come up several times this evening
that, you know, people would like to see
different types of businesses like a
grocery store um out west of town. I
would love to see a grocery store in the
downtown area. Um but the council
doesn't get to pick and choose what
businesses um quite honestly come to our
community. A lot of those are based on
the amount of population we have. Um I
just had somebody talk to me this last
week about they'd love to have a Trader
Joe's come. Well, that's great, but I
think we have to have a hundred thousand
people is their threshold in order to
have a Trader Joe's. Um, we have been,
you know, we hear sometimes through
planning that a particular piece of
property is going to be used for
something. And I'll give you an example,
the corner of Ridge and Persian where we
used to have a gas station in Ward 3
that was part of Albertson's. And so,
um, asked planning, you know, what's the
plan for that? And at that time they
said, "Well, we've been approached by
Dunkin Donuts." Then nothing happened
for two years. And all of a sudden, I
noticed the other day that we are going
to have a Dunkin Donuts at the corner of
Ridge in um East Persian. Um and
diagonal from that, the new Bernieian
Trust is being built. And they actually
have been pretty proactive and put up a
sign that says, "Congratulations, it's
not another car wash, coffee shop, or
you know, tire shop." Um but that was
their choice to buy that property and to
build a new bank there. Right. So,
please know that we would love I'm sure
as a council that we all have our
favorite that we would love to see come
to our community as well, but we don't
we try and work with businesses who I'm
hoping we are trying to work with
businesses who want to come to our
community. Um, once we meet their
whatever their demographic or their
parameters are for their business. Um,
but it's not something where we are
actually I have never gone out actively
and said um well that's not true. I did
talk to raising canes and say we'd love
to see you come to Cheyenne and now my
understanding is and he had told me that
they would come in the next couple years
and there's a plan to do that now but
please know that we usually are not out
approaching businesses and saying hey we
could really use you know your business
in this part of our town. Um usually
people are have an idea they're
entrepreneurs and they come to us. So um
we're just as excited as you are when we
see new businesses that want to open in
our community.
>> Mr. Escoel,
>> Mr. Mayor, through you uh to my
colleague from word one. I believe it's
both. Uh and uh the statutorial part of
it and uh the private property rights
part of it and it's just how I've always
legislated and it's always going to
legislate.
>> Anybody else on the annexation of the 20
6.29 acres?
>> Mr.
Yes, Mr. West.
>> Just real quick, I wanted to make a
comment because it's come up a few times
tonight,
normally I take great effort to um not
speak for my colleagues in anything. Um
but I for one have never signed or even
seen an NDA on any piece of item that's
ever come before council. So, just
putting it out there. And I would I
would expect that my colleagues are in
the same situation.
>> Anyone else? Madame Clerk, would you
take the vote, please?
>> Mayor Collins,
>> yes.
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> Mr. Esabel,
>> I.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> hi.
>> Mr. Moody, [clears throat]
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> hi. Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> This annexation is approved on third and
final reading with Mr. Moody voting no.
>> Number 11. Ordinance third reading
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne establishing the zoning
classification of Li Light Industrial
for land annex to the city of Cheyenne
located northwest of the intersection of
Clear Creek Parkway and Ganet Peak
Drive.
>> All right. We have again by state law we
need to give uh annex properties a city
zone. This one would be um
for what is it LI which is the closest
zone that's located um on this area in
the county and we'll ask anybody here
that would like to speak to this uh zone
change.
>> Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Can you hear me?
>> Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> Members of the council, Charles Miller,
for the permanent administrative record.
>> I'm speaking on item number 11, the
third and final reading to establish the
Alli Light Industrial Zoning
Classification for the land northwest of
Clare Creek Parkway and Ganet Peak
Drive. Is that correct?
>> Yes.
>> Excuse me.
Uh, is it that's the correct one, right?
>> Yes.
uh moments ago on item 10, you advanced
the legislative annexation of this land,
but right now in item 11, the legal
standard fundamentally changes.
Okay. And um I I uh I I would like to uh
when I'm finished here uh inquire to um
Councilman Wolf uh about his um take on
this, please. Uh, but you are executing
a sightspecific zoning map amendment for
a named applicant. I am stepping to the
microphone to place you on notice that
this is a quasi judicial act. Under
Wyoming law, you cannot rubber stamp a
quasi judicial reasonzoning simply
because an applicant requested it. You
are legally required to base your
decision on substantial evidence and to
produce separately stated findings of
fact. Yet, as we firmly established on
the live microphone earlier tonight, the
city has openly admitted it relies on
feelings rather than independent
empirical data. When pressed for
evidence, the city's official response
was, "I don't know what outside evidence
you're looking for, and it's obvious to
me, where is the specific infrastructure
load data to justify light industrial
zoning on this parcel? Where are your
separately stated findings of fact? They
do not exist in this procedural packet.
If you approve item number 11 right now
without explicitly stating your findings
of fact on the record, you are cementing
the exact procedural failure that
renders your decision structurally void.
You're applying applying a flawed
legislative shield to a quasi judicial
action. The reason this must be on the
record right now is because you are
establishing the defective legal
baseline that will contaminate the
massive business park resoning. Coming
up next, you are finalizing a zoning
entitlement on an evidentiary void. The
contradiction is logged. I demand a no
vote. Thank you.
>> Anybody else? Ma'am, did you want to
come forward?
>> We're talking about the uh
the changing of the zone for 26.69
or 69 26.29 acres.
>> Welcome.
>> Hi, I'm Danielle Cox. I don't know what
word I live in. I'm on collagen parsley,
so I'm in the city. I want to state
simply that water is life.
Water is life. And we've already had an
unfortunate spilling of bacterium that
is dangerous to people like myself, a
type 1 diabetic since I was 8 years old.
We've already had a spilling of bacteria
that was silenced. I didn't even hear
about it until last month. and it
happened in February and then you guys
refused to release the information. I
don't know that was you guys. I don't
know who it is, but you did not release
the information on the data center that
poisoned our waters and our children's
play in the my grandbaby plays in the
parks that are were being watered with
that bacterium water. Elderly people
walk there. I moved here from Colorado.
I was super happy to become a Cheyenne
resident. I loved being in this small
town. I thought my husband died here
three years ago. I thought I would never
leave this house that I love
that I have these memories with. But I
am every chance I get looking for a
place that cares about their water,
land, and people more than you have
cared about it. You may not. I wouldn't
sell my property for four times its
value because I care about people and if
it was a data sitter buying it, I would
not be selling.
[applause]
>> I am super disappointed
>> guys for just a second. I'll add some
time back for you. Please, you guys,
let's let's have some decorum. Okay, I
appreciate that you guys appreciate what
she's saying, but let's have some
decorum. Please
>> clap for your chief of staff. Surely we
can clap for her.
>> Come on, sir. Sit down. You're out of
order.
>> With your approval,
>> Mr. Nicely. Please sit down. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> You guys get the chance to decide
reszoning. And every time you go
industrial, light industrial, I know a
data center is coming and I know what
it's done to communities across our
country. They are all complaining. They
can't sell their houses. Bees are not
showing up at farms near the Do you guys
know that bees are life? Do you guys
enjoy hunting? Because there will be no
animals left.
When you kill off bees because you're
okay with the noise pollution all
because it's property rights. It's not
property rights. It's community and city
and world health and life that we here
who are upset care about. Goodbye
>> folks. I just want to say the land is
currently in the county and it's zoned
light industrial. It's coming to the
city. All we're doing is establishing
the same zone that's already in
currently in place. Just so for the
record. Yes, ma'am.
>> K. McAdams. I just really want to
emphasize here
the concern I have since I went through
this 12 years ago. The concern this lady
has, I don't have any. I've lost bees. I
had bees right next to Thomas Heights.
All that pollution shifts over to my
area. People are not careful with with
items. Also, there's a difference
between a business and a um
a corporate company coming in. Um so I
think there needs to be some concern.
And I also have this Cheyenne leads
hitching post district site. They are
asking for the six penny tax of five
million funding for infrastructure site
preparation and related public.
>> Does that have to do with
>> it has a lot to do with zoning?
>> Okay,
>> it has a lot to do with zoning and who's
paying for what?
>> See, I don't want to pay for these
business areas coming in. I don't want
the state to give incentives. If
businesses want to come in, then they
come in. So don't start annexing until
we have a moratorum, which you didn't
allow. So it has a lot to do because I
don't want to see our residents paying
for the decisions you're making here and
now to annex properties. So if I could
go on, this is infrastructure and
amenities to facilitate economic
development, community use, and tourism
related activities. I'm going to be
going through all this six penny tax. I
think you're taken from burns in the
small communities to have your
infrastructure built here from these
zoning areas. So, I think that I have a
point to stand on. Please, I'm asking
for no business zoning until we get
these data centers under under control.
Anybody else to speak to us under this
establishing of a zone?
Anyone else? All right. Dr. Aldrich, may
we have a motion, please?
>> Sir, Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of
the public services committee is to
approve on third and final reading.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Emmens. Comments from
members of the governing body on the
establishment of this zone district
hearing. None. Madam clerk, would you
take the vote, please?
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> yes. Mayor Collins,
>> yes.
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> Mr. Esel,
>> hi.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> hi.
>> This established zone district is
approved on third and final reading with
Mr. for Moody voting. No.
>> Number 12, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located north
and south of West Wall Road and west of
Interstate 25 from Light Li, Light
Industrial, CB Community Business and
PUD Planned Unit development to BP
Business Park.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience
and see if anybody wants to speak to
this change of zoning from LI to
business park.
Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> Um, don't you guys which word he's from?
>> Mr. Miller, can you tell us what word
you live in first, please?
>> Um, I I don't need to actually give you
guys that information.
>> Um, but I'm I'm wondering what Don't you
guys have a staff report before
this goes on?
>> Nope.
Okay. And this is item 12.
>> Yes.
>> Is that correct?
>> All right.
Hold on. I got echoing going on here.
>> Uh members of the council, Charles
Miller, for the record. Item number 12
is the test run for the business park
loophole. Your own staff report for this
item explicitly stated it is intended
for data center uses and allows
development with flexibility and without
further zone changes. You are taking
nearly 400 acres of industrial
development and permanently stripping it
of future public oversight. Councilman
Renie has already admitted on the record
that this BP designation allows
developers to quote unquote skirt around
the environmental requirements of the
indust industrial sighting act. Uh end
quote. If you vote yes on item 12
without generating sight specific
findings of fact, you're endorsing
regulatory evasion and finalizing a
defective zoning ordinance on the
evidentiary void. I demand a no vote.
>> Mr. Miller, if you uh read the staff
report, sir, you'll find that all of
those questions are answered. There's um
the criteria that are required um are
answered on page two, on page three, on
page four. um
and on page five. So all of those things
are before on on the record for the city
council. And sir, uh I would just share
with you also that um no one on this
governing body said that the uh uh the
business park is a loophole so that
people can get around the environmental
um requirements. Those environmental
requirements are still part of they
still have to get the same air
requirements from DEEQ, all of those
types of things. It is a um doesn't have
to go through the industrial sighting
council process, but it does not exclude
all the environmental requirements that
the Department of Environmental Quality
require. All right. Anybody else?
>> You still hear me, sir?
>> Anybody else?
>> Uh I
>> Mr. Miller,
anybody else?
I was just I was just uh going to
mention that I have uh several different
instances from uh multiple of your
council uh staff there and multiple of
your city staff. Um that that does
indicate,
you know, that that BP reszoning is is
uh is a bypass of of various uh
regulations. But I I'll
>> Mr. Miller, that's actually not true. It
could be owned business park, but unless
it's identified as an industrial park,
you still have to go through the
industrial sighting council process, but
if it's if it's identified as an
industrial park, then the industrial
sighting council process isn't there.
But it still requires all of the same um
environmental things, DEQ won't give
them an air permit unless they go
through that process. All right.
>> Is that is that a fact,
>> Mr. Miller? Yes.
>> What you had just stated?
>> Yes, it's true. Is anybody else uh able
to corroborate that like like one of
your city staff or any of the other
council members?
Um just wondering
>> you could ask chat GPT. I'm sure it
could tell you.
>> Well, I'd prefer to do it in this on the
record, you know, because it seems like
your uh your staff and your council have
varying uh opinions uh on what uh is
actually the law and what's not. So, I
was just wondering if there could be
some type of clarification there.
Thank you, Mr. Miller. Ma'am, did you
have comment?
>> My question was it says light industrial
community business
and planned unit of development. Um
what is surrounding this um particular
plot of land?
Ma'am, it's in the middle of a business
park and
um there are industrial uses, a rail
park and industrial uses completely
surrounding this.
>> Okay. So, there's no um
residential property or anything like
that that's bordering it?
>> No, ma'am. That's correct.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Anybody else on this uh
changing of the zone district?
Hearing none.
May I have a motion? Dr. Aldrich.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Cagrave. Comments from
members of the governing body on this
zone change.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Dr. Rainey,
>> in response to Mr. Miller, I did talk to
the deputy director of DEEQ because I um
wanted to ask about questions with the
industrial sighting council.
And um
industrial sighting generally looks at
impacts of a large development.
And then they will if a then they will
assess um a fee or
a monetary amount to reimburse whether
it be a county or a municipality what
some of those impacts of that
development will be.
So, and yes, if somebody goes into
a a designated business park, then the
industrial sighting council does not
look at those impacts.
And generally, we've been able to
through our staff and the board of
public utility staff and Black Hills
staff been able to require
large business developments to
um pay those impact fees upfront.
However, it does not being in a business
zone and I and I actually said this at
the last public service committee as
well.
It does not exempt them from the DEQ
permit requirements and DEEQ requires
permits for air, water, and hazardous
materials.
Any company still has to go through that
process with DEEQ and then DEQ sends it
out to 18 other agencies for comments
that for to be addressed. So, um
I just in my own defense did not say
that
that a company because it's going
through um into a designated business
park skirts around the requirements for
for the permits from DEQ. So, thank you,
Mr. Mayor.
>> Anybody else in the governing body?
>> Hearing none. Madam clerk, would you
take the vote, please?
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Hi.
>> Dr. Aldrich. [clears throat]
>> Yes.
>> Mayor Collins.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Esel.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> No.
>> Dr. Anie.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Mr. White.
>> Yes.
>> This zone change is approved on third
and final reading with Mr. Moody voting
no.
>> Number 13. Ordinance third reading.
Annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, land east of South Gley Highway
and south of the Sweetgrass subdivision.
>> All right. This is an owner initiated
annexation of 3,459.99
acres for future data center
development.
We'll go out to the audience and see if
anybody wants to speak to this
development.
It was rhetorical.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Hi, Stacy Leech. Ward one. I came here
tonight to ask you, Mr. mayor and the
city council to vote no on annexation
and the subsequent reasonzoning of even
more of Laramie County land that would
be used for data centers.
Two months ago, I stood here to speak
about the unknown health impacts of data
centers here in Cheyenne in Laramie
County. I talked about the possibility
of aerosolized bacteria and harsh
chemicals entering our water supply. As
I shared my concerns, you sat here
listening with the knowledge that it had
already happened and you said nothing.
Thursday, July 2nd, reports of an
unnamed industrial user had um disposed
of chemical laden water containing an
antibioticresistant bacteria into our
reclaimed water system, contaminating
our water holding tanks and facilities
that store water used to irrigate our
city parks and golf courses. Not until
July 9th did you, the city, officially
disclose that Meta was the industrial
user that violated our reclaimed water
system. You protected Meta.
You knew in February of this year, you
knew that a Meta data center had
compromised a highly used water system
serving parks and golf courses where
immunompromised elderly people golf.
With your authorization, Mr. Mayor, the
Board of Public Utilities shut down
Cheyenne's reclaimed water system due to
concern that this rare, untreatable, and
deadly bacteria could become airborne.
And you said nothing.
You kept that information from the
public. How many more times has this
happened?
How can we be expected to believe that
when you say this was the only time
when you have proven that you will
protect the data centers over the
public? Just let that soak in. You will
public. You know that adverse events
have already happened. You know that
noise pollution is negatively affecting
people's lives. You know that homeowners
property values are plummeting because
nobody wants to buy a house across the
street from a data center. You know that
we are in a drought and our aquifers are
being depleted.
Yet you continue to choose data centers
over the very people that you promise to
serve and protect.
And since you cannot guarantee public
health and safety, which was the number
one item that you have to um prove in
order to annex, I would like to take
this opportunity I would like you to
take this opportunity to do the right
thing and vote no on annexation.
>> Thank you.
>> Can I
ma'am?
>> Miss Leech.
>> Miss Leech,
>> I have a question, please.
>> Sure.
>> You indicated that this is this is a
result of meta I don't believe that's
accurate. Meta has not taken possession
of the property. It was, if there was
anybody involved,
>> the building of a meta data center. It's
still a data center industry that has
caused this bacteria to be in our
>> Meta did not cause this bacteria. The
>> Meta hadn't been wanting to build a data
center.
>> We're not going to have an argument
here. Let's take turns, okay? And we'll
go through me.
>> My question was it was not Meta that
that caused this incident. It was a
contractor. Is that true?
What I'm reading in the newspaper is
that it was an industrial user and then
then that was verified to be meta the
meta data center. Okay, sure maybe it
is. But like I said, if it was the
contractor, we wouldn't have had those
contractors here building this to leak
this bacteria into our water if we
weren't building a data center for meta.
If it was a
something else, a storage facility, and
it was still caused by a contractor,
>> they probably wouldn't be using the
chemicals to to degrade the bacteria.
[clears throat]
>> Okay, we'll bring I'll I'll ask BOP when
we're done. Okay,
>> that's true.
>> Thanks,
>> I didn't say she.
>> Sir, you're out of order. I just try to
make sure that we're process
>> Mr. Nicely please.
>> And representative welcome ma'am. Come
on please.
>> Thank you. Good evening mayor and
councel. My name is Anne Lucas and I
represent House District 43 in the
Wyoming legislature and the Sweetg Grass
subdivision is right there in the smack
middle of my house district. I met last
night with 25 of my constituents and we
talked for some time about their
feelings and concerns over what is
happening here. I appreciate your op the
this opportunity. I am not an attorney
for the record. I don't play one on TV,
but I am adept at reading laws and
writing laws. Just to get that out there
because it seems to be a concern. I ask
you to consider not just what this
decision means today, but what it means
20 or 30 years from now.
The decisions you make tonight are
likely irreversible. Once this land is
sold and developed, there is no going
back. And you know what? None of us are
going to be here 20 or 30 years from now
to talk about it. We might be here on
Earth, but we won't be here tonight in
this room. I understand the desire for
economic development, but good
governance requires us to ask difficult
questions before making permanent
decisions.
Have all of the long-term impacts been
fully considered? Have nearby residents
been given enough opportunity to
understand what this project can mean to
their neighborhoods and for the
character of our community? I am
especially concerned about placing
another large data center in such close
proximity to existing residential
neighborhoods. This is not the first and
I suspect it's not going to be the last.
The people who choose to build homes
there and they chose these homes in the
in the in the past deserve confidence
that their quality of life has been
carefully considered. Traffic, noise,
lighting, future expansion, unit utility
infrastructure and just overall the
cumulative effect of continued
industrial growth all deserve thoughtful
discussion. This shouldn't be instant
coffee decisions, folks. We are not
required to make fast decisions that
impact people's lives. Growth is
important, but we must be careful. My
request is simple. Don't let urgency
replace due diligence. The decision will
out this decision will outlive every one
of us. Please take whatever time is
necessary to get it right. Finally, I
ask you to remember that you were
elected to re represent people. Data
centers don't vote. these people do.
Thank you very much,
>> Mr. Mayor. Quick.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, this has uh Thank you,
Representative Lucas. Just to clarify,
was this a Sweetgrass neighborhood where
you met with your constituents?
>> Councilman Moody. It was
>> Thank you, sir. Welcome.
>> Um, good evening. My name is Ben Frius.
I'm a resident in Ward 3. Um, I've been
a resident my whole life. Um, and I know
it's not popular, but I am for the
annexation. Although I am for this
agonization, I do see concerns of my
fellow neighbors. Um, I've been in this
city council room longer than I would
have liked to over the past few months.
Um, I've talked to people that are
against data centers for data centers.
Um, and I there's not real a real
solution here. Um, but I'm going to try
and take a crack at it. Some of them are
first off the bat, I know you guys said
no NDAs, but that's no NDAs with the
planning. If businesses want to come in
here, let's be fully transparent. Let's
get the letters out to the neighbors and
everything and be good neighbors. Follow
the Wyoming values that we all live by
of if I'm putting a new fence up or a
new shed, I have to let the city know
and I have to let my neighbors know,
hey, you know, let's be good neighbors
about this. Let's not be irresponsible.
Um secondly, um why don't we use project
labor agreements so we can ensure that
the local workforce gets first shot at
these jobs? Um I know that on our job
site, yes, it is a local workforce. Um
and that's beneficial to all of us to
give us highpaying jobs and uh benefits
in this city. Thirdly, um why don't we
follow Texas and President Trump's
executive order requiring data centers
to provide all power and let's take it
one step further to add a wastewater
treatment plant on site so we don't have
any of these spills again because that
is very concerning. Um as a member who
lives in this city, yes, I want jobs,
but I also want clean water. Um I would
like to ask if not Dennis centers, what
industries are okay to build in
Cheyenne? because I being here my whole
life when the refinery went to
biodeiesel it wasn't much I had to hit
the road to go work um and there's been
talk about young people leaving I was
one of those um I bought a house here
and I traveled out of here but out of
the 15 people that went on the road with
me I'm the only one who came back
um in closing I'd like to ask that all
politicians
um to keep their stance either for or
against data centers and be genuine um
and not just to pander to get votes. Um
I know currently we see a lot of the
mudslinging around currently in our
congressional race at our at large seat
of you know back and forth. Let's if
you're for them be for them. If you're
against them be against them. I'll
respect either opinion either way. Um
again I'm for this annexation but let's
do it right. Do it responsible and let's
not downplay the concerns from everybody
cuz even though I'm for this annexation
the concerns that I'm hearing from
everybody else are real. Um, thank you.
>> Come on you guys, please. The other side
isn't going to clap and we're not going
to clap either. Okay, just thank you
very much.
>> Good evening, city council. My name is
Marin Callas and I'm award one
candidate.
While I understand that this annexation
request will likely be approved, this is
the last opportunity as a member of the
public that I'll have to speak on this
item. So I would like to lament for the
missed opportunity that this annexation
with Microsoft presented.
The 3500 acre request is the largest
annexation in Cheyenne's history and
instead of treating it as the anomaly
that it is, we are treating it the same
way we treat a 2acre request. An
annexation of this size in order to
protect the health, safety, and wellness
of this community should come with it a
legally binding agreement that secures
mutual prosperity between the city of
Cheyenne and Microsoft. Our land and our
infrastructure are the only leverage
that we have to ensure that our
community will receive the maximum
possible benefits with a company that
will reap billions from a landscape that
we will never get back.
A question was raised at the public
services committee meeting. Why are we
picking on Microsoft? Well, my answer to
that is timing. National opinion of data
centers has dramatically shifted toward
the negative. And the fact that we don't
find out about a new data center until
the request for annexation comes before
city council is now problematic.
That leaves only five meetings in the
six weeks preceding approval that give
the public a chance to voice their
concerns. So perhaps the real issue is
our city government's antiquated process
for handling such rapid and enormous
industrial development. But arguing to
change that process doesn't help us
tonight.
This annexation request is symbolic of
big corporations and lawmakers operating
behind non-disclosure agreements,
proprietary privileges, and property
rights laws to do what they want
regardless of public criticism or
disapproval. We're picking on Microsoft
just because they happen to be first in
line in this new climate with many more
billion dollar developers behind them.
The annexation before you was an
opportunity to set a new stage for this
next wave of development. We had a
chance to work with a corporation that
is committed to Cheyenne and negotiate a
partnership agreement in exchange for
our land and our infrastructure.
Microsoft already has partnership
agreements in states like Wisconsin,
so it's not new to them. We had a chance
to set a precedent for future hypers
scale development in Laramie County that
would bring us more than just taxes and
jobs.
Instead, we're saying it's business as
usual.
Once the annexation is approved,
Microsoft will have all that it wanted
from us, and future community benefits
will be at their discretion. Cheyenne
will simply go back to being a grateful
recipient of their philanthropy rather
than an empowered partner. All we can do
now is hope that Microsoft will honor
its pledge to the betterment of our
community and follow faithfully any
future regulations from this governing
body that may come to pass. Thank you.
>> Jimmy Cher one candidate, I'm pleading
with you guys to please do the right
thing on this quality of life over the
dollar. I get advertisements on Facebook
all the time for outside companies that
are advertising for jobs here for the
the data centers. So, it's not always
about providing local jobs for the
people here in Cheyenne. This is an
enormous amount of land that is going to
impact us for a long time. And as I've
said to you before, what happens when
technology changes and then we've got
all of these data centers, all these
business parks are just empty. They're
going to walk away. you're not going to
go and get the tax base anymore. And the
same thing with that leak that happened.
We don't want Cheyenne to turn into
another Love Canal. I know everybody on
this on this committee here knows what
I'm talking about. They're old enough to
remember Love Canal. So, I'm pleading
with you not to accept this annexation.
The attorney will even tell you, you
may. It says may, not have to. I don't
care if the te's are crossed and the
dies are are dotted. You may accept it.
This is too big. And as Councilman Wolf
said, we've got to go and look into this
further. That's it. I want to keep it
short. So, we're not here till 12.
>> Welcome, ma'am.
>> Welcome.
>> Thank you. Um, Peggy Gates, Ward Three.
Um, thank you for the opportunity to
speak tonight. I live in the Sweetgrass
neighborhood. My husband and I built a
house there three years ago, and we
intend for that to be our forever home
going forward. So therefore, we have a
vested interest in this massive project
happening near near us. I know many
things go into creating property value.
Um I'm interested in our home not losing
value and also in Wyoming's unique and
beautiful open landscapes being
maintained as much as possible. Mistakes
happen as as they did and I will welcome
transparency from the city and Microsoft
when it comes to unforeseen things that
may occur in the future. Um, I like to
know the cons as well as the pros and I
will respect an effort by both city and
Microsoft to be transparent about that.
Um, Microsoft's community meeting on May
28th fell on a holiday week. Um, and
then I know there were city meetings as
well. I know of some neighbors who were
out of town that week. We were not able
to attend. Um, Microsoft did post
theformational boards on their website.
I appreciate that and I did look at
those. I'm very interested in the
conservation easement that they have on
the maps. Um, but I would like to
suggest that Microsoft and the city, if
they would like to come back, um, have
another gathering specific to Sweetgrass
and other nearby property owners. Um,
and that it be a conversational as well
asformational meeting. Um, I think that
could go a long way in proactively
easing our concerns. Um,
I don't want the annexation, but I
understand Senator Lumis has the right
to request it just like she did for the
land that my house is on. Um, so it
doesn't have to be a whole year, but
even a 3 to six month time frame would
allow time to put into writing a
reliable agreement that openly and
clearly benefits all the parties. Um, no
jobs will be lost in that time. there's
plenty going on to keep the jobs in
place and those people do have the right
to stand up and speak tonight as well as
all the opposing views. Um so my sincere
question to the city council is why is
it necessary for this annexation and
resoning vote to be completed tonight
and that's it.
>> I know that's a good question that you
asked ma'am. We have a a process and
we've been going through this process
for a number of months now and this is
the last meeting of that and you know I
I would guess if we postpone it for
three months people will be saying they
want to postpone it longer at some point
we just have to vote and say yes or no
and give the the people who want to
develop that piece of property clear
direction whether they can be in the
city or not in the city. I think they
already own the land. I think they're
either going to do it in the city or
outside the city. Um and so we're trying
to give them direction as to how they
should make their plan. Should they
drill wells or should they use city
water and sewer? I think that's where
we're at tonight.
>> Okay. Will there be opportunity for
participation from the public going
forward?
>> You know, I think that's a really good
question and uh and something that uh um
I'm very supportive of and I will ask
again and I see people from Microsoft
here that did the last meeting and um I
think we saw a lot of benefit from that
and I'll ask them to do that again um
because I think once they've done their
planning uh they need to share that with
us and uh hopefully we can share that
with you.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Dakota Titus Ward One. Um
I think we've seen um all around the
country different communities um finding
the ill effects of these data centers um
after they've come in after their city
councilmen have have rushed to bring
them in and and and wanted them in and
done it under the guise of economic
growth. and we've seen people lose their
good water and we've seen people lose
their wildlife and we've seen all of
these consequences happen. Um
and it and it and it does worry worry
me. The other thing that worries me is
the purposeful lack of transparency when
it comes to these data centers. I mean,
um, this council did attempt to cover up
the contamination. Um, and and you know,
it it makes me wonder
who has an interest in this when you see
city councilmen
on social media platforms sitting in
skyboxes at sporting events paid for by
these data centers
is absolutely [clears throat] crazy to
me. Um,
we talk about them being closed loop
systems. If they were truly a closed
loop system, there wouldn't have been
contamination.
It wouldn't have escaped. So, so that's
another fallacy.
And I don't understand how
I don't understand how we're how we're
still just lying to ourselves. I mean, I
live in Ward One. I live in the city. I
have to ask my neighbors for consent to
have a chicken coupe.
And mind you, mind you, it is it is in
statute that you are allowed to have six
chickens within city limits. But I have
to ask my neighbors for permission to
have a chicken coupe while you guys sit
here on your high horses and try to
bring in data centers that you guys
don't have the consent of the people
for.
That's confusing to me. And uh another
concern that I have is that in in all of
this process, there's not been an out.
There's not been a way to reverse these
if we are to bring them into our
communities once we do see the ill
effects of these data centers. That
there's there's no way to back out of
this. There's been there's been multiple
pieces of literature posted
about the fact that you guys don't want
us to have an out because you don't want
to discourage these people from coming
to Cheyenne. And like what I would say
to that is I think just by the pure
amount of people in this room is the
majority of the people of Cheyenne are
discouraged by these data centers.
So please
use use a little bit of of common sense
here and look at what your people are
consenting to and what they are not. And
I know that some of you don't care
because some of you won't get reelected.
But the rest of us do care. the ones
that have to live here for the rest of
our lives. The one those of us that have
operate businesses here, it's absolutely
ridiculous. And I urge you guys to
either no vote or to postpone this until
somebody with a brain can look into it.
>> Yeah.
>> Welcome.
>> Okay. Good evening, Mayor Collins and
the members of the city council. My name
is Robin Kelly. I'm in Ward three and I
live near the proposed 3500 acre
annexation area. I am here tonight to
ask because um [sighs]
because your decisions will directly
affect me, my husband, my family, my
neighbors, and our community forever. I
recognize that some of these data
centers have invested in Cheyenne and
created temporary jobs. Economic
development is important, but growth
should not come out of the expense of
the people who voted you in who already
love live here and call this place home.
Right now, the city is being asked to
annex thousands of acres even before
there's a complete development plan
without knowing the final number of
buildings,
the traffic volume, water um you know,
the water demands, which we we already
know is pretty scarce, uh the noise
levels, the electrical infrastructure,
or long-term impacts to the people and
the environment. This doesn't even
include our loss of property values,
which we already know is great. Without
knowing all of these answers, it's
difficult for anyone to know what this
project ultimately means for Cheyenne. I
respectfully ask this council to please
don't treat this annexation as a routine
boundary adjustment.
Annexation commits the city of Cheyenne
to extending services and infrastructure
and sets the stage for future industrial
development. Once this decision is made,
it's very difficult to reserve to
reverse. If the council decides to move
forward against the people's requests, I
ask that you first require an in
enforcable protection for the nearby
residents, me, including but not limited
to independent studies of traffic noise,
water demand, and public infrastructure.
Clear setbacks and some sort of
landscape buffers between the industrial
facil facilities and our homes. Strict
limits on noise, lighting, and backup
generator operations.
An ongoing public reporting and
monitoring of water usage environmental
impacts.
and maybe a legally binding community
benefits agreement that ensures the
people of Cheyenne
um will get lasting value from this
project and and of this magnitude.
I'm not asking for you to reject the
economic development. I'm a just asking
you to slow down and not make any hasty
decisions to ensure that our growth is
planned responsibly,
transparently,
and with the people who already call
Cheyenne their home in mind. Please slow
this pro process down until you have all
the information you need to make an
informed decision. And I thank you for
your time and consideration.
>> Thank you for being here. Yes, ma'am.
Donna Dundan, word one. Um, I ask you to
please listen to our constituents like
this woman. She is a resident. She's
going to be highly affected. We are not
I am not a paid correspondent for
Microsoft who's been briefed and
prepared and on a payroll to come here
tonight to represent politics that's
driving a one direction which is
basically enslaving the rest of America.
the movement across the nation for the
data centers is too fast, too quick with
too many unknowns.
And Councilman said before, he talked
about the land could sit there for 20
years um and said it's, you know, health
and safety and welfare. Those are
priorities, but for everybody. So that
applies to the people who want to
develop the land and sell their land
that they want to develop, but it also
applies to us as citizens. And there's
more of us than there are of them. We
have the future of our our students um
our elderly and our immuno compromised
um citizens here in Cheyenne. That's a
big consideration and concern for mine
because they're going to be the ones
that are first affected. I did come from
Colorado and I could have sold my house
for many times what it was worth to
Black Rockck. I was offered money and I
declined it and I accepted money from
some people in the community who were
just trying to get their hands on their
first home in Colorado and that's what I
chose because that's what I could live
with in my soul. So those that are
seeking big money, big money is here.
Big money is right over here. They have
representatives. They pay their
employees. They pay our school
districts. They're putting money into
every part of Cheyenne
and because they can make billions here.
That's how everybody in here is getting
benefited from the from the money from
Microsoft. People have jobs and we can't
hold our neighbors
um in content for wanting jobs. We all
want good jobs. We all want safety for
our kids. We all want clean water. We
all want clean air. And I don't begrudge
them for wanting and needing jobs
because that's what we all need. But I
do hold the responsibility for you guys
for government. I had a question for the
mayor. You said there was no NDA
agreements.
So does that include with the um leads
group? You did not sign one with leads.
>> No, ma'am. I do have an NDA with leads
and it and it includes anything that I
learned during a board meeting. But
>> you stop my clock.
I'll add the time back.
>> Okay.
>> Um it does include anything that I learn
while I'm there at the board meetings,
>> but anything that I learn outside of
that if uh you know if I'm talking to a
data center, any other information I get
uh is public and would be treated that
way.
>> So if uh if we're talking about you know
leads as a board u selling a piece of
property or something like that, I I
can't talk about that. But um if if
somebody uh if a data center let's let's
use Microsoft as example comes and talks
to me about their plans those are not
covered under an NDA by any means. Only
things that are covered are the things
that I we talk about actually at the
board meeting.
>> Okay. Um the other thing was you denied
the $50 million mandate. Did you settle
one that for asking for Microsoft to
place when we asked for Microsoft to
place a mandate and it was a suggested
50 million
um that was coming from
>> Oh, that was an amendment before the
city council. Yes, ma'am. That was voted
that was I don't know if it was voted
down or just was not presented, but
>> it has you quoted in here as saying that
would be extortion.
>> That would be a dangerous precedent and
equates to extortion.
>> I did say that.
>> That's what you said.
What did did you accept any uh money for
them to put in aside for us in case of
emergencies?
>> Has has Microsoft paid us any money? Is
that what you're asking?
>> Have you come to an agreement with them
on what they should put aside for us as
a community in case of emergencies?
>> No, ma'am. We have not come to any final
number yet.
>> Have you um exempted them from providing
one?
>> No, ma'am. So, we're going to go ahead
and give them everything they want, but
we don't have this background yet. We
have no surveys on the land, on the
water, on the effects, and we have no
backup cash to know like if something
were to happen. We already have this
amount of money that we could jump right
in and work towards remediation and
safety protocols. Um the
>> ma'am I think I understand your question
and that is you know when you when we
talk with Microsoft they don't know
exactly what their plan for that
property is but once that plan is done
that's an opportunity for us then to sit
down and talk about how do we mitigate
those things we're not there yet we
don't know what that plan is
>> well then isn't it responsible
development as the councilman talked
earlier to go into making decisions
without those in place? No, ma'am. I
don't think so, honestly. Um, you know,
I think that the decision Microsoft is
trying to make right now is are they
going to develop in the city or are they
going to develop in the county? And I
think it's more responsible to develop
in the city because we're not going to
be drilling wells into the into the
aquifer. They're going to be on city
water sewer. We're going to take their
their sewage as we just proved recently
with the unfortunate incident with the
bacteria. We caught that. We isolated
it. We remediated it. And we put steps
in to try to prevent that from happening
in the future. that wouldn't happen if
we didn't have a way to to test it.
>> And and on that point as well, you did
catch that and I'm grateful for the
board of utilities for doing that. But
you also withheld that information till
the other vote went through. So you did
not release that information until the
last vote on the same issue went
through.
>> So that that was known from a February
incident. We went through the last vote
before this one and that was not
released till recently. I mean, if that
if you that were the case, ma'am, we
probably would have kept it hidden until
after this vote, but that didn't happen.
>> Well, that would be totally illegal. So,
I mean, I'm just saying
>> I agree. I agree. Those things should be
disclosed. And uh but
>> this is what we call politics though, is
it not?
>> No, I don't think so, ma'am. But I
appreciate politics.
>> I appreciate you being here this
evening.
>> Okay. Thank you,
>> Mr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Mayor, city council members, Brad
Emmens, agent for the owners and
applicants of this annex station. Um we
do believe that the um uh application
meets the criteria uh the owner of the
land um would prefer uh to develop with
city water, sewer uh city oversight.
They are also keeping 500 acres of this
annexation. So all of this uh annexed
area is not entirely uh going uh to be
developed. it's uh they have kept it in
the AG zone and have looked at the ridge
line as conserving conserving that and
they are also um they do still have the
plans to do the residential development.
So they've been looking at the areas
that they believe would not affect those
areas. Um and so therefore we believe
the annexation should move forward as it
meets the criteria.
>> Thank you Mr. Mayor. I have a question
real quick.
>> Yeah. [clears throat]
>> Uh thank you Mr. Mayor through you.
Thank you sir. Have you had any meetings
with the uh residents of Sweetgrass on
this annexation?
>> Mr. Mayor 3, we did not have a specific
meeting with the uh Sweetgrass area. We
did have a meeting neighbor meeting with
the Grass Hill subdivision, which is the
closest subdivision, which is in the
county. Uh so we invited the closest uh
either adjacent members or the people
that were in the Grass Hills subdivision
to a meeting.
>> Follow Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Thu, are you
willing to have a meeting with the
residents of Sweet Grass regarding this?
>> Mr. Mayor Thu, I I cannot speak for
Microsoft and the owners of the
annexation, but I'd be happy to sit down
with the with the owners, but there are
representatives from Microsoft here that
can speak to that better than I could.
>> Thank you,
>> sir. Welcome.
>> Yes, sir. It is
>> my turn already. Good evening. I'm uh
Todd Humans. I'm in W three. Um, I
reside at the in the sweet grass. Um, I
want to thank the city council for
taking the time to uh hear my concerns.
Um,
I've worked previously as a software
developer and IT architect for the past
30 years, so I'm not inherently against
data centers, but at more than 3,000
acres, this project has the potential to
become one of the largest data centers
in the country. Um,
that means we're entering unchartered
territory. While the planned Stratos
project in Utah may be larger, it is
located in the middle of the desert, far
from any population centers, Cheyenne is
different. Decisions made here directly
affect nearby neighborhoods, existing
infrastructure, and long-term character
of the community. I respectfully ask the
council to pause and carefully consider
whether we want to tie Cheyenne's
economic future to data centers on a
scale not yet seen anywhere else in the
United States.
If the council chooses to move forward
quickly, I ask that you prioritize
directing any financial grants or
community benefit funds or tax benefits
from this development
and apply it to the residential areas
that bear the brunt of these impacts.
These neighborhoods in the 820007 zip
code currently have fewer recreation
opportunities and large-scale
development will only increase that
imbalance. Please consider immediate
investment in parks, golf courses,
public swimming facilities, and other
amenities that would improve the quality
of life for the residents most affected
by these projects. Thank you for your
time and your thoughtful consideration.
>> Thank you, sir. Welcome.
>> Good evening, mayor, members of the
council, staff, and members of the
public. For the record, my name is
Rachel Irwing. I serve as Microsoft's
land development manager. I would like
to begin by thanking council, city
staff, and community members who have
engaged throughout this process over the
past several months. These applications
have been reviewed through multiple
public hearings, committee meetings, and
public discussions. We appreciate the
time, thoughtful questions, and dialogue
that have helped inform the
conversations surrounding this project.
The Highlands application represents an
opportunity to establish a framework for
future growth under city jurisdiction,
city standards, and city oversight.
Annexation allows planning,
infrastructure coordination, and
development review to occur through the
city's established processes, providing
greater clarity and consistency as this
area develops over time. It also creates
[snorts] a path for continued
collaboration between Microsoft, the
city, and the community as future
development is considered. As future
planning efforts move forward, we remain
committed to maintaining open
communication and working
collaboratively with city staff, elected
officials, stakeholders, and residents.
Microsoft has been part of the Cheyenne
community for 14 years and we remain
committed to being a responsible
long-term partner. We value the
relationships we built here, the
opportunities uh we help for creating
local workforce and businesses. Our
partnership with schools, nonprofit
organizations, and community leaders
throughout the region. The success of
our operations is closely tied to the
successes of the communities in which we
operate. As we continue to grow
alongside Cheyenne, we look forward to
making significant investments in the
community and working collaboratively
with city leadership to support the
community's long-term vision and
priorities. We recognize that strong
communities require investments beyond
the infrastructure needed to support any
single development and we welcome
continued conversations about how
Microsoft can help create lasting
benefits for the residents of Cheyenne.
Thank you for your time and
consideration.
>> Rachel, they have been asking if we're
going to have any more public meetings
as you guys develop your plans. Uh will
you be will you be doing some of those
uh like you did at LC uh as you're as
you flesh out your plans,
>> mayor, through you? Yes, we do plan to
have um additional public hearings. Um
we actually have a representative from
our community affairs team who can also
speak to uh more specific timing and
anticipated plans.
>> He's standing right behind you.
[laughter]
>> Good evening, Mr. Mayor, Council. My
name is Donis Trio and I'm with Don. Can
you bring your microphone up just a
little bit?
>> Apologies. Rachel's just not as tall as
you.
>> Good evening, Mr. Mayor and Council. My
name is Adonis and I'm with the
Microsoft Data Center community affairs
team. In the last month and a half, we
have participated and hosted four
separate events to engage external
community to provide more transparency
to our project. And it was mentioned
that um information on the projects that
we're talking about this evening are
posted online and publicly available.
So, we're hoping to be as transparent as
possible, but if the community is asking
for more engagement, we certainly
welcome the opportunity to continue
that.
>> You know, what what's been given to us
in testimony is that um you know, once
this process is done, you're going to go
into a planning process to how you're
going to develop that out. And I think
what I'm hearing from everybody on the
DAS and also in the in the audience
would be an opportunity once you have
those plans to sit down and and share
those with the community.
>> Yes, I do want to reinforce, Mr. mayor
that we are extremely early in the
process and so we are sharing all the
information that we have to date and
although we can't provide answers to all
the questions that are out there we are
providing answers to everything that we
have available to us today
>> and and and in the future as those plans
become available you'll be sharing those
in u in public meetings um as you did
like at LC
>> most certainly we we think that
engagement with the community having
proactive conversations is is the best
approach
>> we agree thank you
>> Mr. Mayor I have a question Mr. Ask
>> uh through you. Uh in some of my
conversations, we've heard that the the
campus would have uh classrooms where
high school graduates can go and uh
learn how they could be programmers or
other jobs at Microsoft. So the office
spaces as well, the CRA classroom spaces
are part of this whole campus. It's just
not all data center. Correct.
>> U mayor through you. Yes, ma'am. Um
specifically for this campus, I I don't
have a specific set of engineering
plans. Um
>> however, that is a possibility. Um and
also I I welcome Donna's to come up to
speak to that as well where we do offer
um locally in the community with
partnerships with uh LC.
>> Absolutely. Happy to share more about
our data center academy. Uh we actually
have a representative and educator from
LC who I think could do a much better
job of talking about the program than I
can. Uh we do ensure that we're
providing job opportunities for local
talent here in Cheyenne. And as part of
that, we want to develop career pathways
through these programs at LC, which we
call our data center academy. We also
work with a number of other nonprofit
providers. We'll hear from a program
called GBA Beta. We really work to uh
ensure that the skilling opportunities
are available to students who are
interested in exploring different
pathways.
>> Thank you. Thank you.
>> Yes, Mr. Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. through you.
Thank you, ma'am. Just a question. So,
you said you're the land management for
Microsoft. Is it just for Wyoming or
what are there other states that you're
also doing it for?
>> Um, mayor, through you. My specific
responsibilities rely solely in
Cheyenne.
>> Paul, sir.
>> Yep. Thank you, sir. And you reside in
Cheyenne?
>> Mayor, through you. I do not reside in
Cheyenne.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, ma'am. Sir,
members of the city council, my name is
Ted Hanland. I live in Ward 2. I'm the
chair of the Lar County Democratic Party
and I'm a Democratic candidate for
Senate District 5. I'm not opposed to
data centers. I've been trying to figure
out how to get jobs in Cheyenne all my
adult life. I'm here to address a
troubling governance issue. What we are
witnessing is a capriccious use of
annexation designed to create a
regulatory blind spot, effectively
allowing mega corporations
[clears throat] to bypass the oversight
of the Wyoming Department of
Environmental Qualities Industrial
Sighting Council, ISC. Under Wyoming
state law, massive industrial projects
that exceed specific cost and
infrastructure thresholds are required
to go through the ISC. This is a vital
regulatory safeguard that's been in
place since 1975. It's designed to
evaluate the socioeconomic impacts of me
mega projects, analyze environmental
footprints, and most importantly,
mandate strict mitigation fees and
community benefit agreements to protect
local governments and taxpayers. Every
wind or solar project must go through
this process. Why are data centers
different? When a project is swallowed
up into the city via massive single
property annexation, developers are
shielded, exempt from ISC review. This
is intentional. By rushing to annex
nearly 3,500 acres of agricultural land,
this council is actively helping
multi-billion dollar developers evade
the very state agency equipped to
regulate them. Cheyenne City government
is simply not staffed, structured, or
funded to act as an industrial
regulatory body. By approving this
annexation without a fully realized
master plan, you're abdicating your duty
to protect the public. You're giving up
all of our leverage. Councilman Wolf was
entirely correct to push for a dramatic
reset and demand a formal community
benefits agreement. If these
corporations want to create a huge
footprint in our backyard, they must
play by our rules, provide binding
transparency, and directly mitigate the
strain they place on our town.
Voting yes tonight set the dangerous
precedent that Cheyenne will compromise
its own regulatory integrity for the
promise of unquantified future tax
revenues. I urge you to vote no or
postpone this ordinance until a full
joint review can be conducted alongside
the DEEQ Industrial Sighting Council.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Uh Mr. Hanland, I
just have a quick question. Who who
determines the scope of the um
industrial sighting council?
>> The state legislature has in the past.
We've made two big changes to the
industrial sighting council that I know
of. In 2010,
we named wind projects to be
specifically part of the industrial
sighting council regardless of their
size. In 2020, we specifically named
solar projects to be part of the
industrial sighting council if they
exceeded 20 megawws, which as you all
know, 20 megawws is a drop in the bucket
compared to the power used by one of
these projects. So the the state
legislature
has the ability to uh to name data
centers to change the the monetary
threshold.
>> Thank you sir. So the the point is
that's not something we have any control
over though.
>> What you have control over tonight is
whether to proceed without the help of
the industrial sighting council. That's
what you have control over.
>> Thank you.
>> Mr. Hanland. Don't run away. There's
another question for you. You're a
popular man this evening.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Three. Uh, thank
you, sir, for that. And I know
especially, would you say that the anger
and that this is a bipartisan issue?
>> I I think it's pretty clear that both
Anne Lucas and I have spoken on the same
side of the issue tonight and I think
both Anne Lucas and I would work in the
legislature together if we're both
elected to uh make sure the industrial
sighting council covers it.
>> Thank you so much, sir.
>> All right. Welcome, ma'am.
Hello, I'm Terry Bell. I live in Ward
One. Um, earlier in the meeting, Mr.
Cagrave made a statement that just hit
me as very disingenuous when he said,
"We have no idea what the owner plans to
do with these properties. The [snorts]
majority of these properties, you
absolutely know what they plan to do."
Back in the late 1990s, Fort Collins
announced that they were going to annex
Timnith, which was a tiny farm town. It
took an 80-year-old farm wife to go to
their meeting and point out that they by
their own ordinance would be required to
provide infrastructure across I25,
which their city council at that time
was not aware of. [snorts] They checked
their statutes and they dropped the
annexation.
This process right here feels very
similar.
>> [snorts]
>> I've lived here almost 11 years and I
love the western values of truth and
taking care of your neighbors and
honestly I was gobsmacked to read that
there are 75 data centers in planning
here and I'm wondering if you have
considered the actual impact on our
water system when our residents have
already been put at risk of serious
disease from a meta contractor which was
not revealed to residents and to say
well We revealed it six months later.
I'm caregiver to my disabled Vietnam
veteran husband and the risk that you
allowed could have sickened or killed
him and many of the immuno compromised
veterans in this town. That just
horrifies me. You promised that the new
cooling systems won't impact our water
systems. Yet the one center we have in
place already cost us an undisclosed
huge amount of money. and a month to
remediate.
Do we have laws in place to ensure that
these costs go to the polluters?
[snorts] They say they'll be disposing
the water, waste water offsite. Do you
have any proof that they're disposing of
it safely or are you just taking them at
their word? Personally, I don't trust
anything Facebook tells me until I've
verified it with at least two revi
reliable sources.
I understand that after over four hours
of residents voicing their concerns to
you at the last meeting, you just went
ahead and approved everything. [snorts]
That is why we feel unheard and
disrespected.
Adding 75 of any kind of business to
this community would have a huge impact.
And yet it feels like you're just making
this up as you go along. instead of
engaging in professional city planning
and foresight
that we really don't want you to have
the leg legacy of destroying Cheyenne
with lack of planning. You've already
earned national news coverage and daily
show ridicule for our contamination and
secrecy about it. How can 70 more
centers be good for this community until
we have more information? Thank you,
ma'am.
Sir,
welcome.
>> Thank you. Here, let's move this around.
Uh, [laughter]
good evening, mayor and city council
members. My name is Troy Amik. I am a
tenure resident of W three, 19-year
resident of Cheyenne. Uh, I, for clarity
sake, I am the director of the IT
pathway at LC. I am here speaking of my
own accord. My statements are not those
of my employer. I want to make that
clear.
Uh Adonis kind of threw a wrench in what
my plan was. So I'm going to by
announcing who I was. So I'm going to
change roles here. I've done a lot of
different jobs in 15 years. Uh the last
15 though have been information
technology. So this is my world. This is
where I live. Um
in that my time with LGC, I've been
there since early 2019. In that time,
Microsoft has donated over a half
million dollars.
Half of that has been scholarships.
That half that quarter million dollars
has directly led to over a hundred
people changing their lives. We're not
talking of oh that this person tried
this person did this. No, over a hundred
people have got highpaying high earning
careers. We talk about the data centers.
We don't need these data centers. I'm
sorry. I don't see a whole lot of other
high earning industries pounding on our
door right now. We talk about we want
all these amenities. We want these other
retailers. We want these we want grocery
stores. We want these things. We get
them by having people that have high
earning jobs.
Without the support and the people that
earn the money, we don't get those
amenities. We don't get those things.
Now, am I saying we need to launch 70
data centers today? No. This will be a
natural growth. Nothing happens that
fast. We don't flip a switch and a house
appears. We don't flip a switch and a
data center appears. They have to be
built in stages. So, this will go. We
talk about annexation.
We talk about the fact that it is, oh,
we're worried about we're going to be
pulling water from the aquafers. No,
that's why we need to annex because if
we annex, then we're pulling from the
city's water. I got a number for you. 60
million gallons.
That's what an average 18 horse 18hole
golf course uses at our climate and our
altitude. We have four of them in this
town.
Four. We have two more in the county
that are pulling from wells.
Three and a half to 5 and a half million
gallons.
That's what a big box retailer uses. A
Walmart, a Lowe's, a Home Depot
annually.
Modern closed loop data centers. 350,000
gallons to 500,000 gallons. It's on par
with a McDonald's.
Yet, we don't stomp and yell about a
McDonald's.
>> Thank you. And I'm happy to answer any
questions you have about eligible C as
well.
>> Thank you, sir. Thanks.
>> Hi, Adonis.
>> Good evening, Mr. Mayor and Council. My
name is Adonis Tri and I'm with the
Microsoft Community Affairs team and I
work alongside Lucas Downey.
I would like to start by acknowledging
everyone who's here this evening both in
the room and online and really thank you
for your time during this entire
process, your passion and your
commitment to the future of Cheyenne.
I do want to share that Microsoft has
and continues to work closely with the
community even if we have room to grow.
I would like to take a moment to
reinforce what that has looked like for
us up to this point.
Since 2012, when Microsoft first started
our data centers here in Cheyenne, we've
worked mindfully to show up as a good
neighbor. We've listened intently
throughout that time and especially
throughout this process.
We understand that projects like these
bring important questions about the
future of the community
and I'd like to highlight our community
first infrastructure commitments in the
context of Cheyenne.
First, we are ensuring that we pay our
own way so that Microsoft data centers
will not raise electricity prices for
local rate payers.
Second, we're focused on minimizing our
water use and being good stewards.
Water is truly a precious resource here
in Wyoming, as we've heard over and over
again, and we're committed to protecting
it.
Third, we are creating jobs for local
residents across construction and
operational roles
and we're supporting local workforce
training programs at places like LC with
our data center academy that I mentioned
a little earlier.
Fourth, we're adding to the local tax
base,
contributing directly to the funding for
local first responders, schools, parks,
and libraries.
And finally, we're strengthening the
community by investing in local
nonprofits and resource that truly
advance the priorities for Cheyenne.
When we're up here talking, we're not
just talking about infrastructure. We're
talking about being a true partner to
Cheyenne for the long run.
Thank you all for your continued
engagement, and we look forward to
continuing to work together to further
these commitments. Thank you.
>> Hang on. Go ahead.
>> All right. Thank you, Mr. Thu. Thank
you, sir. So, you said you're part of
the community affair affairs team for
Microsoft. Is that just Wyoming or is
that include other states?
>> Mr. Mayor Thruyear. Thank you,
Councilman, for for your question.
Everywhere Microsoft has a data center
presence, we have a community affairs
team that supports that community.
>> Paul,
>> yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. for you. Um,
how many actual jobs, not indirectly,
directly work for Microsoft are
currently now in uh, Cheyenne and Larry
County?
Mr. Mayor, through you. Thank you for
the question, council member.
If we're looking at our data center jobs
directly, the number will change from
day to day. Um, but we're north of 250
full-time operations team members, but
with other teams that we have like
security and other on-site staff, we're
north of 500.
>> Okay. Uh, one more question, Mr. Mayor.
Um, 250. And then, do you live in
Laramie County or Cheyenne?
>> Mr. Mayor, through you, council member,
I do not.
>> Thank you,
>> ma'am.
Welcome.
Thank you, Danielle Cox. I am in the
Microsoft area. I got one of those
letters uh early and was stupid because
I trusted my government was doing the
best it would could for its residents.
And Microsoft said it was a god and it
was going to use its own water. They
don't create water. Water is a limited
resource.
McDonald's may use that much
water in a day. They don't poison the
water and return it to the wells. They
may poison our bodies,
but they do not poison the water and
return it to the wells for use. I've
heard that after data data centers are
created, they maybe have 12 workers
there. So, yay. I'm so glad for you
construction workers that have a job
right now. I really do want for people
to be able to provide for their
families. Think about the future. Would
you place your children Microsoft in the
land that you are poisoning? Would you
members are you placing the future of
your prosperity? Or have you gotten
millions of dollars to go buy land and
homes in safer places like the
mountains? Because that's what I've been
looking at. feel like the mountainous
areas are better protected than places
like Cheyenne. I feel
like you guys know that your future is
going to be elsewhere and that's why
you're willing to sell the water, the
land, the resources and maybe Microsoft
and every other data century uh sorry
center is willing to buy our water and
our health. those people who received
scholarships, LC and everything they're
getting from that, they those those
people will have a job that pays better.
Good for them. But is our future of our
whole community worth any dollar that
these
greedy data centers are willing to spend
to buy us?
That's all I have to say.
Hi,
welcome. Can you bring that microphone?
There you go.
>> Yes, absolutely. Good evening. My name
is Stacy Balkan and I currently reside
in Ward 2.
First, I would like to thank the city
council, the citizens, and the employees
of Microsoft that are here tonight. Your
presence alone is what makes this great
city and community stand out above the
rest.
Some of you may know me personally as I
have 29 years deeply rooted in this
town.
I've even worked alongside you in a city
council and I went to school with your
children. We even have children or
grandchildren involved in
extracurricular activities together.
Microsoft data centers have given me a
second chance at starting a new career,
benefited my family in positive ways,
and strengthened the community that I
love.
Microsoft and Cheyenne has had a
mutually beneficial relationship since
2012.
They are not a fly by night company
where they are here to make their money
and leave.
We are here to stay and we want to be a
great neighbor along the way.
Since 2019, Microsoft data center
investments have generated approximately
$1.6 billion
in economic activity,
created thousands of local jobs with
more to come, are the number one
paxpayer in Cheyenne and the number two
taxpayer in Laram County. Let me just
put this into perspective for you. In
2025 alone, Microsoft data centers
generated approximately 11 million in
property tax revenue.
That means $11 million invested in our
public services, which includes schools,
infrastructure, and public safety. Plus,
they are responsive to local charities,
STEM educational opportunities,
skilling, and technology development
initiatives.
If we put this all together, Microsoft
has been an excellent neighbor. They
have gone above and beyond to support
our community, and they have personally
impacted me in very positive ways.
But what's at stake if we don't continue
this growth?
Without these investments, our community
would miss out on thousands of jobs in
operations and construction, millions in
tax revenue, and ongoing investments in
education, workforce development, and
STEM programs.
With our continued partnership, I hope
that together we continue building a
future where the next generation has
even more opportunities than we do
today. Thank you,
>> Mr. Mayor. A quick question.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Three. Thank
you, ma'am. So, let's say we pause this
annexation. How is that going to impact,
say, the 11 million property tax revenue
currently from the data centers in
operation and also the current ones that
are under construction? If we were to
pause and slow down just what how would
that impact that?
>> Yes. Uh, mayor through you.
>> Y,
>> thank you for your question. So, I will
say that I cannot speak on behalf of
that piece. Um, I am here as a community
member first. However, we do have a team
that could definitely answer your
questions.
>> Paul, Mr. Mayor, thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Through you, and what's your position
with Microsoft, man?
>> I am an EHS manager, which means that I
am an environmental, health, and safety
manager.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks for being here.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Please come forward.
Welcome.
>> Hello. My name my name is Mara Mirbrook.
I don't live in the city fortunately,
but the way you guys are going, you're
going to put me in there, just like you
did that guy over there when you took
his form and annexed it. I have no
problem with Well, I do have a problem
with the data centers. They surround my
neighborhood and every week I hear
you're putting more of them out there. I
There's nothing I can do about it and
you're going to go ahead and you're
going to annex all these things in. What
I'm afraid of is you people annexing my
property in because like him, he didn't
have a voice. You say you do have a
voice. Well, you don't have a voice. I
don't want to be in the city. I lived in
the stinking city for 32 years and I
don't want to do it again. Please, these
people are going to keep doing their
data centers, but you don't have to
annex them in. They can figure out how
to get their water and how to do all
their stuff and pay for it. But you
don't have to annex them in because once
you annex them in, then you've got me
blocked in and you're gonna annex me in.
I don't want in the city. Quit annexing
in. Why don't you just stop and just
annex the whole county in to begin with
and then you won't have to annex anybody
in anymore? You'll have it done. You'll
have all the property you want.
Welcome.
>> Yes.
>> I I think we need to clarify that there
has not been an annexation done of uh
the Mr. Nisley's property. That has not
been done at this point. So, I want to
make sure that people understand that.
>> Ma'am, welcome.
>> Hello. Uh good evening. My name is Kelly
Morardi. I own a home in Ward One. I'm
here to speak tonight for the
neighborhoods and families who
well-being will be directly degraded if
this annex is is approved. We're being
asked to zone thousands of acres of an
industrial business park right next to
residential spaces without a meaningful
legal protections against the daily
pollutions that these facilities emit.
My first concern is about the noise.
These facilities run thousands of
massive industrial cooling fans 24 hours
a day, 7 days a week, creating
persistent low frequency sound hums that
penetrates walls, penetrates windows and
doors. The vibrations cause sleep
disruption, chronic stress, and anxiety
for nearby residents. My second concern
is about our most precious finite
resource, water. Wyoming is a high
desert state. We are functionally always
in drought. When our local water
resources are depleted, it's our local
farmers and ranchers and our citizens
who will face skyrocketing water bills.
The planning commission already looked
at the lack of concrete environmental
data and rightfully hesitated.
I ask the city council to do the same.
Do not let corporate philanthropy bind
blind you to the permanent environmental
degradation of our air, our water, and
our quiet neighborhoods. Vote no on this
annexation
until strict, enforcable caps on noise
decibb, and water consumption are
legally in place. Use the leverage we
have now to get legally binding
agreements for community engagements.
Don't rely on the goodwill of our
neighbors. Put enforcements in legally
enforceable agreements in place. I don't
believe that we're choosing, as has been
implied, between a development in the
county or a development in the city. The
developer would prefer to be in the
city. We can wait until we have
enforcable caps for our safety in place.
Thank you.
>> Good evening, ma'am.
>> Mary Goodwin, W three. Um, like most of
the people here, I don't feel that my
voice is going to be heard. So I want to
quote Aaron Brockenwitch.
Uh AI data centers risk are like the
infamous contamination she held clean up
but on steroids.
Uh I'd also like to just add that with
uh Microsoft they have just terminated
1,600 jobs but funny thing they exceeded
that with thousands over 2,000 of visas
for foreign workers. So when they talk
about bringing jobs in, they didn't
specify specifically who nor do they
guarantee for who it's going to be for.
Uh I think this is a dangerous thing and
is going too fast. And you also have to
think about the other new projects that
are coming in. You have 35 acres that's
going to go for the PRC. You've got
casinos, Sean Ranch for one, which is
doubling. Then they're going to put in
their restaurants. Then they're going to
put the hotels. Then you have their
convention centers. You can't run that
without water and they take a lot of
water. You can't run that without
electricity. I've been in Swan Ranch. I
worked there. When the power went out,
they're dead in the water
and they just sit there. And yes,
they're they bring a lot of money in,
but they can't compare with Microsoft,
but they can take the business
elsewhere.
And you certainly can't run a tourist
area with hotels that have no water. So
that is a part of what you talk about
for your future, but you're putting that
at risk by taking on all these uh AI
centers for purposes which frankly no
one here knows. Thank you.
>> Good evening, sir.
>> Good evening, city council and Cheyenne
residents.
My name [cough and clears throat] is
Jeff McPartland and I'm a CCTM for
Microsoft. That means I'm a critical
environment tech manager here in
Cheyenne. I've been associated with
Microsoft for several for seven years.
When I first started, I worked with a
contract company called JLL. About three
years ago, I was given the opportunity
to transition into a full-time role
directly with Microsoft. Tonight, I
would like to share my uh the impact
that Microsoft has had on my life.
>> [clears throat]
>> I was born and raised in a small town
called Hillet, Wyoming. Most of you have
never heard of it. And those of you that
um have understand how small it is.
Growing up there really um one obvious
career path working at your local
sawmills. But I wanted something bigger.
As a young man from a small Wyoming
town, I had to leave home and pursue
opportunities. I spent six years working
as a welder for the railroad traveling
across the United States uh for a kid in
his 20s. That was an amazing experience.
But no matter where I went, I always
missed Wyoming.
When the opportunity came for me to move
back to Cheyenne and work for Microsoft,
it changed my life. Coming from a small
town, being able to say I work for a
company like Microsoft is something I
have always been proud of. It has given
me uh opportunities and experiences that
I never imagined would be uh possible
growing up. [clears throat]
As Microsoft continues to grow in our
community, I think about our next
generation. I think about the smalltown
Wyoming kid who are kids um who are
where I was was. The growth we are
seeing today can create opportunities
for them to build successful careers
without having to leave the state they
love. As I close, I want to emphasize uh
the positive impact this company has had
on me and my families. I encourage you
to consider the opportunity this growth
can bring to our community, our economy,
and our future workforce. Our children
and even our grandchildren will have the
chance to stay in this great state,
build meaningful careers, and support
their families for generations to come.
Thank you for your time and
consideration.
>> Representative, welcome.
Uh, thank you, Mr. Mayor and members of
the council. My name is Daniel Singh.
Um, I live in precinct 33. I represent
House District 61 for now. And, uh, I'm
here to speak in opposition of the
annexation, respectfully. Um, and I'm
going to kind of segue with what was
previously said in the in the previous
uh, comment. Uh, part of one of the
reasons why so many
I'm sorry, I'm I'm thinking with my
words. Um,
one of the primary focuses that we are
told to get more data centers is to
provide more opportunities for the next
generation. That this is what the next
generation needs. That the next
generation is going to leave and go to
places with these opportunities with
data centers and that if we were to
bring these data centers into Wyoming
that we would uh have more young people.
But when you look at polling of young
people under the age of 30, they're
actually the most vehemently opposed to
the data centers themselves, uh over
50%, if you look at GA, uh Galllet
polling, uh over 50% of young people are
strongly opposed to data centers. And so
to sit here and say that young people
specifically uh we need to build these
data centers so that way we can provide
for the next generation and have the
next generation uh stay in Wyoming and
thrive. But I would actually venture to
say that that's the opposite of what
would actually happen and that when you
talk to a young family that if you were
to say uh you can live here and we're
going to have a giant data center in our
backyard that would actually be a factor
in not moving to Wyoming or not moving
to Cheyenne. Um and as I've been it's
campaign season, you all know um and I'm
not here to try to advocate for any
anybody in particular. Um, but as I've
been going door todo, uh, one of the
consistent themes I'm hearing from my
neighbors is that they came to Cheyenne
for a particular atmosphere. And with
all of this new development, many of
them have sold their properties and are
leaving town. And so the projected
intention of gaining a new population, a
new workforce, uh if that's really what
we intend to do, we need to look at the
unintended consequence of uh building
these things. And the fact is that older
residents uh members of this community
are leaving town because of these
particular industries coming into town.
And I'm not saying that we need to bar
large computing operations, but I do
think that we need to do it
incrementally, step by step, and
consider what the what the public has to
say. And I just want to preface uh that
with um article 10, section two of the
Wyoming Constitution, which says that
all powers and franchises of
corporations are derived from the people
and are granted by their agent, the
government, for the public good and
general welfare, and the right and duty
of the state to control and regulate
them. for these purposes is hereby
declared. Thank you.
>> Mayor Collins, a quick question.
>> Yep.
>> Um through you to representative Singh,
can you tell us what committees you
serve on and uh where what you've been
working on in relationship to promoting
AI?
>> Sure. Um Mr. Mayor, uh I'm actually
after after this meeting I'm heading uh
to Casper tomorrow. We will be meeting
with the select committee on blockchain
financial technology and digital
innovation technology. And on the
agenda, we're going to be talking about
electricity loads for cryptocurrency
operations as well as biometric
information and biometric information
and flock cameras. So, if you're
interested in hearing more about that,
we'll be talking about that tomorrow.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, Representative. Yes, ma'am.
Welcome.
>> Hello, Mayor Collins, city council.
Thank you for having me. My name is
Bailey Evans. I am a Cheyenne resident
of W 3 and I run a program called G Beta
Wyoming which is largely funded by
Microsoft. I'm here today to offer an
example of Microsoft being a good
neighbor. My program is an accelerator
program for Wyoming based startups to
help founders understand and access
investment um and funding for their
companies. Accelerator programs like
this one are often quite expensive. Uh
companies often pay quite a lot in
equity in order to access accelerator
programs, but the GBA beta program is
completely free thanks to funding from
Microsoft. Uh they founders don't pay
anything to participate and there's no
fees or anything. Uh since we launched
this program with Microsoft in 2020, uh
we have had 55 companies um in the state
of Wyoming come through this program. Uh
they've created around 250 jobs and
raised about $45 million um in growth
capital for their companies.
uh in that that means that for every
dollar granted by Microsoft into the GBA
beta program, the startups have raised
$59 that is being used to grow companies
here in Wyoming. So a dollar investment
created $59 in Wyoming. Um and over the
years that's the metric that Microsoft
asks me most about. They they've never
asked me how many times are we in the
media or how many times do the companies
that I work with use Microsoft products.
They've expressed a genuine interest and
desire for this partnership to boost
economic diversity and health for our
state. We do get some additional funding
from some other local partners, but
Microsoft has been our largest by far
and our most steadfast funding partner
for this program. And I just want to
thank them here publicly for that
partnership and for investing into a
program like this one and believing in
Cheyenne and in Wyoming's potential. In
fact, listening here today, it feels a
little like Microsoft believes in us
maybe more than we believe in ourselves
sometimes because right now people are
lining up to express fear for what could
happen in the future. And I'm a Cheyenne
resident and I feel it as well. But what
is happening right now that we need to
address is our families, our our young
people are leaving our state. It's
happening right now and it is the one of
the most urgent risks to our community.
People are leaving Wyoming for
communities that do believe in
themselves and have the confidence that
they can handle the risks that come with
progress. Right now, the greatest risk
to the future of our community is
staying stagnant and letting fear keep
us from making progress. Microsoft wants
to be here right now. But if we put up
too many hurdles, they will simply go
elsewhere.
I see the risks, too. But I believe in
us as a community to mitigate and manage
those risks for the benefit of the next
generation of Cheyenne families. just as
we did for the railroad and energy
companies and a lot of other industries
that wanted to make a home in our magic
city. Thank you.
>> Thanks.
>> Yes, ma'am. Welcome.
>> Thank you.
I came here tonight.
>> Ma'am, can you identify yourself,
please?
>> Yes. My name is Kathy White. I live in
Ward 3, which is and I live in the
Sweetg Grass
area.
I am a native Wyoming knight. I was born
here. I have lived in Wyoming most of my
adult life.
I came here tonight with the thought
that
city council members would know
what they were doing. I have left I I
have now begun
disillusioned.
You tell me that you're going to annex
this and you have no plans written or
concocted from Microsoft. That seems to
me irresponsible.
I don't have a thing against data
centers. I have a brother who was a
higherup executive in Microsoft. It is
not about Microsoft or any of these
other big companies that I am
complaining about. It's we cannot have a
big data center like you're talking
about. This is huge. It's not tiny. The
one they have is minuscule compared to
this. And so they're talking about
putting this huge thing in my backyard
without knowing exactly what the plans
are. And I don't see that as a
responsible
way to
approve a plan. It just doesn't seem
like it if if it were totally planned,
it could be a model. You could create a
model that other cities and
municipalities and whatever could look
at and say that's what we want it to
look like. But I'm not hearing that. I'm
hearing that we're doing, oh, we'll do
that and then we'll figure it out later.
I don't want to figure it out later. I
want it to be right when we actually
create it because there's a good plan in
place. And perhaps that's selfish of me,
but I have friends and relatives that
have lived in Wyoming forever and I want
this to be a good place for them to
live.
So, thank you for your attention. I
appreciate it.
>> Mr. Mayor, could I just ma'am?
>> Ma'am, yes.
>> It's for you, Mr. Mayor.
Thank you.
Thank you for coming. Thank you for
taking your time. Now, I hope you and
the rest of the people in this room
understand that Microsoft may not
develop this property for 10 to 20
years. And I'm not saying that in
defense of Microsoft. I'm saying that in
defense of an argument that I've made,
which is why in the world are we
annexing now? Um because when you ask
about, you know, you're acting without a
plan, that's exactly right. And that's
exactly because Microsoft says they have
no plan at this point. And they may not
have a plan for years,
>> but then they can wait for an annexation
if they have no plan.
>> Dante, welcome.
>> [clears throat]
>> Good evening, city council members. My
name is Dante Rustin. I'm the director
of real estate and property management
for Cheyenne Leadeds. I'm a W3 resident.
Uh Cheyenne Leads is a private
nonfor-profit corporation serving as the
economic development entity for the city
of Cheyenne and Larry County. Cheyenne
Leads supports the annexation of the
property per the plane department's
findings citing within the staff report.
A brief history of this partnership
between Microsoft and Medads, an
economic development partnership. Since
2021, Microsoft and Cheyenne Leads have
partnered through contractual agreements
to deliver critical public
infrastructure throughout Cheyenne and
Lurmy County. These investments in
infrastructure include pedestrian
trails, roads, sanitary sewer, water,
pump stations, and elevated water tanks.
Within these agreements, micro between
Microsoft and leads, Microsoft is
responsible for 100% of the costs that
includes permitting, design, and
construction. There's no penny spent by
the public on this. In exchange, lead is
responsible for overseeing completion of
these improvements. Now within these
agreements, our responsibilities
include management of the project
schedule, the budget, coordination with
governmental authorities, including Wide
Deck, WOT, Laramie County, the Board of
Public Utilities, and the city of
Cheyenne. Also, ease and acquisitions if
necessary, procuring the contractor,
admin, administering the contractor's
performance of work, and liazing with
property owners adjacent to
improvements. The successful delivery of
every project is supported by leads
approached for accountability and
efficiency with every task. Abley
supported through weekly meetings with
governmental authorities, the design and
construction professionals. The results
of the partnership since 2021 have
yielded more than 70 million in public
infrastructure from Microsoft. 70
million in public infrastructure.
This partnership is a proven platform in
economic development, delivering
critical public public infrastructure to
the city, Laramie County as and its
residents. We thank you for supporting
Cheyenne Leadeds and our mission to
position the city and Larmy County as a
location for new and expanding
businesses. Your approval of this
annexation will further this mission.
I'll stand for any questions.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. Uh Dante, did you
just say that you help secure or oversee
the subcontractors on a data center
project?
>> Uh Councilman Aldrich, it is the
contractors for the public
infrastructure, not the data center
itself.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you. Uh
thank you, sir. So, I heard he said he
had an agreement with um Microsoft and
Meta. Were you guys aware of the uh
February uh leakage?
>> No.
>> Thank you,
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Mr. Russian, I I've seen you now at a
number of these public hearings between
you and and Miss Hail. Um, and I keep
wondering
why do you come to these? I mean, are
you here in your sort of business
development cheerleader capacity? Is is
that is that what you're telling us?
>> As stated, our mission is to support
Cheyenne and Larmy County and all
economic development ventures and public
infrastructure is a critical piece of
that.
>> Okay. Followup, Mr. Mayor. Um, so you
came in and you opposed the discussion
we've had now on several public hearings
in which we've talked about trying to
postpone this for four months, six
months, and you've opposed that. And I
and I've wondered what what do you see
at stake with a um a postponement of
that small amount of time when you have
a project that is by Microsoft's own
testimony not going to be developed for
a decade or two?
>> Mr. question,
>> Councilman Wolf. The state statute as
listed in the staff report cites certain
provisions to be met. Now, you cannot
single out a project based on size per
the statutes that have been listed by
the state of Wyoming.
>> Um, Mr. Mayor, I I don't I don't need
you to argue the statute to us.
>> Wow.
>> We're the ones who get to interpret it
and with the help of the uh uh city
attorney, so we can read the statutes.
My question is more from a policy
standpoint and what your role is in
economic development when you're trying
to basically coers us to not take
additional time to consider these.
>> Mr. Russian, you don't have to answer
that question. You're not coercing
anybody. Thank you for being here
tonight.
>> I do have a question,
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Through you, Mr. Mayor. Uh Mr. Russian.
We just heard from I believe it was Miss
White um that she was concerned that
there's no plan. Based upon your
professional experience, is it typical
that a company will not invest
potentially large sums of money in
developing infrastructure plans until
they have ownership uh annexation and
zoning of the property? It just seems to
me that why would I invest a lot of
money until I know that I can build
eventually on this piece of property.
Does that make sense?
>> Councilman Seager, to answer your
question, there are many pieces that go
into securing a property whether you
purchase it and then getting the proper
entitlements and permitting. There are
many things and back to the public
infrastructure. BOPU has to be able to
provide the water and they've made clear
that this site is serviceable for water
delivery. There are currently water
utilities in the adjacent bison business
park that can serve this Highlands
property and that will again that will
achieve the merits of the statute that
is being held with this annexation
hearing.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor followup Mr.
I guess my question is, is it usual or
unusual for a developer to come to this
point, the annexation,
without having all of the details of of
the the project put together?
>> Councilman Cra, it'd be very unusual in
my professional experience that they
would proceed.
>> Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, Mayor Collins for you. One more
question. Um we have heard um from one
of our colleagues who threw out a number
that there were going to be 70 of these
data centers and I believe that leadeds
was actually cited as the source of
that. Can you actually tell us what the
and I know you're now um referring to
these by site location because that's
usually how people think of those. Can
you tell us how many we currently have
that are operational and up fully up and
functioning? How many are in the
pipeline that have gone through this
process or are going through this
process and if there are any that you
know of beyond that?
>> Yes, Councilman Aldrich. It is 105 and 9
and that number is found on the Cheyenne
Le's website under a data center tab.
>> Thank you.
>> Thanks, Dante.
>> Yes, ma'am. Please.
>> Thank you. I'm Jane Leinger. I have a
property in Ward One and I also live in
the county.
Uh
I know we're not just talking about um
Microsoft when we talk about this and
the proposal that we have on front of us
right now is number 13, but that also
relates to 15, number 19, number 20, and
number 25. Just want to point that out
for a few people.
I'm um we're not talking about
necessarily I think some people hear
about just Microsoft and where it is.
We're talking about all the data centers
and thank you for bringing up the number
of data centers that are in the mix. Um
it seems like we need to slow down and
take some time to plan out this whole
thing. We've got a data center here,
there, there. It's kind of like a
patchwork quilt. And then people are
worried about whether they're going to
get annexed in because they're
surrounded by the city. Like a patchwork
quilt, you've got a hole and you're just
going to put a patch in it, annex it. Um
2014 there was a you somebody said there
have been uh in the last 20 years a 25%
growth, but in 2014 was the last time we
had a planning session for what the
whole city was going to look like. Do we
want to be hemmed in by data centers and
then the core of our city go silent and
then we start building out our town back
around the data centers? We need to have
a plan that takes care of the whole
picture, not just one data center here,
another one here, another one there. We
need to slow down, take a look at all
the data centers, the whole effect, the
traffic, the roads, the the drainage,
the water usage. Well, I had a
gentleman, thanks for the education, um,
for about the ISC and the DEEQ and the
EPA, and I heard some place in one that
once you're annexed, they don't have to
follow or once they're in a business
park, they don't have to follow the EPA
regulations because there's just one
sentence in that regulation that allows
them not to have to follow the EPA.
Can't when can't we take the city back
just a step and plan the whole thing
out? Have these companies that are
coming in, we know it's going to be a
data center. Have them go through the
ISC, the DEEQ, and the EPA regulations
for the large section of property
they're or small that they're planning
to develop.
Um, I also noticed that they said
something about 300 ft is sufficient for
notifying the public. It's not. And when
you come and and you have a data center
or any public thing coming in and saying
we want to be a good neighbor, ask them
to be a good neighbor and say go two
miles out, go five miles out and hit the
people that are going to be infected.
Hit the citizens of this community that
will want to hear about what's happening
in their neighborhood, not just 300 feet
from where the property line is. Um,
let's see. There's five questions for
annexation. Okay, that's great. But I
heard so one of you up here, I think it
was Escabel say something about um the
zoning that you change it from
agriculture then IB then to light
industrial and it rolls on through.
Let's take that process and slow it up a
little bit. Um I I guess I heard the
real decision happens when you change
the zoning. They could buy the land for
a data center and leave it agricultural.
They can't put the data center there.
But then it rolls on through and it
changes into light business.
>> Ma'am, thank you.
>> Oh my god. Okay,
>> your your time is up. Thank you.
>> Okay, one one more quick thing. Somebody
says um how pause the effect uh to pause
a project, what's the effect? The
question should be if we pause a
project, what's the effect on the
citizens?
>> Thank you.
>> Welcome back again,
>> Mr. Gathering at K McAdams. I just have
a couple of questions. Um, I know the
oil and gas industry has strengthened
its bonding requirements over time to
reduce the chance of cleanup costs,
things like that in the state of
Wyoming.
We don't know how these data centers are
going to go, but I am asking this and
I'm hoping an answer will come from
Microsoft because they are being
represented here, but this includes all
data centers. Do data centers in Wyoming
have a fund like oil and gas to clean up
in case some something goes ary like our
water or our air? Something goes ary
with that and we don't know that. I
would like to see a fund established for
that. I'd like to see a delay so that we
can establish something a fund like that
because as a public citizen even oil and
gas companies ran into problems up in
Gillette and what oil and gas companies
do they tend to file for bankruptcy and
who picks up those orphan wells costs
the public does I do not want to pick up
environmental costs from these data
centers and that's a big concern I think
right here we don't live in Teton County
we live in Laramie County Oh, I don't
want to be a throwaway county. We have
an environment, too. So, could Microsoft
address this? Do you guys have a fund in
all your giving to the community? Have
you established a fund to in case you
have a water problem or an air problem
and people start addressing it? Can you
address that?
>> No fund. I I assume when there's not an
answer, they don't have an answer to it.
And I've watched these meetings and when
something when a company doesn't have an
answer, they're they're glad to talk
about LC, that minimum amount, but I'm
not happy with that. Nor am I happy with
the state incentives. They tout $11
million in taxes. Well, what if they'd
had their usage taxes on the Nvidia
chips and the GPUs? That's about 70
million that's lost. I'm asking you to
delay this. say no to the annexation.
Wait for your state government to do
something about this. Wait for your
county commissioners, but you want to
rush it through. So, two things. So,
there was no answer to that question. I
want you to think about that. I don't
want my air polluted. I don't want our
water polluted. And I don't want to pick
up the cost for that like we did for
Peabody Coal.
>> Mr. Escobel, did you need a break?
>> No, I just was going to say was my
comment was more about annexation, not
zoning. But as the mayor said, if we
don't annex, then it they'll still build
it, but they build it in the county. The
county does not have the regulations in
place like the city does. So, if you're
worried about something bad happening
out there, it's better that it's under
our regulations, which are some of the
strictest in the country.
Uh, also on the board of public utility
side, they have their own anonymity.
They don't
No. So there was nothing covered up.
>> Heather,
>> welcome back.
>> Yes. Thank you. Heather Madrid, Ward
One. Um, our regulations are awful.
They're not sophisticated by any any
wild stretch of the imagination. That's
why they come here. Um,
so okay. Um, also the lead's website is
probably the most biased source of
information. in one of their linked
articles is how all of the opposition is
Chinese funded. So that's the quality of
information that they're putting out and
they don't the industry doesn't count um
data center sites by location. The
industry counts by buildings and it
counts by capacity.
Um so I recently attended a meeting held
by Skybox and Via West about the data
centers the data center well centers
that they want to build on the Cox
Ranch. Similar to Microsoft, they do not
yet own this property from my
understanding. It's contingent upon
annexation or reasonzoning. I've heard
I've heard both things here tonight. Um,
the sale is contingent upon annexation.
That's where the similarities end.
Microsoft is about 2,300 times more
valuable than Skybox. Their walkway cash
value could buy Skybox entirely more
than 300 times. Despite the vast
difference in resources, Skybox managed
to at least produce a map of the
property they do not own with a mockup
of where and how many buildings there
will be. They know where the natural
waterways are, and they will not disrupt
those waterways. They know where the one
little waterway they will have to work
around is located. They know how wide it
is. They know exactly where the two
roads will be located to ensure
emergency vehicles and construction
vehicles can safely enter and exit the
property. They have addressed and
resolved the mausoleum issue. They will
allow the unused land to be grazed. They
gave out business cards with phone
numbers to call them directly if there
is an issue at any stage of development
or operations. They publicly answered
questions three times in a true Q&A
format, not a Q&A where questions were
submitted at least three days in
advance. That means they did not have
all of the answers scripted and
rehearsed before the test. Microsoft
drew lines around the property they want
to annex.
That's all. It's clear that Skybox is
being held to a different expectation.
Why? I read all the supporting documents
for every annexation today. I saw
information on where exactly existing
services are that the annex property
will connect to. I saw the exact fire
station that will service one of these
annex properties. The supporting
document for Microsoft is a copy paste,
but absolutely nothing specific which is
incredibly negligent with the magnitude
of this annexation is considered. I
tried to find documents proving
annexation criteria has been met. It
doesn't exist. not for the Cox Ranch and
not for Microsoft. The annexation
reviews consist of a one-page map. You
are relying on the city planners to
check boxes and that's all that's
happening prior to annexation. It
appears that they are the ones in charge
here. These annexations are illegal,
especially this Microsoft annexation.
This has nothing to do with property
rights and everything to do with process
and equal rules. I don't think anyone
cares that Lumus wants to sell her land.
The only reason Microsoft, to my
understanding, does not already own this
property is because they place
contingencies on the sale. Those
contingencies,
oh no, include a legal process that you
are not enforcing. If this was a simple
sale and purchase of private property,
as I stated before, they would be
talking to a real estate agent, not the
city council. If you annex this property
today illegally, you are creating a
major liability for yourselves. Thank
you.
Hello, sir. Hello.
>> Emil Lee Hazesnau, running for Laramie
County Commissioner. I live out in the
county and I'm watching my county shrink
tonight if you do this. Uh, I wanted to
clear up something here.
>> Mr. Haz, I just got to tease you a
little bit, sir. Your county is not
shrinking. The county is still the same
size.
>> It's the biggest county in the state,
and we want to keep it that way.
>> There you go, buddy.
Uh the story broke u July 8th.
That's why you came forth with the
information. It says Wyoming Titans.
Well, just go away then. Wyoming titans
its wastewater rules after META data
centers contractors flush contaminated
water. Meta said it was working with the
officials to be good neighbors. The
drinking water supplies were affected.
Officials of Wyoming said contractor for
Mark Zuckerberg.
He's the one that's accountable for
Meta, not the contractor.
This tech company Meta flushed bacteria
contamination water into the public
sewer sewers during construction
of a conraversal new AI data center.
50 states this weekend will protest data
centers clear across our country.
This isn't a small decision we're making
here.
What we need to do is put an 8month
delay on this and let the legislators,
the state of Wyoming,
go through how many data centers are
coming and put some regulations toward.
We've heard it tonight. to legislators,
whether they're Republican or Democrat,
they want the opportunity to have a
chance to have a legislative session on
this
what we're doing here. Also, and I'm
going to blow this thing wide open. I
went to uh Chuck Gray and I said, "How
come we can't put this on the ballot for
a vote?" 85% of the people are against
this. They're your bosses. They're the
ones coming here tonight asking you to
slow it down, delay this, get some more
research so Mr. Zuckerberg can't do what
he did already.
Let's put some regulations and let's put
some delays and some rules forward. It's
not going to hurt anybody waiting eight
months and let the legislators have a
time to fix this before we go forward
with it. I think that's the smart thing
to do. Yes, it will come to the county
commissioners. Our founding forefathers
put it real clear. They want you to own
a piece of property, so you'll have
property rights. But you're going to
respect your neighbors, they concluded,
because they have property rights, too.
One person could say, "I want to sell
this property and get annexed into the
city." You got to consider
the people that surround these areas and
what is going to be done and not one but
maybe 10 to 14 data centers would affect
their lives forever. Give it a delay
eight months and I would appreciate
that.
>> Thank you.
>> Good evening ma'am.
>> Me again.
Okay.
>> Through you, uh, since Emily discussed
the legislature,
so back in 2008, I'm serving on the
revenue committee. I wanted to get rid
of those exemptions.
They passed over 50 exemptions. Only
three findings in the tax reform 2000
for revenue did they pass. I wanted to
institute a corporate tax back then. I
thought we should raise the sales tax.
4% seemed a little low,
but I made the comment at that time to
the chairman, uh, Rodney Pete Anderson
out of Pine Bluffs that we should change
the name of the revenue committee to the
exemption committee because that's all
we were doing.
Now, if the legislature wants to reverse
course on that, I hope they do because
they're the reason these data centers
are coming here, the tax climate of
Wyoming, and that's a state issue. not a
city council issue. They come here
because we don't have a corporate tax
because we have a low sales tax because
we don't have a uh state income tax and
they give them those exemptions.
So, you want to stop data centers, go to
the Golden Dome.
>> Welcome, ma'am.
>> Thank you for being here.
>> Uh my name is Lynn Davis and I'm a
resident of Cheyenne
So, good evening, mayor and council
members. Uh, I'm not here to ask you to
reject these annexations.
Data centers have brought real jobs and
real investments to this community. I'm
here because I think there's a
significant gap in the process
and the council has the power to close
it tonight before these properties join
the city.
First, the projects before you tonight
are all being zoned business park.
That designation matters because it
exempts projects from bu being uh
projects built in in business parks from
being re reviewed for community impacts
through the state's own industrial
sighting act um which legislates the
insure the issuance of permits through
the department of environmental quality.
The exemption is also confirmed by
Cheyenne Leads, the area's economic
development organization.
By plan,
industrial devel industrial development
in business parks is exempt from
industrial sighting review and that's a
gap in the review process.
Many of the data centers being proposed,
as you know, are in fact large
industrial projects, many of which have
been approved for business parks use.
Second, that gap in in process played
out earlier this month when the city had
to suspend data center wastewater
discharges after a rare bacteria turned
up in the project site.
That was before it was even finished.
That's the kind of risk an industrial
sighting review catches early.
This one didn't. But here's the thing.
Nearly every data center in this
country, in this county, has been
approved without the state level
environmental review the legislature
built specifically for projects of this
size.
Third, a state bill to protect
rateayers, that's us, from having to
cover the grid costs of these projects
was drafted and never introduced.
And nothing has filled that gap.
So once this land is annexed, your
leverage is gone.
Tonight is the only night you have it.
This council is the only body positioned
to require those protections locally.
I'm asking you to condition these
approvals on an independent impact
review and a binding not voluntary
community benefit agreement.
Please hold these projects to the same
standard the still the state built for
the projects of their size and do it
tonight while you still can. Thank you,
>> Mr. Dwight.
Hello again.
>> Yeah, thank you. My name is Thomas
White. [clears throat]
Um,
for those Microsoft people that are
talking here, yes, you got a job here
already. Yeah, we're not talking about
you guys that have a job here. We're
talking about the people, the future of
these other data centers that are coming
in the around Cheyenne. And I notice
most of the data center is south of
Cheyenne. Why is it west, east, or
north? It's always the southside.
[clears throat] Second is um
you know pe sure there's jobs for people
that's for the data center but they
don't live near the data center. I do
going to be living near data center out
south of town that AI. I understand why
these people are worried. I am there's
construction dirt road flying dust and
everything.
And when they had that open house, I
talked to the guy at D Center. It wasn't
very nice. He said, "It's 12 miles from
Cheyenne." And I told him, "No,
you know, there's people live around
Terra Ranch. Probably like three to 400
people there. That's two miles from us.
That's not 12 miles. Those are the
things you got to consider like that.
Like you guys got this ones by Sweet
Grass Subdivision.
If they're thinking about building the
data center, what do you think those
people's gonna feel like that's going to
have that data center that's going to be
close to them? It's not going to be
good. It's not. My life has changed. And
a lot of people that I live around
there, I have a couple of that was
trying to move out just because the data
center, if you ever notice around the uh
United States, people are trying to stop
the data center because it's going too
fast. Yeah, sure. We got Microsoft here
already there. Yeah, it's working and
everything, but these are new ones that
are coming in more advanced. We don't
know exactly what goes on. The noise uh
radiation micro waves that flows into
the air. We don't know, you know, we
those microwave waves, we don't see it.
We don't feel it's just like X-ray. You
don't feel the X-ray. But later on, the
more you take, the more you start find
the results. And I just hopefully you
guys are listen to the people of the
citizen just figure how many people in
Cheyenne would be here if they knew
exactly what's going on. Sometime I
don't know when their meetings are even
for this county meetings they don't show
it on there. I hear from other people.
So just imagine what this place would be
like if everybody knew what was going on
here in Cheyenne. Especially the
outskirt of Cheyenne that are near those
data centers. It's easy for the people
in the middle don't care because they're
not near it. You guys don't live near
the data center. You guys go home and
enjoy, you know, but people that do live
near the data center are worried and I'm
one of them, you know, like this
incident happened that I'm not going to
talk about that, but that's all I got to
say.
>> Thank you, M.
>> Thank you.
>> Hi, ma'am. Welcome.
>> Okay. My name is Donna Frostto, Ward
One. Um, we come to these meetings all
the time. We say the same things. Um, it
just feels frustrating. You guys all get
paid, workers get paid, whatever.
Residents don't. We show up. Um, and
it's feels defeating that we show up and
it doesn't feel like we're hurt as much.
Yes, you guys had five votes already.
This is the first time since the water's
been contaminated that you actually that
the community actually found out about
it. Um, it just seems like things are
replaying again. I mean, we saw things
where the pandemic even did certain
things where they mandated things from
the top. The science declared it was
settled before the public could speak.
Driven on fear. I know that fear. I
almost lost my job. Um, all because I
questioned what was being shoved down
our throats. They weaponized our
paychecks. It feels like they're doing
the same thing again. Doing it again.
It's your your guys' jobs to not just
protect the buyers, but protect the
community around them. I've owned homes.
I get it. We have laws for the reason.
But it's also with these data centers,
thousands of acres are at risk right
now. The pot water, the power, um the
bacteria found in hid in the whatever
research with the utility just doesn't
make us feel comfortable coming out this
late.
um this is where we're trying to speak
up and all we're asking for is once
again not to skip the research um and
testing what these bill you know it
seems like we're fighting these billion
dollar companies and all I'm asking is
for a pause it's for the community it's
for the residents that are here for the
long term and that's all we're asking so
I hope you take that into consideration
>> thank you ma'am
>> thank you
>> welcome back
to get the microphone just exactly
Right.
>> I love that. Thank you so much.
>> Thanks. I uh I I would like to have you
consider the fact
>> remind us your name again. Okay.
>> Am I okay?
>> Remind us your name.
>> My name is Alex Bowler.
>> There you go. Thank you.
>> I represent the Shine Area Landown
Owners Coalition. And basically what I'm
here to say is two things. One is that
um these data centers need to be
considered as a system not as not as
data center A, data center B, data
center C, data center D and so forth.
They need to be considered as a system a
system of how it impacts the entire area
and as such the plan Cheyenne. The
second comment is the plan Cheyenne
becomes critical and we need to have
this plan Cheyenne updated not by
somebody who is affiliated with Cheyenne
leads but by an independent contractor
an independent contractor and so that we
can get an expert opinion somebody who
understands the ramifications of data
centers across the country. There are
4,900 data centers across the country,
31 in the state and 10, five and nine as
you've heard in uh Laramie County. So we
are the mecca of data centers. So first
of all we need to uh consider the data
center issue as a system not data center
A B C D and E but we need to consider
the total impact of the data centers in
Laram County and we need a the plan is
plan Cheyenne needs to be completely
reconstructed. It needs to be
constructed by an independent auditor
and not by a good buddy of Cheyenne
leads. Those are my two comments. I'm
going to answer the second question for
you. Uh we just did the interviews for
the plans Cheyenne consultant and they
um have selected I understand uh a
national firm that has experience doing
these things and not a good friend of uh
of our local people but bringing an
expert in to help us rewrite those
sections of plan Cheyenne. So, can you
guarantee me that it's going to be an
independent uh arrangement or not?
>> Yeah. Um, I don't remember the name of
the company, but that contract will be
coming before the city council here
soon. Uh, there was a I wasn't part of
it, but there was a committee that did
all the interviews and uh selected this
company and they will be um coming
before the governing body for approval
um uh to do that.
>> I appreciate the answer and as long as
it isn't leads, I don't care.
>> Yes, sir.
Sir, I'll stand for any questions you
might ask.
>> Thank you.
>> Good evening. My name is Lance Gold,
fellow Cheyenne resident. 13 years ago,
I packed up my family of six kids and
moved here to Cheyenne to work for
Microsoft.
Um
13 years ago when I was here I I moved
from Utah larger community but grew up
in Pokeell Idaho about the same size as
Cheyenne Wyoming and that's what
attracted me to this place.
I've talked with my wife several times
uh about what our plans are for the
future and uh consistently it's we've
loved to grow. We've grown to love
Cheyenne, the community, the people. Not
only that, but uh the six kids that I
brought here, all six kids have stayed
here.
>> Wow. They've uh my oldest who's 29 moved
away,
got married, moved back. My second, she
moved away, went to school, she moved
back.
This has become home
for my family of now nine.
We took in a girl that was kicked out of
her house her senior year of high
school.
There's been a lot of impact that my
kids and my family have had on this
community. Not big,
but every single person makes a impact
on people's lives.
This community
that I've learned to love and to grow in
has just been amazing. to my wife, to my
family. Um, and uh,
I can't say
I can, what I can say is is
I started out with Microsoft here.
Microsoft goes above and beyond the
normal statutes or the EPA requirements
and stuff like that.
I know a lot of you might not agree with
that, but that's one of the things that
I love about Microsoft.
I care deeply
about the environment, about the water
that we have.
And uh as I work with Microsoft as a
build manager,
as build manager for these projects, for
these data centers, I take it personally
responsible
to make sure that we don't pollute
water, that our air is clean, because
I've got skin in the game, and I've had
skin in the game for over 13 years.
Thank you. Thank you, sir. Welcome, sir.
You're tall. You're gonna have to bring
that microphone way up.
>> There you go. Thank you. Hope
>> that works. Okay.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Uh I'm Al Gates. I'm in Ward 3. I'm a
Sweetg Grass R uh resident.
Um I just like to make a quick comment
about planning. U the city has two huge
development areas, Sweetg Grass and this
new Microsoft area. They are right next
to each other. They go up line by line
up against each other. If I could make a
wish, my wish would be that some time be
taken to figure out exactly what kind of
buffer should occur between these two
huge developments and that that really
be clarified and and written down and
everybody be clear, especially before we
start making any zoning decisions. So,
that's my quick comment. Thank you.
>> Thanks for being here.
>> Hi again. Hello, Donna Dundon, Ward One.
Um, and the argument here is not if
Microsoft is good or bad for the
community. Microsoft's here. They've
been here. They've been good. They're
sharing their wealth. They're spreading
the money all over. They create jobs.
Um,
that's not what we're concerned with.
We're concerned with doing this right
the first time, taking our time, making
sure we have some facts, making sure we
have some signed agreements that will
legally hold up that we can fall back on
because without that, it's irresponsible
um progression. We can we we would never
do that. You wouldn't do it in marriage
these days. We'd have a you know a term
for uh getting married. Um,
and there's no reason to go into a
business with that. Microsoft isn't a
good neighbor. They are here. They
spread the wealth. They have the wealth
to share. Um, we're talking about the
jobs that they bring. They do bring
jobs, but do you also know how many
terminations they did within the last
year alone? Nationwide,
20,000.
Um, according to this, they've got 4,800
just in July 2026.
So, they're going to have jobs. You're
going to build their things for them.
You're going to plow the land. You're
going to expand it. You build the
buildings. You'll have technicians come
in. And when they're done with that,
there's going to be layoffs as well. So,
we know we we know they make the jobs,
but they also get rid of the jobs when
they don't need when they're no longer
needed. So 20,000 terminations in one
year is a significant decline for a
community
for for an employer.
How much how would that affect us when
they decide to pull out? We're just
asking go slow. Make sure you have the
contingencies. Make sure you have the
money, the funds invested so that if
there was an emergency and we needed
that, we have it and we could go ahead
with it. We're not asking for much. The
only urgency, and I'm going to say the
quiet part out loud. I know the only
urgency here are the people who want to
sell their land. They want their land
deal done. And that
person is right here at the Capitol
building. They want their land done. And
that's the only urgency that we see
happening. You even said the buildings
sit there for 10 to 20 years. the land
once they get it without doing anything
to it. Just make sure you have
everything, all the eyes and tees dotted
and crossed. We don't want to be a
statistic. We don't want to be on
Facebook memes going around the country.
We want to make sure we do it right. Do
it safe for everybody. Let Microsoft be
a good neighbor. Let us be protected
with the right documents in place.
That's all we're asking. Thank you.
Good evening. Welcome.
>> Hello, Hannah Jackson from W 3. Um,
mayor through you.
Um, this is the second time that Mr.
Escoal, to my knowledge, has stated to
his constituents with quite lax feeling,
go to the Golden Dome. We are going to
the Golden Dome. You saw three
representatives, three legislators here
today, but they need time. And while
we've asked for over and over is time.
So I would really like the comment Terry
to your constituents that obviously
elected you into this position to not be
so lax to not sound as if we're dumb
like I can't do it. Hands up here. We
can't do it. Well, we're talking to them
or they wouldn't be here saying that
they're looking at stuff. So the
commentary is where people get
frustrated with the council. So, if we
could stop downgrading
our constituents that you guys serve,
that would be great. Again, we just want
time.
>> One more time.
>> Stacy. Stacy, turn on the microphone,
please. It's not over.
>> Stacy Leech, Ward One. Thank you.
>> I have a probably a stupid question. Um
although I don't really know anybody who
actually has the answer to the question
and I've asked a lot of people. So maybe
hopefully you know since um this is what
we're here talking about. What exactly
is this data? What are they storing? Why
do we need 3,500 acres of building to
store? What data are they storing? Are
they storing it for Cheyenne, Wyoming?
Are they storing it for Larry County?
Are they storing it for the rest of the
country or the world? Are is it
surveillance data? Is it going to be
tied to flock cameras? Um, is it
artificial intelligence? Because I
prefer human intelligence. Um,
do you do you know what this data is and
why it takes over 3,500 acres worth of
building? Because this is only one
center we're talking about. Maybe
Microsoft can tell me what they're going
to do with this with this land. What is
Meta doing with their property? What are
all these data centers doing? And what
is the data that they're storing?
I know of two things that that happen in
data centers and that's cloud computing
and AI computing and I don't know
exactly which which data centers are
going to go into which areas but I think
it's those two areas to my knowledge.
So then you think that by adding
artificial intelligence data centers,
we're going to be able to keep our our
children employed because we're not
going to need there's a lot of a lot of
professions we're not going to need
anymore if we actually have real
artificial intelligence.
So we're going to be we're going to be
building ourselves out of careers.
nursing. I'll still have a job, but
doctors might not because you don't need
a doctor to stand there and write a
prescription when artificial
intelligence can do it for you. There's
um you're need construction workers.
They're going to need to build for us.
But there's a lot of there's a lot of
jobs we're not going to need,
unfortunately. Um I have attorneys in my
family and probably aren't going to need
a lot of attorneys because you're going
to have all you're going to have
everything in the web. So, what what
good are these data centers doing for
our our community?
Thank you.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Yes. To the mayor and to the council.
I'm Janet Tolman. I'm in Ward 3. Um, I
looked up on AI on the internet just to
ask how many people in Cheyenne are
employed by data centers
and it didn't answer. Um, I did get that
MET is going to have 1,100
in one spot and then in another spot
it's at 100. So, I mean, there's all
this talk about all these jobs and the
growth it's going to bring,
but I'm wondering about the people here
in Cheyenne going into those jobs or
will it be outsiders coming in? We don't
know that. We don't know that. We can't
say. And
no one has said, "Oh, there's going to
be 100 jobs and those people are going
to live here in Cheyenne or there's
going to be 50 jobs and those people are
going to live here in Cheyenne."
I haven't heard or seen that data. So,
to me,
it doesn't feel comfortable. I've heard
three people that say they live in
Cheyenne
tonight.
one wasn't originally from Cheyenne.
>> So that [snorts] this is what a question
that I have. You know, my parents, my
grandparents came here and my father
um had four kids and three of us are
still here.
Um
yeah, we're natives.
We chose to stay here.
We made the decision to love this place.
Boy,
>> and that's something that you can't buy.
You can't buy that with a data center.
People are either going to like Wyoming
and Cheyenne or they're not going to
like it. I don't know of anybody
personally that I've talked to that says
it's okay. They'll either say I hate it
or I really love this place and that's
why I've been living here.
So, I don't know. That's just something
that we don't have like more specifics
on and it would be nice to have more
specifics on that. You know, they say
that we're going to have enough water,
we're going to have electricity, our
costs aren't going to go up. But is in
that is that in an agreement that our
costs aren't going to go up? Because
I've read on the internet
that
complaints from people living in areas
where data centers came and their
electricity went up three times what it
cost before. their water went up three
times more than what it cost before.
So that would be a question that I would
have. Is it possible to have that in
writing somewhere that we won't have to
bear those extra costs?
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Mr. Mayor, can I respectfully ask for a
recess?
>> We've been at this four hours. I think
it's appropriate. Why don't we take a
10-minute recess? We'll come back at
10:10.
Ladies and gentlemen, I'd like to call
this meeting back to order, please.
>> All right, ladies and gentlemen, we're
going to call this meeting back to
order. Um,
so I've noticed we've started to have
some people start to duplicate
themselves as far as uh testifying. And
so I'd ask if you've already testified
on this issue, uh maybe have a seat.
We'll let everybody who has not had a
chance to testify, let's get them in
first. And then um I would also ask you
know if you got something new to say
that would be great. We've had a couple
hours worth of testimony now and um so
if you have something new to add I think
that'd be great. Um and we'll go out to
Mr. Nicely first.
>> Yeah. David Nicely 200 Wshide. Um, in
the interest of uh rebuilding trust uh
between the community and the city
council,
um
I would like to see a comprehensive list
of all the NDAs that the Cheyenne leads
the economic development wing of the
city has with whomever. Um they don't
have to tell us what they're not
disclosing, but for instance you, Mr.
Mayor, at least the Cowboy State Daily
reported you as saying um when you
announced in 2024 the meta was coming
that you could were overjoyed that you
could say it because you were no longer
under an NDA. So I would like to see a
comprehensive list of all the NDAs that
Cheyenne Leadeds has, any other the
board of public utilities, any other
public agencies,
um every member of the city of Cheyenne
and the governing body of the city of
Cheyenne so that we know
who has agreements
and who doesn't have NDA agreements. So
we at least know what the scope of those
of the of the issue of transparency or
lack of transparency is.
Um because there is a great deal of
distrust.
Um Dr. Renie expressed it when he said
um you don't trust us but I don't trust
you more than you don't trust
us. And that's a problem. It bothers me.
Um,
back in February, I asked the city and I
promised that we would be kind and
respectful.
Um, Dr. Emmens asked that we add
trusting. I'd love to trust you,
but I don't feel like you're being
square with us.
I don't think we're being told
everything.
Um, so I would like to have you all
promise to give us a comprehensive list
of all the non-disclosure agreements
that you all are involved in, that any
city agencies are involved in, and that
any pseudo governmental bodies are
involved in. I just asked Miss Hail um
and she said, "I don't have to disclose
that. We're private."
Well, which is it? Are you the economic
development wing of Cheyenne or are you
a private privately funded organization?
Um, and maybe maybe you'd like to
address that. Is Cheyenne Leads
a government representative
acting on behalf of Cheyenne or is it a
private entity?
If they don't have to disclose it,
should they?
Thank you,
>> Mr. Nicely. So maybe we can answer a lot
of those questions right now. Okay. The
city of Cheyenne
um its employees have zero NDAs
with the exception of the mayor and I
have one NDA and that's with leads and
I've disclosed that here tonight a
couple of different times and those are
four things that I learned during the
board meetings. But any activities that
I take on as mayor like if you were to
come to my office and you want to talk
about a business um relationship and
you're working with leads that would be
a public document. Anything you give me
would be a public document.
>> But you had one with Meta previously.
>> No, I did not.
>> It came through leads.
>> No, I told you I've only signed one NDA
in my in my life.
>> The Cowboy State Dailies report in 2024
was wrong.
>> Oh boy.
>> Mr. Nicely. I've had I've signed two
NDAs in my life, both with leads. My
first term as mayor, my second term as
mayor, and that's it. No member of this
governing body has an NDA. No city
employee has an NDA. Leadeds is an a
private nonprofit 501c4 I believe it is
or six, excuse me, um that uh we
contract with to help us with some of
our economic development things. Just
like if we were to hire you to for some
farm stuff um as as a private
individual, that doesn't make you a
quasi governmental agency because we
enter earn a contract with you for
something that you might provide like an
educational uh thing or something you
might do. And so um I I think that
answers all the question you just asked.
There is only one NDA that I know of um
that is in the city and I'm pretty
positive I'm the only one and that's
only because of my position as a board
member of leads.
>> I'll just reiterate to Mr. Nicely I've
never signed. I've never seen one.
>> All right.
>> I think that I think all my colleagues
would probably be the same way.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> yes.
>> Could we to help Mr. nicely out. If any
of us has signed an NDA, will you please
raise your hands?
>> Question nicely. We don't have any.
>> Okay, that's great. Um, and and then the
next question would be, do you all
promise to tell us
>> everything you know immediately when you
know it that might affect us? As in in a
job interview, you ask the question, are
there any other things I ought to know
that I haven't asked? or are there any
questions that I should ask? Do you
promise to tell us anything we need to
know when we need to know it?
>> Mitch, I said we will do everything we
can to be transparent with you, sir, and
I believe we've done that.
>> So, what happened with respect to the
contamination at Meta? Why was it 6
months or five months?
>> This is an annexation question because
it's related to trust.
Mr. I honestly don't know why it took
six months. Um
>> well when did you know?
>> I was told sometime this spring that um
an incident had happened and uh that BOP
was looking into it and um and that's
what I that's what I learned and what I
heard and then I think all of us learned
the extent of that here just a week or
so ago.
But honestly, I did hear that there was
an incident that happened.
Not a lot of details, sir.
>> Okay.
>> Bryce, did you want to
>> You want me to
>> I mean, you're here and it would be
great. You're here from the board of
public utilities. I would love
to do that. Thank you.
>> Yeah. Uh my name is Bryce Door. Uh I'm
an engineer with the Board of Public
Utilities. Um, in terms of the release,
um, I can't speak to all of the details
in terms of what happened and why the
decisions were made. Um, I can tell you
this that we will be providing a
detailed timeline of what happened. Um,
as well as some answers to some of the
questions that we have seen in some of
the public um, public information
requests. Um, with that I will tell you
that uh the bacteria that was in the
water is not something that any
industrial type of situation would ever
want in their plant. Um, it is something
that thrives in heavy metal areas. So,
anytime that you would put it in a metal
pipe, it would be something that could
degrade that infrastructure. So, it is
not something that was intentionally in
there. So it was not something that was
ever disclosed to us as something that
would be tested for. So in terms of the
industrial sighting process all of that
none of that would have identified it
either. And I will tell you that when
you are saying that or there is the
concern that maybe we are not doing what
we need to do to protect the public. We
understood that this was something that
is new to Cheyenne in terms of these
closed loop cooling systems. They are
not a new technology. It is something
that is used in many industrial
processes but is not something that we
had seen before. So we took precautions
that created a system that had
everything that was discharged from that
system that was held in a holding tank
that we had to sample before it could be
released to the public water system,
public wastewater system, excuse me. It
was never in the drinking water supply.
Whatever is going on on Facebook, social
media, that never occurred. the drinking
water supply was never in at risk. Okay.
Um so we sampled for what they
anticipated to be in that water and it
was to a standard that we believe that
we could treat. So the only thing that
we can understand that may have happened
is that whatever vessels they were using
on site for this process may have been
contaminated to a point to where now we
have set up the rule that says you will
not discharge to the public wastewater
system period until we learn more about
what's going on and we can understand
what's what happened exactly from them.
So we have an ongoing thing. We're
trying to get more answers. We're trying
to understand further of what what has
happened. Um, I will let you know that
the reason that we shut the the
wastewater treatment or the reuse system
where it is aerosolled and it's sprayed.
That was what in our research we found
was the most potential risk for human
health, which is why we shut down the
reuse system as soon as we found out. It
ran for one night
and it was at a time when no one would
have been on the park. It, excuse me, it
wasn't a park. It was only the Prairie
View Golf Course for one night.
There was nobody there. There was not a
risk. We did not want to create public
panic. We did not foresee it. This is
the same process. We've said this
multiple times. We treat everybody the
same. We've had releases from the
refinery, other industrial users. We've
had concrete show up in the wastewater.
They're not things that we always just
if there's not a immediate risk to
public health, it's not something that
we want to create a public panic over.
What has happened with the with social
media and all of the things it has kind
of been an explosion and I get why
you're scared.
I It makes total sense, but I promise
you I
I have worked for big corporations. I've
worked for Pepsi, Gatorade, and Heiser
Bush. I have taken a pay cut every time
along my career until I've landed in
this position. And what I value most
about this position is that I get to
protect my community.
And I know that that's what all of these
people are here to do, too.
To be public servants to you all. And I
understand why maybe it doesn't seem
that way, but there are only certain
things that we can control. And there
are certain things with data centers or
other industries that can be a challenge
and that can be scary. But the things
that we can control at our level, what
we have the ability to work with, we are
doing our best to protect this community
and do what's best for the community.
And like I said, there will be more
information coming out. But if there is
any time that anyone would like to come
and have conversations with us about
what happened and not get the
information from a third party that's
repeated the same information 50 times
over until who knows what it is the game
of telephone,
feel free to come and talk to us. We'd
be happy to talk to you and I can stand
for any further questions.
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> Mayor Collins through you. Um Bryce, my
understanding is that this has now
become our standard with all data
centers is that for discharge water that
the water will be discharged into t a
tank and the water is then tested before
it's released into our public system. Is
that accurate?
>> Uh Mayor Collins through you. Um for the
time being uh we will not be accepting
any discharge from closed water uh
cooling systems um until further notice.
That's we're we're we're following
industry um you know best practices,
lessons learned, paying attention to
what's happening all over the country um
so that we can better educate ourselves
um on what to look for, how to address
these things. Uh but until further
notice um whatever wastewater is pulled
out of um these facilities and and I
also had a stint as um a groundwater
remediation engineer and there are
facilities that are designed to to treat
these specialized type of industrial
wastes and that's where these these
companies are taking this water is to
one of those facilities. The plant that
we have it is designed to treat
municipal waste. There are different
processes and technologies that you need
to treat industrial waste water and that
is where these facilities are trucking
this water to when they do these fill
and flush and kind of maintenance
operation. So what happened this first
time is not a standard practice. It's
different than what will happen for the
lifelong operation of the facility.
>> Dr. Mayor Collins threw you a couple of
follow-up questions. The first being um
one of the questions that was asked
tonight by an individual and I'm sorry
I've taken uh three pages of notes and
so I don't remember which person asked
this but the question was how do you
know that that water is actually I
actually it may have been you that asked
this Robin um is where do how do you
know that water is actually being taken
and it's being done with what it was
supposed to be done with and treated um
and that it's not just being dumped
somewhere. Is there some sort of a
certification process that a company
goes through to say, you know, we took,
I don't know, 300 barrels of water that
were contaminated off to this company
and this is the the certification we
have showing that they received 300
barrels of contaminated water.
>> So, in sorry, Mr. Mayor through you. Um,
in my experience, um,
there are certain industries where it
depends on who regulates that process.
In my experience, that was DEQ. We had
to, uh, fill out, um, um, chains of
custody that showed where that water
goes and understand how that all
happens. Uh, that is not something that
as a municipal
uh, sewer operator that we manage that
process. that would be something that
would most likely be either a DEQ or an
EPA type of regulatory situation. Um,
people can break the rules. They can
take it and put where they want it.
That's not something that we can
regulate. Um, but I know from a
industry best practice, you would be
very foolish to take a big tanker of
something and dump it on the ground
somewhere without the proper permits to
do that.
>> Follow up.
>> One more.
>> Have um EPA and DEEQ been involved in
this process since it happened in
February?
>> Uh, absolutely. Uh, Mr. Mayor, through
you. Uh, that was our first first step
is, hey, who can we talk to to learn
more about this thing? um is it
dangerous? What do we need to do with
it? Um are there major concerns? Um and
I think that the answers that we got
from the EPA and DEEQ, um we reached out
to um public health, county public
health, um and from everything that we
got back with that, you know, it was not
something that was um something that
anyone was very familiar with or
understood the majority of the risks
for. So that's why out of an abundance
of caution, we decided to
shut down that system, no longer put it
in into the aerosol type form and clean
it out the best we can and and keep that
system shut down until we're able to
kind of process it through and kind of
flush it through um our wastewater
treatment plant to where we thought that
it was um at a low enough level um to
where we could turn that system back on.
And that's when we decided to notify
everyone that there's the potential for
it to be there. Um, but at that time and
I think within the week of us turning it
back on, it was it was non detected in
our plans any longer.
>> Mr. Moody,
>> thank you. Thank you, sir. I'm still
curious why it took this long. Actually,
Congresswoman Hegman, future Senator
Hegman, actually said Wyoming residents
have the right, this is from her, to be
informed as soon as the contaminations
occur to make informed decisions
surrounding their own health and safety.
That's our future United States senator.
You want to comment on that?
Uh, unfortunately I can't comment on
that at this time, but like I said, we
will be um providing formal documents um
that will address some of those um those
answers. But I think from a general
standpoint, um it's our standard
practice to make sure that we have the
full story unless there is an immediate
um public health risk um that that could
be happening.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through you, um I
wanted to clarify about public health.
Um the Cheyenne Larmy County Public
Health was notified uh three days I
think before the press release went out
about the exposure
and that was after a thorough um
uh what I want to say
communication with both about all the
processes they had gone through and the
the fact that there was no bacteria IA
showing up at all in the water at that
time. Um, no one at the health
department had dealt with this bacteria
before. It is found in the uh naturally
occurring in the ground.
>> Yes.
>> So, it's not that it's unheard of. It's
just not something that's common. It
really likes copper pipes. So when it
was in the vessel that it was in, it
took to the pipes really well.
Um, yeah, really like those. Um, but at
that point, like I said, we reviewed all
of the actions that was taken by DEEQ
and the state lab and it was clear that
I mean we uh Department of Health
doesn't have any regulation over um that
it would all have gone to DEEQ
regardless.
So, I just wanted to throw that out
there, too.
Well, I thought it was important if the
de uh the board of public was here, we
could answer those questions, but I
think we probably should get back on
item number 13 now. So, Bryce, thank you
for being here standing up and doing
that. Um, welcome, ma'am.
Hi there. Uh, Shay Fifer, W 2. Uh, don't
have a script, so forgive me. Um, just
speaking because
I guess I don't appreciate, I guess,
being treated like we're just feel
fearful and scared. We just want to be
have information you know and informed
citizens are governed citizens and you
know that's the only way we can
safeguard our liberty. Um
and shuffling us off to the state and
sleeping and giving us actually no real
answers or the head bobbing and the eye
rolling
that is very much noticed and not
appreciated.
You know we voted you in to your
positions
for a reason. Um, I've moved all over
the country and I came back here and I
moved to Cheyenne. I didn't move to a m
community named Microsoft
and I think annexing this property
without having any sort of plan tonight
and then going right to 14 and 15 and
reszoning [clears throat] them to a
business park which is a misnomer I
think um is just insane because you're
going to have no leg to stand on if you
do this so quickly in one night. have
plans, have safeguards, you know, have
some rules and regulations. That's like
that's what we're asking for. Not a
year, not 18 months. Just have some
plans in place before you do use your
leverage because 3,500 acres is a ton of
property.
And don't like I know we know it's what
it's going to be, but what about
everything else? Everything else.
Everything. You know, it's just I'm not
scared. I'm concerned, but I like to
have information, you know, so that we
can all, you know, make educated
decisions on things. And
I don't know. I don't know. It's just
it's very disheartening. It's very
disheartening.
So, you give this to them without
without anything, with no plan in place.
I don't care if it's 10 or 20 years or
30 years. I plan to be here, but, you
know, we need safeguards in place. And
you know, $1.3 million, I think they
said at a city council meeting a couple
of of weeks ago, over 10 years, that's
chump change. 40 trees, that's
ridiculous. You can rate the state of
Nebraska and they will send you 200
trees for free. For free.
I mean, Microsoft could afford to give
every resident of Cheyenne a million
dollars and they would still be
billionaires.
And I'm like taking a tally and I know
it's probably not totally accurate, but
one two three four five six seven yeses.
Seven yeses on the like we're for this.
All getting paid. You know the nos,
nobody's getting paid.
We're just concerned.
Just don't lose your leverage so
quickly. You know, you do have a lot of
power.
You have a lot of power. So take that
seriously.
Have you already spoken on this issue,
ma'am?
>> Yes, but I have something to add within
what I'm saying.
>> So, I'm Jane Leinger. I have a property
in the in W one and I live in the
county.
>> Miss Leinger, you have to do it really
quickly, okay? I think it's unfair to
keep us here all night with you. Keep
coming back over and over again. Okay.
>> This is only my second time. Thank you.
>> It's one too many.
>> Thank you.
And I'll notice I've got about half a
minute already taken up on this. For our
community, slow down. Make a plan that
includes all the data centers for not
just the city, but also for what's going
on in the county going forward. We need
to know what's going on. Um we need to
know how it's going to affect all our
services. Skybox, Google, Meta,
Facebook, Microsoft, they plan and I
heard in one meeting they plan because
here because they want to be close to
each other. They have done this
intentionally and they're smart about
it. We need to be as smart. We need to
be excuse me.
You can change the business park
designation so it includes the things
like the ISC, the DEEQ and the EPA.
So our citizens are protected in
information is power. Let's get the
information for the citizens. Have the
impact studies. Have the corporate
agreements. If skybox can show a full
plan, all other developers can do the
same. Make it a requirement. Hear the
consent. Hear the voice of the majority
of the people here. Slow down. Plan.
Inform. Be transparent. A pause for the
people is not going to hurt the
companies. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Hi, ma'am.
>> Am Short Elizabeth Marvin. I live over
in the uh Willow Pond neighborhood. Um
hi, it's late. How are you? Um we
appreciate your time.
I was listening to the live stream and I
drove over here at 10 o'clock at night
after finding a babysitter um
just to like
really make sure I was heard because I
can't figure out how to get to the
online part of it. I don't know where
it's hiding.
Whatever. Um,
I am this mystical, magical youth that
you guys keep talking about wanting to
attract back to Wyoming.
I grew up here. I went to the South
Triad schools. I was the inaugural class
of South High.
I fought tooth and nail. I did this
great thing where I married an Air Force
guy, so we immediately had to move away.
But I fought tooth and nail to bring my
kids back to Cheyenne because I love
this community.
And if we're going to annex and make
Cheyenne City proper bigger, I would
love if you guys would keep possession
of the land,
build a Thanksgiving's point type park
thing,
revitalize the old depot, make it a
passenger line again, do a a
a what is the word?
I can't even remember. Do do holiday
trains, do Halloween trains, do There's
only this much. If you look online,
there's only this much rail line that's
not built
on the top end of the state. Make it one
big circle.
Adopt the bison contract. Do things that
are good for our state.
Don't quit selling out. Like don't don't
don't give the guys that have a reason
to say pretty please
who have more information than us
all of the cookies. Like please.
[laughter]
I'm telling you I came back because I
remember Cheyenne being fantastic. I
brought my kids here because I remember
Cheyenne being fantastic.
And I'm like,
if it wasn't demeaning, I would be on my
knees. Please,
please hear us when we're saying no.
Please don't trust these corporations
just because they have pretty words and
numbers.
I don't have a million dollars or I
would buy it myself. Like, I would do it
right now. I would open on every weird
empty corner a farm stand or something.
I would do things if I could, but we we
want we asked you to do those things for
us. Please, please,
>> have you spoken on this issue yet, sir?
>> I have one question for you.
>> Can you do it quickly, please?
So, uh, I appreciate you guys'
clarification on the fact that there
isn't NDAs and that we've kind of gotten
that out of the way. Um, I I did hear
through the grapevine. Um, Mr. Mayor,
that you may have gone on a fishing trip
with some Microsoft executives. So, I
guess I ask you in the uh in the
[clears throat] faith of uh transparency
um since you don't have an NDA, if you
would like to disclose uh the things
that you guys might have talked about on
that trip. I can tell you I did not go
on a fishing trip with Microsoft
executives. I did go on a fishing trip
with my brother-in-law. Um, he doesn't
work for Microsoft. He's self-employed.
Um, but I've never gone on a a fishing
trip or any sort of an excursion or
anything with any sort of a data center
company, sporting event, you name it.
I've never done that.
And I'm not sure any of member of the
governing body has either. I would I
would be very surprised if the answer to
that was yes.
Yes, ma'am.
Hello, Mr. Mayor. Um,
I was kind of expecting a firstname
basis, you know, kind of like Microsoft
Corporation representatives tonight, but
apparently you don't know me like that.
So, hi, I'm Anna Cordova, Ward One, and
I'd like to just bring us back to again
the five questions that um are part of
this application. And I'd like to direct
you to the exact wording of the answer
given to question one, which is
annexation of the area is for the
protection of the health, safety, and
welfare of the persons residing in the
area and in the city or town. And all
portions of that question must be
satisfied for um this council to move
forward with this annexation.
So their response, the annexation of
this property will increase the health,
safety, and welfare of the future
occupants. By being in the city limits,
the property will receive access to city
fire and police and sanitation services
as they are extended to the area as it
develops. This will allow for
coordinated fire and response and a
larger response, improving emergency
service coverage for future development
in the area. By being within the city
limits, the property will be able to
connect to the city services such as
water and sewer. Access to city water
and sewer instead of relying on private
wells and septic systems reduce
long-term groundwater impacts that could
also affect downgraded downgradient
properties. Now, someone earlier uh at
this meeting brought up the fact that um
these applications should also be in the
best interest and for the health,
safety, and welfare of those in the
city. With a previous annexation that
was given lip service, there was a
feeling that it would be of benefit to
the city. In the literal application
posted online and given as evidence for
why this annexation should move forward,
we're not even given lip service. We're
not even told this annexation would
result in great economic development for
the city. were not told it would provide
jobs or would somehow feed into making
the city and its health, safety, and
welfare better in any me in any
measurable way. Again, this council is
being brought here today to vote on
whether this application is valid. And
one of those points is whether or not
all five of the questions that are
required in the application are answered
satisfactorilally.
In my opinion, question one is not it
doesn't even give lip service. It's not
even a feeling. It's not a study has
been shown or so many millions of
dollars will be um added to the city's
revenue. [snorts] Please vote no. Thank
you.
>> Jennifer, do you have anybody online?
>> Yep. Kathy Sigaliano, you can go ahead.
Hi Kathy.
>> Hello. Good evening. Kathy Sigliano,
Ward 3. Um, I just wanted to stay on
here long enough to oppose uh this
annexation. I'm sure someone is doing
tally marks on for and against. Um,
I also just wanted to bring up a reason
why I'm opposed to this is because, um,
when I worked at Codal Banker over 5
years ago, um, a blueprint of a plan was
shown for the Sweetg Grass area and
definitely nowhere in that blueprint was
um, a data center. It was supposed to be
housing, a convention center,
restaurants, shopping. You guys built
the tunnel going to the college because
it was hopes that any students that may
live in Sweetg Grass could bike or walk
to the college without having to worry
about connecting in a different area or
running across um college. Um I'm sure
that the people who have bought homes in
that area are probably taken back um
that they will now be next door to a
data center. um and the HLS that were
fiercely fighting their annexation with
Wer a few months back. Um I've had
extensive talks with her and we all know
how she feels about the annexation of
her property and now this data center
possibly going in in who knows how many
years um within about 300 ft of her
property line. And we've talked a lot
about Meta and Microsoft and whoever
these data centers are being good
neighbors and um the health and safety
well-being of the people around these
areas that are being annexed. And I just
I feel like you guys are just completely
ignoring that. And I don't know if it's
because you're afraid to say no to these
corporations because you don't want to
be labeled as a, you know, city that's
not favorable to corporations coming to
our town. Um, a few people have said it
tonight that they feel you're more
favorable to the corporations than you
are the citizens of Cheyenne. and the
fact that this contamination happened in
February. Um, Cowboy State Daily said,
mayor, that you knew about it when it
happened immediately, but tonight you
said you just found out about something
in the spring. So, I would like
clarification on exactly when you did
know this happened and what exactly you
did know when it happened because those
two statements are contradicting each
other. Um, we need transparency and the
city has not gotten it or the citizens
haven't gotten it from the city and I
really really hope that you're listening
to the citizens tonight. I know we're
not your only constituents as Dr. Emmens
mentioned. Um, but you have clearly
heard over and over with months of these
talks that the citizens don't want any
more of these or at the very least to
pause them. Thank you. Anybody else?
Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> We can hear you.
>> Um, excuse me.
Uh, okay. [sighs]
Mayor Collins, members of the city
council, and city attorney Brody for the
permanent administrative record. My name
is Charles Miller, I'm stepping to the
microphone on item 13 to issue a formal
constructive notice of statutory
invalidity.
You're about to rubber stamp the 3,500
acre Highlands annexation to facilitate
a flexible business park zoning
designation. I am placing this body on
notice that doing so directly violates
the core evidentiary requirements of
your own unified development code and
your August 2025 data center noise
standards.
Do not let city staff shield you with
the excuse that noise is an issue left
for future administrative enforcement.
Your own UDC definition creates an
immediate mandatory legal threshold for
the initial zoning classification
itself.
The code states verbatim that an
industrial use includes data centers
which consistently produce noise
discernable at the property line. This
text creates a fatal procedural trap for
tonight's vote. And to legally classify
this 3,500 acre tract as a business park
rather than heavy industrial. You must
pro possess substantial empirical
evidence proving today that this
multi-gawatt development will remain
completely silent at its outer
perimeter. But your own transcript
proves you possess an absolute
evidentiary void. Microsoft's land
manager openly confessed on the record
that they do not have detailed design or
engineering plans for this campus. Yet
your city noise policy strictly requires
acoustic measuring measurements
reflecting typical full load conditions.
It is a mathematical and legal
impossibility for this council to adopt
formal findings of fact verifying a
business park classification when the
applicant admits the acoustic telemetry
does not ex exist. This issue is fully
ripe tonight because you are granting a
permanent entitlement over a ghost
project. If you bypass this step, you
are repeating the exact failure that
cost your neighbors 45 miles west their
zoning power. In McGan verse Laramie,
the Wyoming Supreme Court ruled that
sight specific map changes cannot be
treated as flexible political votes.
They are quasi judicial acts requiring
rigorous factual support. Your own board
of adjustment generates detailed written
findings every month because they know
generalized staff handouts cannot
substitute for a clean microphone
record. By voting yes over this data
void, you are consciously creating a
regulatory blind spot to help a trillion
dollar developer evade the socio
economic
>> Thank you, Mr. Miller. Your time's up.
Anybody else?
All right. Is there anybody else who
hasn't spoken tonight that wants to?
>> All right. Hearing none, we'll go to Dr.
Aldridge for a motion.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Emmens.
>> All right. Comments for members of the
governing body on item number 13, the
annexation
um of 3,459 acres.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend.
>> Okay. So, uh for the public to know,
it's on the second page of the
ordinance. So under section five of the
ordinance, it says that this ordinance
shall be enforced in effect upon its
publication. I'd like to cross out upon
its publication
in and then insert
on January 25th, 2027.
>> Is there a second?
>> Second.
>> All right, that was seconded by Mr.
Wolf.
All right, here we go again.
Does anybody want to talk about setting
this back until January 25th of 2027?
Jennifer,
Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Mr. Miller.
>> Um, can can you hear me?
>> We can hear you.
>> Uh, Mayor Collins, members of the city
council, uh, Mayor Through you, I'm just
wondering if, uh, I might be able to ask
a question and then have you pause my
time. Uh, what is what is the desired
purpose here for this? If if the um if
is that Mr. Moody? Could he just explain
what the purpose is of of this
amendment?
>> Mr. Moody.
>> And then could you pause my time?
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. A lot of people
have been asking for us to slow down and
pause. This is six months. That's why I
chose that.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Um Okay. And so slowing down and pausing
uh what is able to take uh what what
changes are able to be made if you were
I mean the what is it going to
what's it going to do just
it's not going to change anything right
it's just going to
uh extend the effective date is that
correct
>> correct
>> yep
>> um but then I had another one for Mr.
Moody. Um, [clears throat] my research
indicates that Mr. Moody was part of the
board of adjustment. Um, and that right
before he was uh
elected for this seat. I'm wondering if
he has uh any anything that he can say
about uh the difference between
legislative and quasi judicial like the
findings of fact that are
>> require that has nothing to do with
what's before us today. I'm sorry. We're
not looking Mr. Miller. All we're
talking about is moving the effective
date from immediately upon publication
to January 25th.
>> Well, maybe I could start talking about
the meta contamination considering you
just allowed other people to go quite
into.
>> You're out of order. Do you have
anything you want to say about the
effective date?
>> Um, I just urge you guys to to vote no
on the entire thing until
you can get more information in regards
to how it's going to affect everybody.
Thanks. Jennifer, do you have anyone
else?
>> Kathy Sigliano, you can go ahead.
>> Hi, Kathy Sigliano. W three. Um, I guess
I would be opposed to um Councilman
Moody's amendment simply because I think
if he's going to propose any kind of um
delay, it should be after the
legislative session so that the
legislators had time to do their work.
Um, since that's been indicated a few
times from some council members. Thank
you.
>> Anyone else? Jennifer, anyone else in
the audience? Mr. Madrid, Miss Madrid,
>> Heather Madrid, Ward One. I I feel like
I have to get up and say that I support
this because I don't want my silence to
be mistaken as that I don't support
this. And I think the purpose would be
there would be different counsel. There
would be time to negotiate a community
benefit agreement. But I think that and
I'm just this is a suggestion. I don't
know if it's allowed technically, but
maybe we could just do a show of hands
of who supports this and who doesn't and
that people who vote have to be
people who live here. Um, not trying to
cut off anybody else's opportunity to
talk. Obviously, people can come up, but
I have a feeling a lot of people won't
because we're exhausted. And I don't
want it to be confused again that our
silence is we don't support this um
amendment.
Understood. Anyone else?
>> Okay. McAdams. And I would wait till 17,
but um I'm concerned it's going to be a
yes vote. I I appreciate you moving that
date because people want time.
I want everyone to think about the scale
of what we're discussing. Wyoming state
government operates on about 5 billion a
year. Microsoft earns roughly 100
billion in annual profit. In other
words, one company can earn the
equivalent of Wyoming's entire annual
state budget in less than three weeks.
This isn't an argument against data
centers. It's an argument for making
sure Wyoming negotiates from a position
of strength. These companies have
enormous financial resources. That means
we should carefully ask whether the tax
incentives, water use, power demands,
and long-term commitments are truly in
the best interest of Wyoming citizens.
We should know exactly what we are
giving, exactly what we are getting in
return and exactly who bears the costs
decades from now. Wyoming has valuable
assets, our land, our water, our energy,
and our communities. Those assets belong
to the people of Wyoming. We should
welcome investment, but we should also
ensure that any agreement is fair,
transparent, and leaves future
generations better off when we found
them. We only have 271
votes in the state of Wyoming. We are so
bitty, but I want the power of our vote
to be there against these mega
corporations. Already in Wheatland,
another data center proposed. We need to
wait. I'm asking you for a no vote cuz
then I'll have to stay here till 17 and
come up with some other reasons. So
please no or at least delay. Thank you.
>> Ma'am,
this is on the
effort to u move the effective date till
January 25th, 2027.
>> Mr. Mayor and council members, I just
want to come up. I just that's we're
asking just for time. If that's if if
Mr. Moody's, you know, if his amendment
gives us that time, do it. I mean,
that's all we're asking because there's
too many unknowns. And it gives those of
us, even if you're going to do it anyway
at some other time, it gives us time to
get our own answers. And please just
just give us that time,
>> ma'am. As I understand it, if we vote
for this, um the annexation will pass.
It just won't become effective for six
months.
>> And it gives us time to get our answers.
>> Okay.
>> Anybody else?
>> All right. How about from the governing
body?
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you through you. Um,
Mr. Moody's brought a motion that I I
actually brought in front of the public
service committee at their last meeting.
Um, the original motion said two things.
Um, delay the effective date of the
annexation until the end of the year.
And, uh, purpose of that delay would be
to allow the mayor to negotiate a
community benefits agreement with
Microsoft. Um,
if there was ever an annexation
that called out for more time, it's this
one. Um,
and
and in large measure because,
you know, Microsoft told us this is a 10
or 20 year project out.
Um we have so much about this that we
don't know.
Um and um and we could know and I have
felt that we ought to keep the
city and the mayor's office in a
position where they can actually
negotiate from some strength.
But the motion when I brought up by the
public service committee didn't garner
enough support to pass. Um and um I'm
sure it won't hear either, but I do
speak in favor of it. Uh Mr. Mayor,
thank you.
>> Dr.
>> Mr. Mayor, can the um bringer of the
motion to amend I have the same
questions Mr. Miller had. I guess it's
like what other than just delaying six
months and having this argument again in
six months what is going to be achieved
within that time and what
>> we won't have to have it because I
believe if we if this passes and then
the motion passes it'll already be
annexed it's just the effective date of
the annexation will be six months so we
won't have to have this argument again
>> other than what's going to be achieved
within that six months time what
information is going to be brought
forward
>> do you want to answer that Mr.
>> I was asking for the maker of the
motion.
>> It's fine. It's fine.
>> All right. Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Through
you again, as we hear from our
constituents is to give them time. It
also gives Microsoft time, too, to have
some of these open houses that they've
had because it was held near Memorial
Day weekend. And again, it just gives
everybody time. That's what the people
are asking for. I'm doing the will of
the people.
>> Dr. Ems.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. So,
[clears throat] we've had this
conversation now what five times I
believe about postponing. At least five
times. Every time we've gone through
this, the council has voted against the
pause.
I don't understand why we keep doing
this. I still see it as a workaround. I
don't think it's appropriate. I think
changing the date by four days or 20
days or whatever from um
Councilman uh Wolf's amendment is just a
workound to try to get around the vote
that we've already taken at least five
times on this. So I would encourage us
to vote no.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> Mr. Mayor, thank you through you. Um
well to Dr. Ren's question. Um, this is
going to be part of my closing argument,
but I'll make it now. What could we do?
Well, we could do a lot of things.
We could
make changes or start making changes to
the uniform development code
to address specifically data centers.
And in those changes and that's
legislation that we would do in those
changes we could address. Okay. Data
centers shall use best available
technology.
We could
this stupid thing. I'm sorry.
We could address questions like um how
are we going to regulate power plants
that produce power with fuel cells
because the regulations are either
non-existent or aren't in fact able to
address the complexities of fuel cells.
We could address natural gas fired power
plants and the effects that they have.
We could talk about sequestration of CO2
emissions. We could address the
potential for small nuclear reactors
which is lingering in the background of
all of these discussions. We could
address emergency power. We could in
fact prohibit the use of diesel
generators for emergency backup power
because of the emissions that they
uh release to the air. We could talk
about on-site pre-treatment of
wastewater discharge. We could talk
about traffic and traffic impacts. We
can talk about, and this is a point
somebody else made, but I had already
written it down, requirements for
reclamation of these plants when we stop
using them or they stop using them and
whether or not we ought to bond for
those just like we do in the oil and gas
industry and uh in the land quality
processes. We could of course talk about
contributions for other community
benefits. Um, and we could talk about
manamp regulations. We could suggest or
adopt in regulation that if you're going
to build a man camp, you're going to
build it on your site. This isn't
actually my insight. It was from one of
the uh one of the city leaders for whom
I have an enormous regard. Um, and um
and he suggested it. So could we use
that time? Yes, of course we could and
use it very productively. We are missing
the boat on all these issues. We need in
the city one person who is dedicated to
knowing everything about data centers.
Everything.
We should be developing a data center
master plan. communities that have been
dealing with mass with data centers have
started to develop these things and the
industries have been working with them.
So could we use six months? Sure, we
could use a couple years and we could
also tie it into plan Cheyenne which is
now as we just heard a contract's been
awarded and that's going forward. And
here we have the ideal
project, the ideal annexation to
actually try to take on those kind of
foresighted
strengthening our community,
strengthening the ability of this
council of the city government and being
responsive to all of you to actually
do the planning. planning that we have
heard from so many of you and involve
Microsoft in that make them a partner in
that planning and all these other
companies.
So I I think this notion that we can't
use six months really well is is just
facious. Of course we can use it and we
may use want to use more. Um but and let
me respond to another thing that I heard
from Councilwoman Emmens that she's
tired of hearing about
uh having a pause. Well, I've been to
every single one of these hearings as
have a number of you uh for the last two
months. It has consumed my life and the
life of many people on this council and
many people in this community. We owe it
to each other. We owe it to the city to
actually
think much harder about this. Now, I
promised myself that I would not argue
from a legal standpoint against his
annexation.
And I will just say one thing.
A competent lawyer
can get this annexation overturned in
court
without much trouble. It is
not soundly based in the statute. The
facts are completely absent.
And um so but I'm not going to try and
make that argument because I have a few
other things I want to say about but we
should without question
slow this process down.
It's not going to affect Microsoft.
They'll tell you it will but it won't.
They're not going to abandon this idea
of being part of the city because we
provide tremendous benefits. This goes
back to one of the very earliest
comments I heard from the mayor, which
is it's just changing the color on a
map.
That is so far from wrong as uh being
kind of uh astonishing
as we have heard and you can read and
you can see
once we annex and once we zone then we
have committed the city's resources and
if we haven't gotten anything for that
if we haven't in fact gotten the kind of
understandings and arrangements And as
I've said before, it's not just having a
partnership to help build the city. It's
in fact having a thoughtful in informed
discussion about environmental issues,
environmental conditions, wildlife,
cultural resources, all the other
aspects of that. So yes, we need to
spend more time on this. This
annexation, this is my point to
Councilman Enlins,
has gone at the She says we have to move
at the speed of business. This goes at
the speed of light.
No other place in the country could you
other than Laramie County could you go
and get start to finish before the
governing body
your full annexation and your full
zoning rights. There was any other place
in the country you could do that and
which is one of the reasons these
companies are here and are going to
continue to come here.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Craig,
>> if we were delaying
the vote for 6 months, I could see how
we might do some of those things, but if
we're going to vote tonight and just
delay the
>> start,
>> they're grandfathered.
>> It's over. I mean, I I don't know. We
can do all those things regardless.
>> Um I I don't see how appro approving or
not approving if it obviously if it's
not approved, it doesn't matter. But if
it's approved and it's simply an
effective date six months from now,
>> they're grandfathered.
>> It's it's
>> it doesn't matter.
>> Well, um m Mr. Mayor, let me respond to
that.
>> First of all, I recall my first motion,
which actually just postponed this. And
remember, we postponed the Cox edition
on this crazy
mausoleum issue. Something totally out
of left field. We postpone that for four
months. My gosh. I mean, if we can't
postpone this. So, my first motion was
postponed. Postpone it for a period of
time, then we haven't decided it. My
second motion because that one didn't
pass was okay well grant the annexation
that has the benefit to Microsoft of
having the certainty of that but it does
give us time to open and work on
arrangements with them and to address
some of these other issues.
Now, I would I preferred my first
motion, but you know, and and we could
but the other thing to consider is that
you could grant this extension and if we
weren't finished, you could go in and
adopt another ordinance to change that
date because we may need more than six
months or the legislature may be telling
us things that we need to respond to.
So,
thank you, Dr.
>> Mayor Collins. I I guess I need a point
of clarification because my
understanding is that with this
amendment
that the annexation would be approved.
>> Yes.
>> And so there there is they're
grandfathered in at that point. What
what is I mean it's approved. It would
be approved tonight. it just wouldn't
take effect until whatever it was,
January, whatever. I will be a no vote
on this because I don't see that this is
going to uh address the concerns that
anyone has other than people who just
don't want to see it happen. Um, so I
think that this is uh simply uh just
delaying the date and they would be
grandfathered in and none of those
things all of those things that uh
Councilman Wolf talked about can be done
whether they are annexed or not. Um we
can address the UDC, we can address, you
know, fuel cells, we can address those
are all things that can be addressed. um
they're not contingent upon Microsoft
and so for that reason I'm a no vote
tonight.
>> Anybody else on the motion to uh change
the effective date until January 25th,
2027?
>> All right. Hearing none. All those in
favor of the motion to
change the effective date, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> May I see the hands of the nose? Dr.
Rainey, Dr. Amos, Mr. Crave,
Dr. Aldridge, and Mr. White. That motion
fails,
and we're back on the main motion. Mr.
Mayor,
>> yes. I move to postpone until January
25th, 2027.
>> Is there a second?
>> I'll second.
>> Point of order, Mr. Mayor. Um, I need
our attorney. Again, by practice in past
attorneys recommendations, we can only
postpone for a two-eek period unless we
somehow lay it back to a committee. Um,
so
I guess if we're going to do this, can
at least our attorney give us the proper
wording?
>> Mr. Broie, [clears throat]
>> Mr. Mayor. So yeah, under Robert's
rules, uh the the two uh best motions
before the council are a motion to
postpone. Practice of council is that
has been postponement is till the next
meeting of the council. So that would be
two weeks. If you want to do a date
certain under Roberts, the appropriate
motion is a motion to recommmit. Uh you
would recommmit it to uh committee. The
committee would then be directed through
that motion to report the item back to
the city council at the date uh so
chosen.
>> Thank you, Mr.
>> Mr. Mayor. I can read the motion. I move
to recommmit um this until January 25th,
2027.
>> Is there a point of order that we have
to vote on one before we can do another
one? I I think the motion was um was not
an appropriate motion uh based on
Robert's order. So, it was out of order.
So, we have to make a new motion in
order to bring it in. Would that be
fair,
>> Mr. Mayor? Yes. Okay.
>> Mr. Moody, if you wanted to do that and
um you wanted to send it back to like
January 17th, that would be or excuse
me, January 18th,
>> 2027, that would be the public service
committee meeting.
>> Okay. Mr. Mayor, I move to uh rec
recommmit this to the public services
committee to January 18th, 2027.
>> Second.
>> Okay.
Go out to the audience. The motion is to
postpone this until or not to uh to
delay this and send it back to the
public service committee on January
18th, 2027.
Sir, go ahead.
>> Can you bring the microphone up for us,
please?
>> Elgates W three. Strongly support that
motion. For all the reasons we've been
talking about, there needs to be time to
talk about how SweetGrass interacts with
this new business park to look at all of
the impacts that Mr. Wolf described. I
think this truly gives us the
opportunity to really make sure that
we've got the good clear plan in place
uh before we go jumping into this. Thank
you,
>> sir.
I would just like to say that I that I
do support the motion. Um I
[clears throat]
I have an a comment to add to this. Um,
we've seen three representatives
come tonight from from a higher body of
government than the city council and and
raise a lot of the same concerns as the
constituents. And I guess I would just
ask, why would we not want to um wait
for those folks to convene and wait to
see what they say? Why do we have to try
to get ahead of them? Why can't we uh
see what they say and see what they
bring to the table? Why can't we kind of
follow their lead and on a on a state
level and kind of all work together to
do something that's actually going to
benefit the people of Cheyenne?
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Janet Tolman, Ward 3. I I support this
motion and some people are saying,
"Well, why?" And I say, "Because
your constituents are requesting it.
I'm up here requesting it. And everyone
who's come here and said something in
regard to
wanting a delay, wanting to know more.
They're saying, "Please, we are wanting
you to vote this."
You can say, "We're not worth it." You
can throw us out the door and say, "Oh,
no. We're going to do our own thing
because we've listened to you.
But are you really listening
if you hear what we have to say and
don't act accordingly.
>> Okay.
>> So, I'm just thinking here. Um,
>> identify yourself. Remember,
>> McAdams. I'm sorry.
I'm just thinking I like the idea of
postponement. I love that. You know, I
don't think this would even be brought
up if it we trusted that the next vote
would be no to annexation.
So, I guess I'm looking at this. If this
land gets annexed into a business park,
can the city still say no to a data
center
or how does that work? Can anybody
answer that question?
if it's annexed and then it's zoned
properly. No, we cannot say no to a data
center.
>> There you go.
>> If it's z if it's zoned properly, um
unless it doesn't meet all of the uh
other requirements that we would have,
traffic, those types of things.
>> Yeah, those are minor requirements now
that I'm seeing with these data centers
and they're just so new. That's why I'm
looking at this postponement and I would
strongly recommend no until we get some
idea of what exactly we're up against
with these data centers. These are
billiondoll corporations and we're a
bitty state. So our vote counts. So
please, please consider no vote on this
annexation until more information and
yes to this. Waiting to see what our
legislators will do. Thank you. Thank
you.
Mr. Mayor, uh, I'm Robin Kelly. W three.
I am for that 100%. That will give us
that time that that's all we're asking
for. And Mr. Mayor, to you directly, if
you were to vote for this delay, um, you
would get a lot a lot of respect back
from some of the people. Just give us
that time. That's all we're asking.
Thank you.
>> Yes, ma'am.
Hi, Elizabeth Marvin. Um, I am in
support of the motion to postpone until
2027. Um, and I'd like to apologize for
my emotional outbursts. That was kind of
embarrassing.
>> Don't apologize for being human.
[snorts] Thank you. Yes, ma'am.
>> Lynn Davis, I am fully in support of of
delaying this or postponing this until
until January. If we don't do it now,
it's going to happen again because this
isn't this battle is not is not over. We
still need to have the answers and you
might as well do it now and take take a
few minutes. I understand that it's
going to be annexed anyway and I'm I'm
fine with that personally, but um the
problem is that we have we still have
some work to do. You guys have still
have some work to do. as as Councilman
Wolf presented, he he it was an ideal
list of things that exactly support why
you need you need a little extra time to
uh to get your ducks in a row.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. Yes, ma'am.
>> Peggy Gates, Ward Three. Um, what I'm
not clear on is what rep legal
representation does do the citizens have
in this. And so if that time can allow
something legally binding that protects
our interests,
I'm all for it. And I don't know if
there's an easy answer to that, but um
the word legal has come up and so I am
um interested in what protects us as
homeowners and citizens
um in this process. So, thank you,
>> Miss Madrid.
>> Heather Madre, Ward One. Um, I support
this postponement or the the
recommittal, I guess. Um, I feel like
right now we're living in a petri dish
and I've emailed I've emailed you guys
relentlessly and I don't even know if
you're reading them anymore, but we
we're living in a petri dish. The reason
that we are is because our regulations
are terrible and they're coming here to
experiment when they're going to take
their new best laid plans. All all the
lessons they've learned the hard way
here at our expense, they'll take it
somewhere else and build data centers
according to their
regulations and ordinances which are
just lacking here. That's just the fact
of it. They're coming here for a reason.
We've made ourselves a target. Well, we
haven't, but we are a target. Um,
I promised myself that I wasn't going to
make
any any threats of legal action,
but this is illegal, and I agree with
Mr. Wolf. It's so clearly illegal that
it would be an open and closed case. So
to answer the lady who just asked this
question, I am looking for a lawyer
actively have been and I will let you
know when I find one because this is
illegal. Not the data center. This
annexation is illegal. I don't think
anybody you I don't I don't remember who
made the comment that we just don't want
this. I don't want this. But that's not
part of the criteria. So if I want it or
not doesn't matter legally.
Um and I recognize that I can't have my
way all the time. I feel like we have
enough data centers personally. Um
the fundamental
according to the statute you guys aren't
following your own rules for this
annexation. that makes it illegal and
that makes everything after this
regarding this annexation the all the
reasonzoning and map updating measures
also illegal. Thank you.
>> Welcome back.
>> Thank you uh Mayor and Kas one
candidate. I am in support of the
recommittal of the postponement for all
the reasons that Mr. Wolf stated um
previously. I'll keep it short. Thank
you.
>> Hello sir.
Christopher Kamargo, Ward 2. Um, I'm in
support of this recommittal. Um, I think
you guys need to be reminded that you
were elected by us constituents. You
need to hear us and that hasn't been
done. Um,
this recommitt
I mean it's going to be annexed. It's
that's already the the decision from the
majority of you, but how's it we need to
figure out how can it best benefit the
city.
There's a lot of rate hikes from BOU
electric.
Um we have our storm water prevention
that still needs to be addressed.
These guys need to pay for it. you know,
they want to come into our city or
whatnot,
you know, let's uh figure out what's
going to benefit the community of
Cheyenne.
>> Welcome back.
>> Thank you. Uh Sha Fifer W 2. I am 1,000%
in favor of this amendment.
um just so we can you know get our ducks
in a row as people have said and kind of
on the heels of BOU like if they didn't
know that was going to happen or where
it came from the contamination kind of
stuff and I didn't want to beat that
dead horse obviously we need to you know
pre-est the area for that kind of stuff
and maybe we need to lay down
groundworks for that kind of stuff like
what are we going to test for prior to
them ever even breaking ground so this
will give us a little pause so that we
come up with a better plan of what we
are going to do. And sorry this is
bothering you, Dr. Emmens, for the fifth
or sixth time. But like, you know, I I
10,000% agree with this.
>> Anybody online?
>> Mr. Mayor, we do have somebody online,
but I also want to just uh mention for
the record that January 18th of 2027 is
Martin Luther King Day. So, it will be
moved one day just for the record so
everybody's aware. Um, I do have Mr.
Miller. You can go ahead.
>> We'll call that a scrier's yard and I'll
fix it.
>> Okay.
>> Hello. Can you hear me?
>> Yes, sir. We can hear you.
>> All right. Mayor Collins, members of the
city council, and city attorney Brony
for the permanent administrative record.
My name is Charles Miller.
Um, I'm stepping to the microphone uh
right now to do something that might
surprise some of you. Um I'm here to
express express my well also to speak on
this uh postponement or reccomitt. I'm
here to express my respect for several
members of this governing body. To
Councilman Larry Wolf, it is no secret
that we've had our procedural
differences. You have previously
requested that my First Amendment right
to speak be restricted to a single
agenda item and you question on the
record if I was a chat GPT robot.
However, true civic duty requires
acknowledging when a public official is
fighting for the citizens. During these
Highlands annexation hearings, you stood
firmly firm to publicly dismantle the
false narrative that developers have an
inherent right to force the city's hand,
accurately noting that a property
owner's bundle of sticks does not
include the right to be annexed. You
astutely warned that once this land is
annexed and zoned, the city loses its
leverage to negotiate a community
benefits agreement. I have the utmost
respect for your legal expertise on this
matter and your demand that this city
negotiate from um and your demand that
this city negotiate from a position of
strength. To Councilman Pete Leborn, you
and I have also clashed on this live
microphone. You have previously called
my audits completely out of control and
asked the city attorney to dismiss my
factual basis. But I have watched you
fight alongside Councilman Wolf to
demand answers on this annexation and
push back against a rubber stamp
process. I respect your fight in this
matter and I'm telling you right now, do
not give up. The citizens of Cheyenne
need you to continue pressing for the
truth and holding the line no matter how
uncomfortable it makes the
establishment. To Councilman Mark Moody,
I I respect what you are doing. You have
consistently stood by your constituents
proposed amendments to protect our
community and cast the lonely no votes
against this corporate machine. However,
with respect, you need to step up your
game. It is not enough to just vote no.
You must aggressively challenge the
procedural and statutory defects of
these ordinances as they happen on this
floor. Finally, to any other council
member up there who may be sitting on
the fence or thinking about dissenting
today, doing the right thing is always
harder than doing the wrong thing. It is
easy to rubber stamp a 3500 acre
corporate ghost project because you are
afraid of losing a developer. It is hard
to demand actual engineering data, risk
the political backlash, and enforce the
law. But your fiduciary duty is to the
taxpayers who live here, not to attack
Monopoly's construction timeline. Retain
your leverage. Do the hard thing today.
Vote no on this annexation. Thank you,
>> Mr. Mayor. Mr. Labler.
>> [clears throat]
>> I'm reluctant [cough] to respond to uh
the comments that were just made. Can we
finish public comment and then I'll come
back to you?
>> Certainly.
>> That be better.
>> Well, but this is response to public
comment.
>> I understand. But let's
>> I've seen plenty of other people have
that right.
>> You're right. Go ahead.
I think this speaks to this entire
process, our entire discussion. It has
gotten to the point of some sort of
personalitydriven
uh
and interest driven discussion that
really is
not helpful.
This is an important decision. It's got
a lot of pieces to it. It's going to
affect us for a long time. And if if
this is the kind of discussion and the
kind of understanding that we have here,
whether this passes tonight, whether
it's postponed or however it's going to
work out, um this isn't about
personality
and this isn't about people who believe
that their point of view is u the
dominant and all powerful point of view,
whether it's on one side or the other.
This is really not the kind of
discussion and effort that's going to
lead us to a resolution and a activities
that will allow
uh even the existence of what's under
construction now.
Um we can do better than this. And I I I
really would prefer that if we didn't
get into this personality stuff. Uh and
I I it really really Let's think about
this.
Is this the best the city of Cheyenne
and its citizens can do in discussing
and considering
what I believe is the most important
annexation action we've ever had. I
think we can do a lot better than this.
Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
Jennifer.
>> Uh Jared Little, you can unmute
yourself.
>> Jared.
>> Hi. So, this is actually Nicole Little.
Thank you very much. Uh the Ward One, I
just wanted to call in with support for
the movement to push back until January
of 2027.
um just giving us additional time to
make sure that we are moving forward in
the safest manner for our community um
and making sure that we are taking the
correct steps forward. um just setting
up the future of the I don't want to say
movement necessarily for the data
centers but just in these industries
that are moving forward taking the right
steps with this particular annexation
this particular agreements and and
conversations with this company it will
really lead the way for our future
conversations with the following
companies that will be coming to our
area after that. So, I just wanted to
call in again and appreciate your guys'
times and just put in my support for the
delay until January of 2027.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> That's it.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes, ma'am. On the motion to uh commit
this back to the committee till 2027.
>> Yes. Donna Dundan, Ward One, I want to
commend the motion to move this. I thank
you very much. Um I also had a question.
Um, you guys said, "What difference does
it make?" Well, if it's not going to
make a difference, why does it bother
you? Can you please just wait as well?
Or can you give a reason why you can't
wait? We go every day and when people
are down and having a hard time or
struggling and you know or kids growing
up, what do we tell them that one day
can make a difference? A day can make a
difference in somebody's life. And
between now and then, anything could
happen in that timeline that could
reawaken our eyes. It could lead us into
another direction. It gives us
opportunity. And I want to thank you all
for what you're doing because it's not
easy. We know that it's not easy, but
we're hearing we're hearing you finally
hear us a little bit more. This is a big
annexation. when you go into this, you
have the several others that will follow
immediately. So that's why we're focused
on this and I thank you for your time.
Why not one more day? Why not give it
the time? What's it going to cost you?
That would be my question. And the other
thing I'd like to say is that you guys
have Okay, I'm not pushing the age
thing. We're all aging. You guys have
enormous amount of experience up there.
You have so much world and life
experience and from the titles you have
so much education.
Let's move on intelligent design. Give
it the time it needs. Let's use that
knowledge and education and let us have
a day.
Thank you.
Anybody
else on the motion to uh commit this
back to the committee? Jennifer, anybody
online?
Okay, we'll close public comment and
we'll go back to the governing body
comments. Mr. Cag.
>> Mr. Mayor, I'm going to speak in
opposition um for a couple of reasons.
First of all, our history with uh
postponements is not all that great.
Uh, second of all, although Councilman
Wolf gave us a whole laundry list of
things,
actually, I don't think many of those
could get accomplished within six
months, and
I just know how slow government is. Um,
I I just don't think we would be very
successful.
Um, and I'm not sure exactly what we
would learn in this period of time. So,
I'm going to be a no vote. Thank you.
Dr. Emmens.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, I'm going to
be a no vote for the reason that I think
the things that Councilman Wolf talked
about are important, but it's not either
or. There's no reason. We can't continue
to move forward, but still address those
issues. If the if the concern is really
the issues, not the data center, then
let's keep going with progress, but
still address those issues. They're all
important. Nobody's saying they're not
important and they shouldn't be dropped.
We should take care of them, but we can
do two things at the same time. We can
walk and chew gum. We can do this and
move forward. I I agree with um
Councilman um Crave that we don't do
well with this and I'm really afraid
that it will just sit and not no
progress will be made and then we're
going to be right back here again and
then we're going to be right back here
again and then we're going to be right
back here again and that's not good for
anybody. It's not good for the mental
health and physical health of what some
of you have put into this. It's just it
makes no sense to me that we would put
this artificial barrier in here knowing
that we're committed to doing these
things. So for that I'm going to be a
no.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. through you
just in response to these two comments.
Neither of them are very complimentary
of the council.
They all kind of assume that we'll do
this and twiddle our thumbs for six
months and then we'll come back and I
guess grant it or deny it or whatever. I
don't think that's really what should or
would happen.
We need We're being run over by the data
center industry and we're playing
catch-up and we're behind years behind.
So
we're trying to give ourselves
time to actually think intelligently
about this particularly time when you
know we may want to hire somebody to
just as I said be the point person on
data centers sometimes I wish I had made
that motion before we close the budget
but I'm not willing to concede that the
council couldn't in fact make
substantial progress on these issues in
six months. Will we finish them all? Of
course not. Many in the UDC is
difficult. A master plan for data
centers is difficult. Although I'd
frankly like to spend some time looking
at ones that other communities have in
fact considered and adopted.
Um if we don't do that, if we don't if
we don't give ourselves the time, we
don't we won't have that. we won't have
the possibility to do this and then to
in fact take it into account as we
consider this annexation next time
around. And of course I can say all
these things because I won't be here.
So uh I only got six months left here.
So um but um hopefully whoever gets
elected will will be inclined to
actually do the tough work. This is the
tough work of governing tough work of
identifying problems trying to work
together to find solutions
and why we wouldn't take it in this
case. I I don't I don't understand.
Thank you
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Thank you Mr. Mayor through you. I echo
what my colleague from W one next to me
said.
Council, let's listen to our
constituents. They're the ones demanding
it. They is ask for a delay. Okay,
there's nothing wrong with this. We do
need to adopt the UDC code. Ms. Madreas
provides great information that we can
work off. And let's actually listen to
our constituents for once.
Vote I.
>> Anybody else in the governing body? Dr.
Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. I would just say
first and foremost I think that was
offensive. Uh I don't think that we
haven't been listening to our
constituents. I think that um sometimes
we don't agree and that's okay. And we
hear from people this we have we serve a
community of 67,000 people.
>> 85% of us don't want
>> ma'am. Sir,
>> that is that is not
>> my experience. So, um I think that those
of us that are voting the way we are are
do believe that we are voting in the
best interest of our constituents. Um
just because we don't agree does not
mean we're not listening. So, uh for
that reason, I will continue to be a no
vote.
>> Who who are those comments addressed to
council?
>> Uh let's let's not let's not thank you.
Anybody other comments on the motion to
uh to I guess call it postpone, but to
uh move it back to the committee in
January of 27.
All right. I hear no other comments. All
those in favor of the u the motion to
effectively postpone signify by saying
I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> May I see the hands and nose? Dr.
Rainey, Dr. Ammon, Mr. Crave, Dr.
Aldrich, Mr. Escoel, and Mr. White. That
motion fails.
back on the main.
>> We're back on the main motion.
>> M Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Crave,
>> I would like to address the five issues
that are uh part of the state statute on
annexation. And I I just wonder if
there's anybody left from uh planning
that that might be able to help answer.
>> I see handsome Seth Lloyd.
>> Mr. Lloyd, thank you so much.
>> Seth Clifford Lloyd, is that right?
>> I liked it.
>> U Mr. Mayor, members of the city
council, my name is Seth White. I'm with
the City of Shine Planning and
Development Department. Um, the request
was to go over the criteria in state
statute. Um, and I believe address
>> Yes, Mr. Mayor. If you'll give me a
little latitude, I'd just like to go
through these questions very quick and
just
>> I think they're pertinent.
>> Get on the qu uh on the record. Uh, Mr.
Lloyd, the first the first question
discusses u uh protection of the health,
safety, and welfare of the persons
residing in the area as well as the city
and town. So, can we address both of
those entities and kind of go through
why we think annexation of this property
for the purpose of data centers would be
better uh in the city rather than the
county.
>> Mr. Mayor, I will go through that. So
the area in question um would normally
develop should it develop with
development would be with water uh wells
and septic systems as opposed to water
and sewer which would punch holes in the
aquifer and bring um uh whatever
discharge they have back into the
aquifer. Um generally speaking it is
healthier to be on a centralized water
and sewer system than it is to be on a
well or and septic system. Um, this also
relates to the people adjacent because
there's others who are using that
aquifer. Um, residents mostly of the
county. Um, so that would help that
specific area as far as health. Um,
regarding safety, um, the city of
Cheyenne has police and fire protection.
Um, generally those have quicker
response times than the county
equivalents. Um, they don't have as much
area to cover. For one, um the fire
staff, we have a large fire staff um
certified. If I remember correctly, we
had a certification come through that
we're one of the few fire departments
that are have that certification. Um I
don't remember the exact name title of
that certification, but you can maybe
you can get that from the fire
department. Um
then we also have um the community as a
whole. um specific if this property
develops with data center type
development. Um there are tax benefits
to the community. Um I believe that um
the city had a property tax hit because
of the cut to residential property
taxes. Um however, nearly the same time
we annexed the North Range Business Park
which had working data centers and that
helped offset if not fully offset that
cut to property taxes. Um, so that could
be a benefit to the city because then
the city can provide more services. It
can employ more staff. It can retain
staff so you're not spending as much
time training staff. Um, these uh data
center organizations do have um benefits
for the community as far as training
programs, the other things that have
been mentioned already. I don't think I
need to hash those out. So that's um
some of the elements of question one.
Also general development area. If this
area were to generally not speaking to
data center specifically, if this area
were to develop with other um industrial
uses that could provide jobs um to the
community. If it were developed with
residential uses, then it could provide
housing to the community, which is also
a known need for this community. So
there's um definitely um by annexing
large acreage to of land to the city,
there are definite benefits to the
community as a whole. um depending on
the type of development, obviously the
applicant is requested uh for data
center development, but should that fall
through, there's other uh potential
options that could be out there.
>> Thank you. The second question um
discusses uh does this constitute a
natural, geographic, economical, and
social part of the annexing city or
town?
>> Uh yes. So, this area is contiguous to
city limits. Um I know that's one later
down on the list, but it's 45.6%
contiguous. Um so nearly 50% of that uh
border is contiguous to city limits.
That makes it natural geographically. Um
residents who live in the area or people
who work in this area would likely
either shop or recreate within the
Cheyenne region. I'm sure that people
who live along Chalk Bluff Road, for
example, utilize shopping or recreation
in the Cheyenne area. Um so it's already
part of our social fabric. that that
area is part of our social fabric. Um,
and it because of its proximity and the
percent contiguous, it's definitely a
natural geographic fit.
>> Thank you. The next area is uh asks, is
this area logical and feasible addition
to the annexing city or town and the
extension of basic and other services
customerally available to residents?
>> Yes. So the question here is um
historically it would be difficult to
develop this area due to extension of
water and sewer infrastructure. However,
the applicant has met with the board of
public utilities and I'm pretty certain
they wouldn't be here. We wouldn't be
here if they hadn't had a plan and the
board of public utilities found that as
an acceptable plan. So the board of
utilities has reviewed the potential for
this area. They know what they can do.
The applicant has reviewed the potential
for this area. they know what they need
to do in order to extend those services.
Um, water and sewer is much more
difficult to extend than power and
natural gas. So, um, I have all
confidence that those can be extended.
Um, we can also provide fire service,
police service as previously mentioned,
sanitation services. Um, the city also
provides maintenance of paved roads for
example, which the county does not. Um,
so those are some of the services that
would be extended. Um, should they
dedicate roads, the city would accept
them and take on the maintenance.
>> Thank you. Uh I think we've already
addressed this, but uh is the area
sought to be annexed uh contiguous?
>> Yes, it is.
>> Okay. And uh two more questions. Uh if
we don't operate our own electric
utility, um is one available? Does the
city have a franchise?
>> Yes, through you, mayor, we do have
electric utility franchises. Um this
area will be able to be served serviced
by our electric utilities. And then the
final question we're asked to consider u
not less than 20 business days prior to
the public hearing uh did we send out
certified letters to those within the um
state required um area?
>> Yes, we sent those out prior to the
public hearing. Um 20 business days more
than 20 business days ahead of time. Um
we had uh confirmation of receipt of
those certified mailing and then we also
sent the neighbor mailing at the same
time as the certified mailing.
>> Thank you. Appreciate your help,
>> Mr. Mayor, it's my opinion that we have
met the required statutory
issues for this annexation.
>> Anybody else in the governing body want
to talk about this on third and final
reading?
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins to you. Um I am going to
be a yes vote tonight for this and there
are several reasons why. First and
foremost, um I live and work in Laramie
County and in Cheyenne and I did grow up
here as well. Um my future is here. I'm
not planning to go anywhere anytime
soon. Um I believe that it's in the
city's best interest to have this um
data center in the city limits. Um and
the reason for that is um if it's in the
city limits, we can meter the water. we
can know how much water they're actually
using and be able to have that that
amount and that data. Um, if they are
located in the county, they are able to
drill wells directly into the aquifer,
which I think is much more problematic
um than being able to use city water and
meter it. Um, I also know that we have
ordinances that control electric uh or
the I'm sorry, the light pollution and
the noise pollution. Um we also um
benefit from having the uh sales tax
revenue, but um the electric I think has
been addressed the power that they need
um because of our statute that allows
the high use or um tariffs and so um
where they cannot pass on their uh
infrastructure costs to the end consumer
or residential users. Um, all of our
rate increases, as you know, if you live
have lived in Wyoming for a while or in
Cheyenne, have to go through the public
service commission. Um, and so that, um,
is that that added layer of protection.
Uh, for those reasons, I'm going to be a
yes this evening because I believe that
annexing this and having a data center
in city limits is in the best interest
of everyone in our community.
>> Any other comments, Mr. White? Mr.
Mayor, uh, just some clarification if I
could. Heard a couple of different
things tonight. So, does Microsoft
already own this parcel of land? Has
that transaction been finalized?
>> I believe the answer is yes, but we'll
ask.
>> Mayor Collins through you. Yes, we do
own this property. Uh, we closed on the
property June 26th.
>> June 26th. While while you're up here,
can
>> you
>> I can tell you I I was told by the land
owner that they they had finished that
contract and it would happened.
>> So, my next Thank you, Mr. Mayor. My
next my next question is this. Um, and I
and I was asked this question earlier
tonight. I think it's a great question.
Can you or someone um one of your
colleagues provide information?
We get this question a lot. What are in
data centers? Is it we're just we're
storing the servers. Correct,
>> Mayor Collins? Through you
>> data centers are storing the servers.
>> Absolutely. Um so internally, yes, there
are servers and other um technology that
essentially store cloud infrastructure.
So, think hospitals, businesses, um what
you do on your phones on a day-to-day
basis, calling 911, all of those things
um is what runs through a data center on
a daily basis. So, commercial
infrastructure.
>> And then I was asked another Thank you.
Then I was asked another question um is
the you know why the why the drive and
the increase of building these data
centers and my answer was because it's
being driven by demand and by demand I'm
talking all of us using these
uh using these for research during these
meetings
um uh Tik Tok the creator economy all
those things. Um, so am am I correct in
that,
>> Mayor Collins? Through you, Councilman
White. Yes, you are correct.
[clears throat]
>> Thank you.
>> You're welcome.
>> Um, so,
so here we have a transaction that's
been completed legally.
And so um you know I think uh property
rights are implicated whenever
government action uh affects a property
owner whom we know who owns the property
now uh their ability to use develop or
sell their land. And so if the owner
initiate owner is initiating a request
for annexation,
I just don't think um that we should
deny it if all the statutes and and
ordinances and state laws have been uh
the requirements have been met. Um it's
not because I believe that there is a
inalienable right to annexation. It's
just because I believe government really
needs to exercise
uh it discretion in a manner that uh
respects those rights, provides
predictability and this maybe is more uh
most important treats applicants
consistently.
We would if a ranch owner wanted to sell
their land to a manufacturing facility,
warehouse, housing development, um we
wouldn't be here. but we are because
it's a data center and so uh I think
that we operate best when the rules are
applied consistently rather than based
on the identity of an applicant and
that's just my opinion. I know many
folks disagree with me. I've tried to
respond to everyone that's emailed me
about it in a respectful manner. I hope
I've I hope I've met that uh threshold
and um
I'll be supporting it.
Dr. Rainy,
>> I can do you want
>> Dr. Ems? I don't care which one of you.
One of you [laughter] go. The other one
will go second.
>> Thank you. Uh, Mr. Mayor, I'm going to
be voting for this, too. And I was
really hoping that more people would be
here because to hear this because I
think this is really important. When you
look at what we're doing and I know it
feels fast and it feels like we just
made this decision to go, but when you
look at Laram County historically, this
is an evolutionary process.
14 years. Well, for n in 1990, however
many years ago, I can't do math after
11. So, 30 30 oh gosh, 36 years ago, we
brought Echoar
to Cheyenne. And Echoar was like the
first satellite
cool technology. I don't know, but it
was technologically advanced.
It was a data center and that was 33
years ago. In 2007, we brought
greenhouse data here and it was the fir
it was another independent data storage
unit and it's still here and it's grown
and it's developed and I remember when
they came and the guy came and talked to
me I don't even remember what job I was
doing but he said hey I want to do this
thing and I thought well that's weird
but okay. Um, so that was in 2007.
In 2012,
Governor Garinger, who was our governor
at the time, went out on a limb and
decided we need needed to put in 4G 4G
fiber, which was very advanced. And I
remember when it happened, people said,
"Why in the world does Wyoming need
this? that is way too advanced for
anything that's going to happen in
Wyoming. In 2012, we brought ENCAR, one
of the biggest computers in the country
for the um as part of the Noah system.
And then I believe in 2012 was when we
brought Microsoft.
So this is not something that's just
happened overnight. This has been an
evolutionary process. Now in 1990 when
Echoar was brought here, did we think
this is where we were going to be?
Absolutely not. Because we had no idea.
But the reality is this has become our
niche. And every community who is
successful needs a niche. This is
Wyoming's niche. That doesn't mean we
just get rid of all of the safeguards
and we don't do our due diligence and we
don't do the right things, but this is
not something that's happened overnight.
And so because of that, I feel like this
is the next evolutionary step and I'm
going to support this annexation.
>> Dr. Rainey.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. Um, Mr. Mayor, I
have a I'm glad to see Mr. Emmens has
stuck around. I had a question for him.
Actually,
there's a few there's like two or three
things I want to address and then I have
some comments.
>> Please.
>> So, Mr. Emmens, I know you had referred
to this early on and and I know some
people missed it because they asked a
question in regard to what
First of all, the location of the
Highlands data center is back to the to
the south of the ridge. Is that correct,
>> Mr. Mayor? Through you. Yes. there's uh
an area that the um family that's sold
the land is saving for the rich line to
protect it from
>> and that was the other question. How
many acres is there's going to be a
buffer of how many acres in there
between
>> sweet grass and highlands?
>> So there's at least 500 acres at a
minimum because there's 500 acres the
annexation's 3500 in the zone change is
only three. So there's at least five 500
in between. So there's a 500 acre
buffer. So I know because some people
ask what kind of buffers there going to
be. So there's a 500 acre buffer between
Sweetgrass and Highlands and Highlands
is set back behind the ridge so it won't
even be visible from Sweet Grass. Is
that correct?
>> Mr. Mayor, through you I believe in the
contracts from the meetings that I said
and that there was discussion that there
was some high limitations and that they
could not be seen from the other side.
Okay.
>> Thank you, Mr. Emmens. Oh, I know
another thing. Um, you can probably help
me with this too. There's been again
some discussion by, you know, some of my
colleagues and some people in the
audience about the lack of definitive
plan for the Highlands development. And
yet I think any large development that
I've been a part of in the city for the
last several years has not had a full
complete plan. Um, how long did the how
long
did um like first of all sweetgrass I
know when we annexed that and that was
the that will now be the second largest
annexation to the city. I don't think
that plan was fully developed and how
long was that buildout supposed to be?
>> Mr.
>> Mr. Mayor three. So we um weren't
directly involved in Sweetgrass. So
>> but you sat through those meetings with
me.
>> Yeah. Um so you know they um but I would
say a similar size development just in
for instance like the point was over 25
years and they still have commercial
developments still to go. Um so these
projects take a lot of time uh to work
their way through the system. Um even on
uh probably the Swan Ranch Industrial
Park probably started 20 years ago and
it's half built out. Um so they they
they take time. um you know the
developers put them in and hope that the
people come to to building them. So um
even even in a small site I would say
from the time we get through city
council it's probably a year and a half
before we get through site plan and all
the other approvals before you start
construction.
>> Okay. Thank you Mr. Mr. Mayor. Just
wanted to point out I mean again there
was some discussion about that it was an
issue that that Highlands did not have a
develop plan and yet we I we can point
to
the point Sweetg Grass two residential
developments whose plans evolved over
decades
um still not completed yet and I know
Sweetgrass we've changed multiple times
even since it's been started and then
Swan Ranch is another one But I can't
even remember when that one came
through, but that started out as as
um industrial near the highway and then
commercial and then residential and that
eventually got changed to all
industrial.
So um plans change over time. People
have said that and point some of the
people in the audience have pointed that
out. But plans do change over time and
we have had several large developments
where they were not where we did not
have a definitive locked in plan. So
that's not unusual. Um,
somebody also commented and and my
colleague from W 3 alluded to that that
but someone in the audience had
commented that
um the presence of the data centers were
going to raise our power rates and what
my colleague alluded to that state
statute 37-3-116
that says that they cannot data centers
or actually large industrial power users
not data centers alone can't their power
needs cannot affect our rates. So, we're
protected in that regard. Um, and I want
to reaffirm one more time that again it
was alleged or said that by having the
data center located in a business park,
they escape scrutiny from DEEQ and that
is not accurate. DEQ does
does regulate require permits from them
for again for water, air, and hazardous
materials. And again, DEEQ sends out to
to 18 other state agencies for comments
that need to be addressed. So, I did
want to cover I mean, those were some
things were brought up in the
discussion. I did want to address those.
Um,
so thank you. And then, Mr. Mayor, I do
have some comments. Um, and people have
heard me say this. I mean,
UW 66% of UW graduates leave
immediately. 75% leave within the first
year. Um even though and
we are second in the country in
exporting our youth. Um those people
that do move into Cheyenne generally are
more of retirement age. And while
Wyoming's population has risen somewhat,
the number of jobs available in Wyoming
has actually declined. In fact,
according to the US Bureau of Labor
Statistics, the number of non-farm jobs
in Wyoming saw a decrease from from July
2015 to July of 2025.
Um, Wyoming's annual average income is
over $82,000 a year and that rank and
that puts us at fourth in the country.
However, when you take Teton County out
of the equation, we are below average
for income in the country. Um and what's
what's more those jobs that we do have
we're um as I said previously we are
losing jobs and those jobs that we have
retained have actually decreased in
value. The state median wages dropped
from 2012 to 2022.
So
if Wyam is going to strengthen diversify
its economy, we need the jobs that the
data centers bring. Um, so and I can
read I the evening's gone on long
enough. I had a whole paragraph here
where comments from the president of LC
on why he thought data centers were an
excellent fit for Wyoming and Cheyenne.
But but I'm just going to say in my
opinion they are an excellent fit. We're
not bringing in an oil or gas field.
We're not bringing in open pit mines.
We've actually discouraged a a
meat processing center a few years ago
from coming here. So, we're I mean,
we're we're looking at self-contained
buildings filled with computers with
well-paying jobs. Um, I do want to say I
have listened all I mean I've sat here
as my colleagues have
at least four to five hours a week for
the last two months and I've listened to
all the comments. Um,
and I think a lot of you that have
concerns about water and and power, I
think we've addressed those. I know our
board of public utilities and Black
Hills Energy can take months, in some
cases up to two years to negotiate with
data center providers to make sure that
we know what their water and power needs
are and what they will be and that we
can meet them. we require any new data
center to pay their own way and pay for
all of the in infrastructure impacts
that would be required to serve them.
And that's what the Industrial Sighting
Council does in that regard. And we're
already requiring that. Um
to to date, I'm not aware of any going
back to 2012. I'm not aware of any of
those costs that we've had to bear that
the city hasn't required them to cover.
Um, I already referred to the permits
that are still required by DEQ, so I
won't belabor that. So, I I think we
have tried to address the concerns that
people have brought to us. Um, and I am
I am pretty sure that from now on you
will start seeing, and Mr. Mayor, you
can confirm or deny this, but I'm pretty
sure we're going to start seeing a lot
more guard rails added into those
discussions. Um, I really think Cheyenne
pretty much between our board of public
utilities, the city requirements and and
Black Hills has it that we are leading
the nation in these efforts. So to steal
a phrase from our governor, we're doing
it the Wyoming way and it's working.
For those of you that just don't want
data centers, I obviously I don't agree
with you and and we're not going to come
to an accommodation on that. Um, and I
and while I've listened to the people in
the room, I want to again echo what my
some of my colleagues have said,
I have heard from a lot more people than
those of you that are sitting this this
room. And I am hearing a different
message. I honestly believe that the
majority of our citizens want to see
Cheyenne develop and prosper
economically and they want those
opportunities for their children,
grandchildren as a small business. And I
think having more in more people walking
around or more residents with increased
income benefits all of us. And I'm not
going to belver that point because I
can't do it better than what Mr. Amik
said earlier. So, but I do think that
growth begets growth and the more growth
we have, the more opportunity we are
going to have for dining, recreation,
entertainment. So, um, Mr. Mayor, I
think this is the path we need to to be
on. I think it's a safe um
I I think these are some of the best
corporate citizens we have worked with
in all the time I've been on council.
So, obviously, I am in favor of the
annexation. Thank you, Mr. Mayor.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. The hour is late,
but this decision is uh major.
And the point I want to make uh is that
there is sentiment here on the council
and in the community
that believes that a more thorough
analysis and understanding of this
matter needs to happen.
And I hope that uh the other members of
the council aren't going to be uh
offended when we bring up repeatedly
the issues that have been uh put aside
here in this annexation action.
There are many factors here that need to
be considered
in the fact that this development is so
big and is moving so fast. I also want
to express my appreciation to Microsoft
for the tour that I went on recently
that really educated me about a lot of
these factors. It's one thing to think
about. It's one thing to hear about.
It's another thing to actually be on the
site and really attempt to understand
how it works, how it's changing uh as
technology evolves.
And I want to say that when I was at
that uh Microsoft site there on the on
the Bison Business Park uh
and many of the factors that were talked
about tonight are the are certainly of
concern.
And I looked out over that
what is basically the uh Crow Creek Bowl
that we live in.
Um, and I saw opportunity and I saw
challenge
and I'm glad to have opportunity. There
are people here that have had
opportunity they wouldn't have
otherwise.
But I think there are great challenges
just in that area.
And when you drive down South Reley
Highway as I have all my life,
you see change that is uh
really stretching the boundaries of
control.
And when we look at the what happens in
these uh data centers, I'm I'm pleased
to learn more for instance about the
efforts that our fire department makes.
There's a lot to know here.
I think we've begun some sort of
understanding of it. I think it's
important that we recognize that there
are a variety of opinions here.
Um certainly I don't think any of us are
are all in one opinion,
but really what we're talking about here
is something that is a gold rush. This
is happening so fast
and is so comprehensive.
It is really difficult and I'll I'll use
me as an example. It's difficult to
grasp all the factors that come into
play
that uh Cheyenne hub bringing that
natural gas into this area can power
some really
uh power plants of size that we just
uh don't have haven't had or perhaps
regionally we had something smaller.
So, I really hope that that there's some
sincere commitment on the other members
of the council here to continue this
discussion after this approval tonight,
which is obviously going to happen to
really take a look at that further
regulation, that further understanding.
And I I I do want to say that a
community agreement and benefit
agreement
is not extortion.
That is not extortion.
that is payment
based on
business practices
that brings benefits
to balance out some of the
problems that come with it. And I also
want to say that if a corporation wants
to uh gift the city of Cheyenne uh for
the benefit of uh various things we want
to do, that's not a bribe.
That's that's their choice.
But I do want to more than anything else
go to the fact of our own judgment and
my judgment here.
Um,
we just heard that uh from the city
staff those conditions of annexation.
We've heard a lot about them. I take
[clears throat] them very seriously and
I evaluate them. And when I evaluate
the uh question of logical and feasible,
I believe I was sent here by the people
uh for the purpose of evaluating that to
my judgment.
to my judgment of looking out on that
bowl that we live in and evaluating all
of my experience with the board of
public utilities with uh the power
company
with the developers
uh and when I come to that conclusion
it's my opinion
that what I'm seeing here in my opinion
based on my vote is not logical
and it truly is not feasible.
I think that this entire discussion has
really degenerated into something that
uh needs further attention and I hope we
can do that. Some of the suggestions
that have been made here in terms of
having a central repository of
information would be very helpful. We
know there's more coming.
We know that there are uh and I think
when you talk about logical,
it's logical to me
that when across the country in the
news, we see
this intense
uh effort to uh make data centers go
somewhere else. We're going to have data
centers. Where they're going to go is
the question.
But when logically isn't it going to be
this pressure on us
on this undeveloped property to build
build data centers and they bring
benefits and they bring challenges
but it's all right for us to have our
own opinions
and I think it's important that we
develop those opinions and when we come
back
to this governing body with the issues
that we see and that have been
thoroughly expressed here by those of us
in the minority that they're not going
to get blown off that we're going to
take a real serious look at how the
unified development code handles this
aspect of our community because that's
going to be a lot of work and that's
going to be difficult to do and when we
look at the concerns that are raised as
we learn and develop I hope that I hope
that other members of this body are
going to recognize that there is a
belief among a substantial number of
people. Uh
certainly there's many people that I
don't know if they even have an opinion
about this. They're living their lives.
But there is a there is a group of us
here on the council that have expressed
ourselves very clearly
and are going to be following up on what
we know about this. And I hope that
we're respected. I hope that we're uh
treated with uh an understanding that it
wasn't oh we already annexed that's over
with. And I do want to say to uh my
friends at Leads and the people that
I've been working with and talking to at
Microsoft, this is business.
So let's be businesslike about it and
understand that the eb and flow of
commerce
uh happens that that we're in a very
difficult period of time in our country.
We're a war.
There are factors here that that are far
from us. But when we when we talk about
this issue here, let's respect each
other and respect those opinions so that
we can proceed because there's a lot of
proceeding coming down the pike on the
this very issue on other specific areas.
So, um I
believe I've said enough. Thank you.
Mr. Escoel. Yeah, Mr. Mayor, I'll try
and be brief. Uh, on our break, I asked
the gentleman over here that's been
working in data center for 13 years. I
said, "Well, why aren't you concerned
about your health? You had people that
live a mile away. are and I guess you
know fear spreads like fire
um to the people of Sweetg Grass
subdivision.
I think probably one of the luckiest
subdivisions in in Cheyenne. Saddle
Ridge isn't going to have a conservation
out there. They're not going to have a
five uh 100 acre
uh
area between
your subdivision and
this uh annexation.
Uh
and the family felt strongly about
having that conservation easement there.
Uh it could have been a wind farm, it
could have been a solar farm, uh it
could have been the meat processing
plant out there. uh and you're protected
knowing that there's not going to be any
development between you and that ridge.
Uh and I think that's, you know, if I
lived there' be happy to know that. Uh
when we went and toured it, they showed
us their uh lighting is directed down.
There's big black shields above it. Uh
so I don't think that will be affected.
And
it it just seems that from the days I
was in the legislature, we always said,
"Why don't we get high-tech jobs here
for our kids to quit leaving the state
of Wyoming?" And then we do. And
um yeah, I think there's always going to
be some apprehensions. Uh, but I think
if I ask most people, would you rather
that the data centers leave the state of
Wyoming or your children leave the state
of Wyoming?
[snorts]
And I know what I choose because I
already lost two of my daughters to the
other states and and one of them's
actually thought about uh coming back to
work for Microsoft. So, I would support
him.
All
right. Anybody else have any last minute
comments?
>> Mr. Mayor, um
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> thank you through you members of the
council.
U there's an ancient African
saying that I just read about in a book
I'm reading about China,
and it's this.
The dogs may bark, but the caravan moves
on.
I've been barking at this
since it came to us.
Uh,
I didn't get on this council to
engage in a fight with one of the
largest corporations in the world.
Um in fact it's really contrary to my
entire career which has been built
building things in the energy industry.
Coal mines, trona plants, natural gas
processing plants,
pipelines,
windmills.
Somebody mentioned the uh regulation of
the wind industry in 2010.
I drafted those that legislation and the
rules that came out of it with um Cindy
Delansancy.
Um so I'm not opposed to data centers
and I'm not opposed to large industries.
Um but what we have here
and I'll set it and I'll keep this
short. Um,
annexation is one of the most
significant actions that a city can do.
Why is that? Because it's the extension
of the municipal
sovereignty to another part of the
county.
So that's why it requires
very thoughtful approach
and it requires evidence
and we can argue about what kind of
evidence and what kind of factf finding
should be done
but
in this case and I said I would not do
this and I'm not going to there's
there's a really significant set of
legal issues that
could be addressed if somebody so
chooses.
Councilman White says we got to treat
everybody the same. Well, we do. We
annex everybody. That's our policy. And
all you have to do to know that is go
look at all the ordinance of annexation.
They're all the same. They all have the
same language.
And I think if you read the staff
reports, they're very much alike.
They're not really based on evidence.
They're not really based on witnesses
coming forward and saying this is what
supports these statutory factors.
They're based on a fundamental starting
point, which is this is going to be
annexed. So just just get ready for
that. Now I tried to get a political
solution to this. I tried to get this
extended for us to give ourselves more
time,
but I failed with my two colleagues,
which is probably only a testament to
what a lousy politician I am.
Um,
so the argument that we've been doing is
about Highlands being a data center.
Well,
yeah, it might be.
Microsoft won't tell us that
data centers are the the project dour
but in 10 years data centers might be
pass a
technology may have changed dramatically
and the data centers that are built
might be a lot smaller or they might be
a lot bigger or they might use less
water or they might use more
We don't know. But more importantly,
Microsoft doesn't know.
So what is what does that leave us? What
are the kinds of things that we should
be thinking about?
Well, here's my list of that. So when
all of you think about this tomorrow
when we all wake up um
here are the things I think you should
be prepared for. Number one more data
centers are coming there more
announcements to be made.
Now some people on this dis actually
already know that but the rest of us
don't. And I want to make also one point
really clear about this metacontractor
contamination.
Most of the people on the council, maybe
almost all the council found out about
it at the same moment that all of you in
this audience did.
Nobody told us about it.
So there are more things coming. Now, I
mean, just just look what's happened in
the last couple weeks. We get an email.
We on the council got an email and
everybody in the community got an email
that says Vantage is having a
open house.
in three days. In three days to announce
a project
that is both a power plant
and a data center that they hope to
start construction on
early next year
and spend 20 billion dollar on. That's
how fast this is moving. To give you
some perspective on 20 billion dollars,
if you asked AI, what is the entire
capital investment in Wyoming in the
coal industry?
AI's estimate was 32 to 42 billion.
So, one plant announced with three days
notice
proposing to spend almost half of what
the coal industry spent over the course
of almost 50 years.
That's the magnitude of what we're
dealing with.
Yes, these are going to bring maybe vast
economic benefits, but they're going to
come with lots and lots of challenges.
So, the things you really ought to be
watching up for, the things to closely
pay attention to are Google and Tall
Grass because they want to build their
own power plants and they want to build
their own data centers. Vantage, which
is right next door to those.
Keep your eyes on Meta just because of
what we've already seen and about their
behavior.
And of course, Microsoft, which has, if
you look at the maps that we've
prepared, Microsoft has construction
sweeping all the way around in a 180
degree arc around the south side of the
city.
Now, state legislation, we've talked
about that and Dr. Renie is, I think,
highly likely to be involved in this. We
we who live in this county are going to
need to pay very close attention to this
because in truth,
data centers are only a Laramie County,
city of Cheyenne issue at this point and
maybe for a long time into the future.
So what you're going to faced with is
that 90% of the legislators who are
going to come down here,
they're not impacted by it, but boy are
they going to have opinions about it.
And we and the city sitting there
starting next year in the legislative
session are going to face a really
significant set of issues that could, if
they come out wrong, fundamentally
change what's going on in the data
center industry in this state.
So, um,
I made my pitch on all the things we
could be doing.
I appreciate all the mayor and the
council spending all of our time.
Um, I've uh appreciated all of you
coming, sharing your lives and your uh
views with us. So, thank you. Um, I
guess this dog is not going to bark
about this one anymore. Um, but there'll
be other things.
>> Thanks,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Real quick, thank you again everybody
for public comment, but I did want to
bring this up.
If you actually look at the
documentation, the applicant is not
Microsoft, nor are Microsoft yet. We
heard Microsoft actually now owns the
property, but according to our official
documents, it's not Microsoft. So
something to also consider legal
[snorts] ramifications. Thank you.
>> Any other comments? Dr. Ry? No.
>> All right. Hearing none. Madam clerk,
would you take the vote, please?
>> Mr. White?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wolf?
>> No.
>> Dr. Aldrich? Yes, Mayor Collins.
>> Yes,
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Mr. Esel.
>> Hi,
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> No,
>> Mr. Moody.
>> Dr. Renie.
>> Yes,
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Yes.
>> This ordinance is approved on third and
final reading with Mrs. Moody, Wolf, and
Leborn voting no.
>> Number 14.
>> I move to journ.
>> We can't.
It's a non-debatable motion. We can take
a vote on it, but it's 12:30.
>> Is there Is there a second?
>> No.
>> Second. Second.
>> All right.
>> Question.
>> Mr. Wolf is right. It's a non-debatal
motion. All those in favor of adjourning
for the evening, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> Let me see the hands of the nose.
Rainey,
Dr. Emmens, Mr. Crave, Dr. Aldridge, Mr.
Escoel, and Mr. Why? We will continue.
>> Mr. Mayor, let let me make a point that
that I
>> Mr. Mr. Wolf, you you've had your point.
It failed. Let's move on with the
agenda.
>> This is a failure of our processes, Mr.
Mayor.
It is really just such an imposition
both on all of these people, and all the
people who are we're not even we we've
still got hours to go. We've got the
Reed annexation that or the Reed zoning.
We've got all these other things. We
should reschedu this and have another
council meeting to pick this up. And
frankly, this is a problem that is of
our own creation. We should manage these
agendas when we have things like this in
a way that doesn't create such an
imposition.
>> Mr. Wolf, I I understand what you're
saying, but the council's made a
decision. We're going to move on.
>> Next item, please.
Number 14, ordinance third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, establishing the
zoning classification of AG agricultural
for land annex to the city of Cheyenne,
located east of South Kley Highway and
south of the Sweetg Grass subdivision.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience.
This is the land that was just recently
annexed. This would actually um
establish the zone as AG, which is what
it is currently in the county. and um
ask anybody if they want to speak to
that.
>> Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Um I second Mr. Wolf.
Okay. Uh can you hear me?
>> Yes.
Uh
just one moment here. This is number 14.
Is that correct?
>> Yes.
>> Yes, Mr. Miller.
>> All right.
And
you said that this was establishing a G
zoning.
>> Yes, Mr. Miller.
[snorts]
>> All right.
Um, Mayor Collins, members of the city
council, Charles Miller for the
permanent administrative record. I'm
stepping to the microphone on item 14 to
issue a formal constructed notice
regarding the procedural laundering of
the 3,500 acre Highlands annexation.
Right now, you're moving to establish an
AG agricultural zoning classification
for this newly annexed territory. The
city claims this is merely an
administrative requirement under
UDC2.2.8
to assign the most anal analgious city
zone to the current county zone. Uh, let
the appelllet record reflect exactly
what this is. It's a calculated
procedural fiction. Your own planning
and development staff report explicitly
admits the true purpose of this action
on page two, stating verbatim that the
AG designation is merely a holding zone
which will allow the land to be reszoned
more easily in the future as the land
develops. We know exactly what that
future is because it is sitting right
next uh on your docket. In agenda item
number 15, you intend to instantly strip
away this 3500 acre agricultural holding
zone and permanently flip it to BP
Business Park to accommodate a
multi-gawatt Microsoft data center
campus. You're utilizing a two-step
laundering maneuver. You were using a
temporary agricultural assignment to
sanitize the annexation and push it
through with minimal friction only to
immediately trigger the business park
loophole moments later to bypass the
statemandated environmental oversight of
the industrial sighting act. I'm placing
you on notice that you cannot you cannot
sever the legal liability of these
actions because you are applying a sight
specific zoning map amendment for named
corporate entities specifically ARP
Hammond Hardware and Lumis Livestock
Company. This rem remains a quas quasi
judicial act. You are legally mandated
to base your decision on substantial
evidence that to produce separately
stated findings of fact. You cannot
legally use a temporary holding zone to
blindside the public and bypass the
heavy industrial scrutiny that a project
of this magnitude requires. By approving
this agricultural stepping stone without
empirical infrastructure data, you are
cementing the evidentiary void for the
business park resoning. Coming up next,
this procedural illusion is now logged
on the record. Your manufacturing is
structurally defective entitlement. I
demand a no vote. Thank you.
One more
>> Jennifer.
>> It looks like they put their hand down.
>> Okay.
>> Anybody else on AG?
>> My assumption is that it's going to be
voted on.
>> Would you identify yourself, please?
>> Janet Tolman three.
Um to the mayor and the council, it's
been said that everything is treated
equally.
So I guess this is just procedure here
that everything is going to be voted to
be annexed in. Everything is going to be
voted to change from one zoning to
another zoning and everybody is going to
agree to that.
And my question is
why are we invited to give our input?
>> Anybody else want to speak?
Yes, ma'am.
>> Shay, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Okay. Can you hear me?
>> Shay, we can hear you.
>> Hi. Um, sorry, Shay. Five forward two. I
had to leave because I was upset and I
cry when I'm upset. Um, I guess my
question now since the annexation
already passed through is how is it
appropriate to do an annexation and then
two resonings in the same meeting on the
same night? That just seems, you know,
wildly inappropriate. And then my second
question would be, I'm pretty sure out
of your own mouth, Mayor Collins, that
you said at least twice tonight that
this property had not been sold yet.
So, how did that all of the sudden be
like all now they have the closing date?
But we didn't know that before that. I
>> I think ma'am, if you go back and listen
to the record, you'll you'll hear that I
said it actually had closed.
>> No, you did not. You said twice before
earlier in the evening that it had not.
>> Ma'am,
>> I I knew I was told by the owner of the
property that it had closed and uh I'm
I'm sure if we go back and look at the
record, the record will show that I said
that.
>> Okay. Wow.
I didn't hear that. But my my concern is
that you are reszoning and annexing in
one night. Now
you aren't giving the citizens the time
that we asked for and that Mr. Moody
asked for or that Mr. You know, Wolf has
asked for with the annexation. So, pause
on the resoning.
Like, your pants aren't on fire. It's
fine. Jumping into this is just kind of
suicidal.
Thank you.
Anybody else on the agricultural zone?
>> Hi, Jane Leinger,
City and County. Um, once you get the
resoning done, which I'm sure we'll go
out through, what kind of leverage do
you think you'll have in order to get a
uh agreement with whoever owns the
property to really um be good neighbors
to the rest of Cheyenne. I think you'll
have lost your leverage.
>> Anyone else?
>> Hearing none, I'll go to Dr. Aldridge
for a motion, please.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second
>> seconded by Mr. Cagrave. Comments for
members of the governing body on
establishing the AG zone. [snorts]
>> Hearing none. Madame clerk.
>> Mr. Crave.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. White.
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> No.
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Yes.
>> Mayor Collins.
>> Dr. Emmens.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Escapel.
>> Hi.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> No.
>> Mr. Moody.
>> No. [clears throat]
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> All right. This uh established zone
district is approved on third and final
reading with Wolf, Lebornne, and Mr.
Moody voting no.
>> Number 15, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located east of
South Kley Highway and south of the
Sweetg Grass subdivision from AG
Agricultural MPU planned unit
development to BP Business Park.
>> All right. This is the owner's requested
zone uh to business park for 3,34 acres
uh for mixeduse employment which as we
all know would be a data center. Go out
to the audience.
>> Good evening again sir.
>> Hi Al [clears throat] Gates Ward three
still awake. Um, I'm I'm comforted
[clears throat] about the set aside of
the 500 acres that was discussed uh with
the whole with the whole deal. That's
that's great. That talks about building
a buffer uh between SweetG Grass and the
Highland Park. That's awesome. I do
[clears throat] wonder as part of a
zoning decision if it would make sense
to zone that 500 acres differently so
that there's assurance that that doesn't
change. That's my only comment. Thank
you.
Let me let me ask staff this question,
but I believe we annexed that all
agricultural and we're only changing
3,000 of it to business park. So, I
think that the intervening land is
agricultural, but I need to ask our
staff that just to make sure I didn't
misspeak.
Conor's coming running. Thank you,
Connor.
Mayor and members of
Mayor, members of council, counterway,
planning development department. So with
the annexation, you've got the 3500
acres. The last assigned zoning assigned
the AG zone to 3500 acres. The zone
change only reszones 3,000 of that. So
the other 500 stays in the egg zone.
>> So your wish has been done, sir.
>> That would be awesome. I'd love to see a
map of that.
>> Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> Anyone else in the audience?
>> Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Can you hear me?
>> Yes, Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> All right. Um, Mayor Collins, members of
the city council for the permanent
administrative record. My name is
Charles Miller.
Um, I'm here to submit a formal
objection to the proposed reasonzoning
of the 3500 acre Highlands development.
You just said it was 3,000 acres. Is
that correct?
>> 3,34.7
acres.
>> Oh, okay. Um, well, the of that many
acres, uh, devel Highlands development
from agricultural to business park. This
body cannot legally approve a business
park designation when the project's
actual operational footprint violates
your own unified development code and
stands in total defiance of current
public health and safety crisises.
First, under your own UDC text, well,
actually, let's speak also about what
Mr. Moody had brought up uh and others.
This is not an owner initiated
annexation anymore because it was
transferred over in the middle of the
annexation. So that's just another
another point there that kind of
contaminates this. But anyhow, uh a
business park classification is
restricted to light low impact uses. If
a facility consistently generates noise
or intense utility burdens discernable
at its perimeter, it is legally
classified as heavy industrial. Trillion
dollar tech developers are attempting to
treat this BP zoning as a flexible
political rubber stamp. Yet, by their
own admission on your microphone, they
possess an absolute data void regarding
sight specific engineering and fullload
acoustic telemetry. You're adopting
formal find findings of fact over a
ghost project consciously creating a
regulatory blind spot to help a
developer evade the state's industrial
sighting act. Second, the this council
cannot claim that environmental
protections are a future enforcement
issue when your current framework is
failing in real time. Just weeks ago,
routine testing caught the rare
environmental pathogen
coupraitis gelardi inside our wastewater
system traced directly to data center
cont to a data center contractor. This
contamination forced the immediate
suspension of our reclaimed water
irrigation program over public health
risks and saw untreated bacteria escape
straight into Crow Creek. Rushing a
massive chemically intensive industrial
expansion without established
environmental baselines, localized
pre-treatment requirements, or dedicated
oversight is an absolute abdication of
your fiduciary duty to the taxpayers.
[cough] Finally, look at the systemic
breakdown of our emergency
infrastructure.
On September 21st, 2025, during the
Kinder Morgan pipeline rupture and
subsequent toxic release, this city
failed to deploy federally integrated
wireless emergency alerts to downwind
neighbors to
>> know your time is up. Thank you, sir.
Anyone else in the audience
hearing? None. Dr. Aldrich, may we have
a motion, please?
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation oop,
sorry, Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of
the public services committee is to
approve on third and final reading, and
I so move.
>> Second. Seconded by Mr. White. Comments
from members of the governing body on
the zone change.
>> Hearing none. Madam clerk, would you
take the vote, please?
>> Dr. Renie,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Crave,
>> Mr. White,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wolf,
>> no.
>> Dr. Aldrich,
>> yes.
>> Mayor Collins,
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Esel,
>> I.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> no.
>> Mr. Moody,
The zone change is approved on third and
final reading with Mrs. Wolf, Lebornne,
and Moody voting no.
>> Number 16, ordinance, third reading,
amending the official zoning map of the
city of Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located south of
I80 east of College Drive from AG
Agricultural to BP Business Park. All
right, we have another owner requested
zone change to uh go to business park
for 387 acres uh to create a mixeduse
employment and again I believe we know
this will be for potentially a future
data center site
Mr. Emmens. Welcome again.
>> Uh, mayor, city council members, just
because this is a new location, um, very
similar items, but wanted to be come up
as the agent for the applicant and
owners on this project and be happy to
answer any questions that have come up
with the council about this zone change
from agricultural to business park.
>> Mr. Evans, this is the RE property. Yep.
>> Just for the record, I think it's almost
people recognize this, right?
>> Yep. This property. Yep.
Thank you, sir. Anybody else in the
audience?
Okay, Jennifer,
>> Mr. Reid, you can go ahead.
>> Good morning.
>> Let me begin.
>> Let me begin by thanking you, Mr. Mayor
and members of the city council for your
public service, your gem de
demonstration of joblike patience during
these meetings and willingness to suffer
unmmerited personal attacks and endure
barges of misinformation.
>> Sir, could I get you to identify
yourself for the record, please?
>> Uh, my name is Dan Reed. I am the
spokesperson for the Reed family.
Thank you, sir.
>> This property has been in the Reed
family for four generations now and fell
to the stewardship of my generation in
the 1980s.
For over 40 years now, we have
endeavored to sell the property, always
giving preference to the residential
development of the land. Among my group
are professional real estate agent
uh an executive of a construction
company working on chip fabrication
centers and other major construction
projects.
Previously the members of the Reed
family worked with local developers to
successfully develop a nearby industrial
park of over a 100 acres.
Members of this group have developed
hundreds of acres of rural residential
property in Larmy County. So, we're not
without relevant expertise in these
areas.
Twice we have been in contract with
residential developers only to have them
withdraw from the contract at the end of
their due diligence period for
topographical
and related reasons. In the early 2000s,
I worked for weeks to find the land
acquisition person for Costco to see if
we could attract to them to our property
as an anchor establishment.
I was told Costco had no plans to expand
into Wyoming.
And now we have a buyer who is
enthusiastic about the property and with
whom with whom it has been better to
negotiate than with any previous buyer
we have worked with. As I've said
before, having engaged in over a
halfozen negotiations for the sale of
the property, Microsoft has been the
most reasonable and agreeable buyer with
whom to negotiate. I am convinced that
their plans for the reed land represent
the optimal future for the land and its
contribution to the city of Cheyenne.
Thank you,
>> Dan. Thanks for calling in this late.
Appreciate it.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> Oh, all right. But do you hear me? Just
joking. Um, Mayor Collins, members of
the city council, and city attorney
Brody, Charles Miller for the permanent
administrative record.
Um, just for clarification, this is item
number 16, the third reading to reszone
the 387 acre reed land parcel from AG to
BP Business Park.
>> That's correct.
>> And it's uh for another data center
development. Is that correct?
>> Yes, sir. I think the record is that
it's Microsoft.
Ah well um
so let uh let me ask you this. Have you
guys overruled your planning commission
officially?
Uh like uh like have you changed the um
done the
the overruling
>> yet or?
>> Well, you did just overrule it moments
ago with the Highlands reszoning. Um and
now you're preparing to do it again.
Um on June 1st, your planning commission
explicitly recommend that recommended
that this governing body deny this exact
resoning application because this is a
sightsp specific zoning map amendment
for a named developer. It is a quasi
judicial act. Um under the tonga
doctrine, you cannot legally override
over overrule your planning experts
without introducing new substantial
evidence and generating separately
stated findings of fact to bridge your
analytical gap. You have no new
evidence, but worse, the evidence you do
have mathematically proves this resoning
harms the public. Look at page five of
your own planning and development staff
report for PUDC 26121.
Under the mandatory review criteria of
UDC 221DB,
which asks whether the application will
harm the public health, safety, or
general welfare, your own staff
explicitly wrote, Cheyenne has had
documented housing challenges, and
taking land anticipated for majority
residential development and zoning that
land into a business park would
adversely affect the general welfare of
the community.
Um, your comprehensive plan designates
this land for urban residential and
mixeduse residential development. The BP
zone practically prohibits residential
uses. You are literally deleting a 387
acre residential footprint during a
documented housing crisis to grant an
industrial entitlement for a data center
ghost project.
Um,
you're manufacturing a structurally
defective voidable ordinance. Um, you're
ignoring your own staff's written
warning about the destruction of
residential zoning and overruling your
planning commission without providing a
single page of empirical infrastructure
telemetry to justify it.
The housing deletion [sighs] is sealed.
The Tonga violation is logged. Demand a
no vote. Thank you.
>> Jennifer, do you have any more,
>> sir?
>> Uh, Troy Ach 3 still at LC. Um,
speaking for myself again, but I can I
want to say that please support this.
Please vote. Uh, yes.
When I get to meet with students and
people who are trying to change careers,
change their lives, people who are
in deadend jobs and want something
different, somebody who's graduating
high school but doesn't want to leave
Wyoming,
a veteran who is rotating out but
doesn't know what life of the military
looks like. And I try to explain to them
what these careers are. The idea that I
can walk them to the end of campus
and show what they are. Microsoft has
been an amazing corporate partner for
us. They have had all kinds of
opportunities for our students.
The ability to have that next door in my
opinion personally is very powerful.
That's all I have. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
Anybody else in the audience want to
speak to this um owner requested zone
change?
>> All right. Hearing none, Dr. Aldrich,
may we have a motion, please?
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to approve
on third and final reading and I so
move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Tom Crave, Mr. Crave. Um, go
back to the uh governing body. Comments
from members of the governing body.
I hear none. Madame clerk, would you
take the role?
>> Mr. Moody?
>> No.
>> Dr. Renie?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Crave?
>> Mr. White?
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Wolf?
>> Hi. Dr. Aldrich,
>> yes. Mayor Collins,
>> yes.
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> yes. Mr. Escoel,
>> I.
>> Mr. Leborn,
>> yes.
>> This zone change is approved on third
and final reading with Mr. Moody voting
no.
>> Number 17, ordinance, first reading,
annexing to the city of Cheyenne,
Wyoming, land west of Roundtop Road and
south of HappyJack Road.
>> We'll refer this item to the public
services committee. Number 18,
ordinance, first reading, amending the
official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, establishing the zoning
classification of BP Business Park for
land annex to the city of Cheyenne,
located west of Roundtop Road and south
of Happy Jack Road.
>> We'll send this item to the public
services committee. Number 19,
resolution over ruling the planning
commission's disapproval of an amendment
to the future land use map of plan
Cheyenne, changing the land use
designation from agricultural, rural,
and urban residential to mixeduse
employment and amending the urban
service boundary for property generally
located east of South Kley Highway and
south of the Sweetgrass subdivision.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience
on this uh resolution before us. Does
anybody in the audience want to speak to
it?
You can put your hand up, Jennifer. We
know. Mr. Miller,
>> Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> We can hear you.
>> Mayor Collins, members of the council,
Charles Miller for the permanent
administrative record. Um, this is in
regards to items 19 uh and 20 to place a
formal constructive notice.
uh in regards to placing a formal
constructed notice of legal in
invalidity regarding resolution
PUDC-26-116.
Tonight you are invoking Wyoming statute
15-1-506
to officially overrule your own planning
commission's June 1st denial of the flum
the future land use map amendment for
the Microsoft Highlands expansion. Let
the appellet record reflect that under
the Tonga doctrine in Wyoming statute
16-3-114C,
your vote tonight is a quasi judicial
act. You cannot legally reverse the
three to two disapproval of your own
planning experts without generating
separately stated findings of fact and
introducing new substantial evidence to
bridge the analytical gap. You do not
have that evidence. The staff memos
provided to you tonight to justify this
override are entirely procedural. They
contain zero new technical studies, zero
updated infrastructure analysis, and
zero empirical data to counter the
planning commission's stated concerns.
You are attempting to bridge an
analytical gap over an absolute
evidentiary void. On the June 1st
record, the applicant's own
representative, a Rachel Irwin,
explicitly confessed that Microsoft has
not yet advanced detailed design for
this 3500 acre campus. It is a
mathematical and legal impossibility for
this governing body to adopt affirmative
findings of fact to amend a
comprehensive plan for a multi-gawatt
facility that the developer admits does
not exist on paper. By voting yes to
overrule your experts based on a
procedural staff memo rather than
empirical infrastructure telemetry, you
are acting in an arbitrary and
capricious manner. You are manufacturing
a structurally defective land use
entitlement that is void abinio. When a
district court strikes this down under
the novo review, the resulting debt
detrimental reliance litigation will
bankrupt uh the taxpayers of Cheyenne.
Probably not bankrupt them, but uh the
topa violation is logged. The
evidentiary void is sealed. I demand a
no vote on items 19 and 20. Thank you.
>> All right. Is there anybody else in the
audience want to speak to this um
overruling of the planning commission?
>> Yes, Jennifer.
Maj you can go ahead.
>> Majar.
>> Hello.
>> Can you unmute yourself?
>> We can barely hear you.
Is that better?
>> It's so much better.
>> Okay, cool. Things get disconnected
through technology. Isn't it fun
restarting things? Anyway, what I want
to say is as I've gone through things
with people talking about their
addresses and stuff, you are actively
decreasing
values of properties
for owners who have lived here. for a
long time.
Not as long as maybe Lumus, but other
people who have decided to establish
their life here and invest in their
future of their families and their
homes, their properties.
If you guys decide to go forward with
this, giving so many permissions to
these outlets that want to take our
resources,
I would hope that we are able to be
compensated not just for the property
because the property often times is more
than the home,
but the property, the home, the
improvements, and the emotional
investment
in building here because you are setting
a precedent to wipe it all away. And the
people who want to leave,
look at the map. This is happening
everywhere. There is nowhere to go. So
if you have a secret space, let us know.
I do not appreciate this for the sake of
my family. Thank you for your time.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
Jennifer, do you have any more? Anybody
else in the audience? All right, we'll
go out to Dr. Aldridge for a motion,
please.
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to adopt
and I so move.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Cagrave. Comments from
members of the governing body on the uh
resolution before us.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you. Through you.
>> Why do we have to do this? I mean, does
the UDC or something else require us to
actually overrule the planning
commission?
>> Mr. Mayor,
isn't it? State statute requires a
quorum of the body, which is seven.
So, state statute required four votes
for an affirmative vote and there were
only five members there that night and
two voted no. So, even though it had a
positive recommendation, it didn't
comply with state statute, so it came
out with a negative recommendation.
>> I don't think that answered Mr. Wolf's
question, though. And why is it that we
have to actually Why do we have to do
it? Why do we have to overrule them? Mr.
Bloom, can you answer that question?
>> Mayor, member of members of the council,
Charles Bloom, plan the development
director. Um, really it's a combination
of two things. The planning commission
bylaws and state statute bylaws only
allow the chair of the planning
commission to vote in the event of a
tie. Um, so if you have an
if your result without the chair voting
is an odd or is not an even vote, then
they can't vote. And then also state
statute requires that for a land use
plan amendment that a majority of the
the board vote in favor of that change.
Um, and that doesn't take in account any
attendance. So in this specific case,
there are only five members present and
they're unable to hit the quorum of the
seven member board.
>> And Mr. Bloom, because it failed there,
it's required that if we want to move
forward, we have to overrule the
planning commission. Is that a rule?
>> Mayor, members of council, under state
statute, the governing body um is
required to overrule the planning
commission uh due to those reasons to
approve that land use plan amendment.
>> Thank you. Did that help, Mol?
Uh suppose so so we can't just ignore
what they did. Mr. Bloom through you
mayor.
>> Mr. Bloom.
>> Mayor through you to Councilman Wolf. Um
you can recognize that they considered
the item and they're unable to um obtain
that majority vote of the total
membership of the commission. Um I
um
I need to ask the staff real quick what
that vote was um at the Isn't the memo?
>> I think it was three to two.
>> It was a
>> We just didn't have enough positive
votes to meet the four requirements. The
majority of the board,
>> correct? So the members present did vote
to approve this land use plan amendment.
However, due to not meeting the four yes
votes under state statute, um it would
not be a to move forward with a positive
recommendation for approval unless
overruled by the governing body.
Okay.
Anybody else from the governing body
hearing? None. All those in favor of the
resolution, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> May I see the hands of the nose? Uh Mr.
Wolf,
Minister Moody, and Mr. Lelay.
The resolution is adopted.
Next item is number 20 on page four.
Resolution amending the future land use
map of plan Cheyenne. Changing the land
use designation from agricultural,
rural, and urban residential to mixeduse
employment and amending the urban
service boundary for property generally
located east of South Gley Highway and
south of the Sweetgrass subdivision.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience.
Does anybody in the audience want to
speak to this?
>> Okay, hearing none. Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to adopt an
ISO move.
>> Second,
>> it's been seconded by Mr. Cagrave. Uh
comments from members of the governing
body. U Mayor Collins.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> I just um I want to make sure that I
understand this because we just had the
Gates family who asked this question
before they left. Um, this is the
property that we had just given the A
designation to, the 400
some acres that was
left out of the 3,000
that um, we voted on for a business
park. Is that correct?
No,
>> Mr. Bloom.
>> Okconor. Thank you, M. Mr. White. still
here. Mayor, members, council, Conor,
Planning Development Department. This is
the future land use map amendment for
the Highlands property.
>> Um, it only changes the 3,000 acres that
were basically approved for BP. So, it
does not fully change the entirety of
the 3500. It's just the area that was
reszoned to BP
and then it adds the entire acre or the
entire 3500 to the urban service
boundary.
>> Okay. Thank you. Any other comments?
All right. Hearing none. All those in
favor of the resolution, please signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. No.
>> Mr. Wolf, Mr. Moody, and Mr. Labour
knows. The uh resolution is adopted.
>> Number 22. Resolution authorizing the
mayor and the city clerk to sign a final
plat for Swan Ranch Rail Park 21st
filing city of Cheyenne, Laramie County,
Wyoming, located west of Interstate 25
and north of West Wall Road.
>> All right, we have a final plat. I
believe this is the uh plat for some
land with 26 acres we annexed earlier in
the in the meeting. We'll go out to the
audience. Does anybody want to speak to
this final plat?
>> Yes, Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Can you hear me?
>> Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> Um, I uh I'm not sure exactly
what what happened here, the Charles
Miller, for the record, but uh but I had
my hand up for the previous item to to
comment on.
>> Um
that was pretty important deal there. Uh
so I don't know. Uh, but I guess I'm
gonna have to just move on to this one.
But, uh, [clears throat]
Mayor Collins, members of the city
council, uh, it's me, Charles Miller,
for the permanent administrative record.
Uh, this is the final plat for the Swan
Ranch Rail Park 21st filing, which you,
um,
you
it looks like that in my notes it was,
is this pulled from the consent agenda?
Yes sir.
>> Ah um okay. So this PLA application was
prepared and submitted by AVI
engineering.
Um
uh I'm glad you guys pulled it from the
consent agenda. Um but this is the exact
same firm whose agent submitted the
defective Highlands applications that
we've already established completely
lack basic infrastructure and acoustic
telemetry. Under Wyoming law, approving
a final plat requires a statutory
guarantee of adequate public facilities.
You cannot legally certify a final
industrial subdivision plat when your
own board of public utilities has just
banned closed loop water wastewater
discharges to the sanitary sewer. And
you possess zero empirical modeling on
how the cumulative load of these
industrial rail parks will impact our
municipal water supply. Hiding an
expedited industrial plat and a blanket
consent agenda. Boy, vote does. Well,
and I'm glad you guys removed it. Um,
but still, it's you're not shielded from
judicial review. Um, uh, I demand a a
member of this, uh, I'm sorry. Um,
I I demand you guys vote no. Thank you.
>> Anyone else in the audience?
>> All right. Dr. Aldrich.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
public services committee is to adopt
and I so move. Second
>> seconded by Mr. Crave. Any comments from
members of the governing body on this
final plat
hearing? None. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. The final plat is
approved.
>> Next item is number 26A on page five.
lease agreement between the city of
Cheyenne and First and Union Apartments
LP for 8.37 acres of land at the
northwest corner of Converse Avenue and
Carlson Street.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience.
This is the affordable housing project
that is going to lease 8.37 acres from
the city of Cheyenne to build 184 unit
affordable housing complex. Does anybody
want to speak to that item?
>> Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Can you hear me?
>> Yes, Mr. Miller, we can hear you.
>> All right. Uh,
so was this also p pulled from the
consent agenda?
>> It was not.
>> Oh, okay. Um, Mayor Collins, members of
the city council, Charles Miller. Um, do
do you guys have any other items that
were pulled from the consent agenda?
We're on item number 26A. Mr. Miller, do
you have a comment on item 26A?
>> Um, yeah. Okay. Let's see here. The
uh there's a there's a massive
documented contradiction in your
fiduciary management of the city's land.
Just moments ago during item 16, you
voted to strip 387 acres of residential
designated land and hand it over for a
data center business park. Your own
planning staff explicitly warned you in
their written report that Cheyenne has
had documented housing challenges and
that deleting res that residential land
would adversely affect the general
welfare of the community. You completely
ignored them. Now, in item number 26A,
you're attempting to put a
taxpayer-funded band-aid on the exact
housing crisis you just intentionally
worsened. You are moving to approve a
50-year ground lease with First and
Union Apartments LP, a Utah limited
partnership, to build 184 units of
affordable housing on 8.37 acres of
prime municipal land at Converse Avenue
in Carlson. But this is not just a
lease. It is a fiduciary giveaway. Under
section three of the contract, you allow
the developer to defer their rent
payments if they claim they lack
available free cash flow. Worse, under
section four, once the rent is paid or
the term expires, you are contractually
obligated to transfer this municipal
property entirely to this out ofstate
developer via via a special warranty
deed. You're giving away city-owned land
to subsidize a housing shortage that you
actively accelerated just 10 items ago
to appease a trillion dollar
hyperscaler. You cannot log logically or
legally claim to be protecting the
public welfare while executing this
two-sided arbitrage against taxpayers.
You're handing away our residential
zoning to tech monopolies and then
giving away our municipal land to
outofstate developers to hide the
damage. This blatant fiduciary
contradiction is permanently logged. I'd
demand a no vote. Thanks.
>> Anybody else in the audience or online?
All right. Hearing none, Mr. Esabel, may
we have a motion, please, sir?
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve in an
amount of 400 $4,521.64
per month for the term of 50 years. And
I so move
>> seconded by Mr. Wolf.
>> Mr. Mayor, I move to amend by substitute
dated July 9th, 2026.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Crave. We'll go out to
the audience. This is just a little bit
of a cleanup. Uh identified who the
title company would be. um corrected the
notification locations or the people to
be notified and corrected the map. So
just a couple things housekeeping things
like that. Is there anybody in the
audience would like to speak to the
substitute that uh uh puts the uh the
document in its final form?
>> Yes, Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller.
>> Yeah. Could you um could could you go
ahead and and
>> Mr. Mr. Miller, you want to identify
yourself for the record?
>> Yep. Charles Miller, for the record. Uh,
sorry about that. Uh, uh, council
members, uh, Mr. Mayor, would you
possibly be able to, instead of breezing
past that, uh, description of the
amendment, would you be able to
officially read the changes so that it
could be responded on?
>> Mr. Mayor, uh, Councilman Escoel doesn't
have it on the action report exactly
what came from the attorney's office.
>> Would you read that, Mr. Esel?
>> Pause my time as well, please.
>> Yes, sir.
A substitute is nonsubstantious
substantive in nature and corrects
formatting and typographical errors. It
also fills in information that was
inadvertently omitted from the original
draft, including one, the name of the
title company in section 19 for purposes
of it obtaining the committee commitment
for title insurance
for the leaseold policy. Two, the city
notice recipient of section 27 and
three, exhibit A, which contains a map
of the lease premises. Finally, the
substitute updates the first and union
signature block to correctly identify
the signing party.
>> Mr. Miller,
[clears throat]
>> so is is this standard procedure for you
guys to not have the actual substitute
uh in front of you? You just have a
description of what the changes are.
>> Mr. Miller, I'm holding the substitute
in my hand, sir.
>> Um, okay. So, so h how come
Okay.
[clears throat]
Uh I I guess I'm just uh kind of
confused as to why
uh you guys aren't able to to read the
the actual legal text.
>> Mr. Miller, the thing is I don't know 12
15 pages long as you know. Um so we've
just told you what was included in the
uh in the substitute.
And I'm sorry. Is that was that uploaded
to the uh your portal before this
meeting?
>> Mr. Miller, I don't think it was.
>> Um well then I'm going to have to say
that this is a severe procedural and due
process violation. Um you've just
admitted that neither the public nor the
permanent administrative record has been
provided with the actual physical text
of the substitute document. You're
attempting to legislate based on a brief
description of the changes. Um, let the
appellet record reflect that under
Wyoming law and foundational principles
of due process, you cannot legally pass
a binding municipal ordinance based on a
ghost document. The public has a
statutory right to review and provide
meaningful comment on the exact legal
language you're attempting to codify. We
cannot comment on a verbal summary.
Furthermore, as we have firmly
established tonight, if this substitute
amendment applies to any of the site
specific land,
>> Mr. Mill, your time is up. Thank you,
>> Mr. Mayor. Mr.
May I reiterate what's nonsubstant
substantive in nature
and only corrects formatting errors.
Thank you. Anybody else in the audience?
All right. How about from the governing
body on the substitute?
All right. Hearing none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed. All right. The substitute
is adopted and we're back on the main
motion. Comments from members of the
governing body.
All right. Hearing none. All those in
favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
>> The lease agreement is approved as
amended with Mr. Moody voting no.
>> Number 26B 2026 to 2027 collective labor
agreement between the city of Cheyenne
and Cheyenne firefighters, local union
number 279, International Association of
Firefighters.
>> All right. We have before us the uh
collective labor agreement uh with our
local fire union. We'll go out to the
audience and see if anybody wants to
speak to that.
Jennifer.
>> Um President Tholute
yourself.
>> Can you hear me? Okay,
>> Mr. Thol.
>> Uh Mayor Collins through you to the
governing body. Uh members of the city
council, Shine Firefires Local 279 is
allowing this version of the collective
lab labor agreement to move forward in
the best interest of both parties
despite changes being made beyond the
agreement reached during the March 23rd
negotiation meeting and despite this
version being submitted to the governing
body without further input from local
279. We do ask for one change that the
footnote on page 28 referencing an email
from Chief Dyshorn dated December 23rd,
2023 be removed. This footnote was a
change added without the consent of
local 279. We understand that Mayor
Collins feels this footnote is important
to show how we got here. However, nearly
every part of this contract has a
history explaining why it was added or
changed. Shine Firefires Local 279 keeps
that background information in separate
internal documents. Adding footnotes to
every provision would only increase the
size of the agreement without adding
actual substance to the terms contained
in it. For that reason, we respectfully
ask that the footnote be removed before
final approval. Thank you for your
consideration.
>> Anybody else in the audience? Yes,
Jennifer.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Can you hear? Mayor Collins, members of
the city council, Charles Miller for the
permanent administrative record. Um, I'm
stepping to the microphone on agenda
item 26B, the 2026 2027 collective labor
agreement between the city of Cheyenne
and Cheyenne Firefighters Local Union
279. I am absolutely not here to oppose
our firefighters.
Um, I am here to place on the permanent
administrative record exactly how this
governing body is actively endangering
them and defrauding them out of the
resources they require to survive.
Earlier tonight, you rubber stamped a
3,500 acre industrial data center
expansion. As Councilman Councilman
Renie confirmed on the live microphone,
you deliberately funneled this hypers
scale campus into a business park zone,
knowing full well that doing so legally
exempts the project from the
>> Mr. Miller, you're way off topic here.
We're talking about a collective labor
agreement with the fire union. If you
can get back to that, I'll let it go.
>> Okay. Okay. So, now um
now on item 20, it's it's it's
definitely Germaine here. Uh
the Wyoming Industrial Sighting Act
exists for one reason, and it's to
assess mandatory impact fees on
multi-billion dollar industrial
developers so local municipalities can
properly expand and equip their fire
services to handle massive new hazard
zones. Okay. So, you're signing a labor
contract with local 279, legally
obligating our fire firefighters to
respond to catastrophic events, chemical
coolants, and high voltage fires across
a new 3500 acre footprint, knowing
definitively that you just threw away
the state funding required to properly
equip them for it. You handling mic
handling Microsoft an industrial
entitlement while forcing the Cheyenne
taxpayers to foot the bill for their
emergency services. When the municipal
budget inevitably falls short because
you bypass the Industrial Sighting Act,
it will be the members of local 279 who
pay the price with their safety. This
contract is a documented reminder of the
fiduciary and physical liability you
have just forced onto this city's
emergency infrastructure. Govern
yourselves accordingly. Thank you.
>> Anybody else in the audience?
Hearing none. Mr. Esabel, we have a
motion, please.
>> Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to approve and I so
move. Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. Moody.
>> Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sir.
>> I move to amend section 21
classification of employment and basic
wages
subsection EMS pay to strike 97 cents
and read 77 cents for EMT basic for
shift 40hour personnel.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Dr. Aldridge.
when we uh were going back through the
contract, we found a scribers error or a
math error um where we uh made a mistake
on this one particular item and this
just goes back to uh correct that to
what was uh the appropriate number. Go
out to the audience. Is anybody in the
audience
hearing? None. How about from the
governing body?
Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed? Okay. The amendment is
approved and we're back on the main
motion.
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> for members of the governing body,
>> I have an amendment to remove the
footnote in the email. It's highly
unusual to have a email attached to a
binding labor contract.
>> Second.
>> Okay. We have a motion from Mr. Escoel,
seconded by
Dr. Aldrich to remove the footnote. Um,
we'll go out to the audience. Um,
anybody in the audience want to speak to
the motion to remove the footnote pound
on page 28 of the contract
hearing? None. How about from the
governing body?
>> Mr. Mayor, I'm not sure I understand why
the footnote was added to begin with. Um
if you uh if you look at the the
contract um under company strength, it
shows a minimum staffing of 20
firefighters. Um it is management's um
position that we should raise that to
22, putting two more firefighters on on
the street every day as a minimum. And
um uh
you know I I feel really uncomfortable
arguing with our our fire union about
the the city wanting to have more
firefighters on the street than what the
union is asking for. But uh that's what
the u um what the footnote does. Um it
is um that's part of it. The second part
of it is that we were working on our
effort to reduce overtime and um that
overtime number would needed to be two
above the minimum firefighter number. If
we leave that number at 20 then the
union can take uh overtimes to 22 which
is our minimum staffing every day when
we start. So if one person is sick, one
person is on FLMA, one person's in
training, every day we would have an
overtime. The idea was to have a two
member buffer to prevent that from
happening. So uh because for the last um
couple of years, actually more than two
years now, two and a half years, we've
been operating as a 22 member minimum
staffing paying overtimes over that. Uh
we wanted to put in the contract um
documentation that showed that um it was
management's um position that our
minimum staffing should be at least 22
firefighters. if that helps.
>> Mr. Mayor, I I don't uh disagree with
you. I just feel that it should have
been part of the collective bargaining
and in the contract, not in a footnote.
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> Mayor Collins, uh through you, I I
agree. I'm not I'm not in um in
opposition to um the staffing at 22.
What I'm in opposition to is that it is
being added as a footnote to an
agreement that we have agreed upon uh
with the during collective bargaining.
>> Dr. I would I would share with you I
don't know that we did agree to that.
You know, we talked about uh adding a
MERP and some other benefits to the fire
department if we could get overtime
under control and um we all know that 22
is the number of firefighters we're
minimum. So if if our minimum staffing
goes to 20, then we will not have gotten
what we negotiated for. So anyways,
that's how we got here. Anybody else in
the governing body?
Dr. Emmens.
>> Um thank you, [clears throat] Mr. Mayor.
So, I'm sorry. I'm confused about what
does the document without the footnote.
Does the document say 22 or 20?
>> It says 20. Ma'am,
>> 20. Thank you.
>> Any other comments? All right. We have a
motion to remove the footnote. All those
in favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
>> No.
>> May I see the hands of the nose, please?
Dr. Rainey, Dr. Emmens, Mr. Wolf, Mr.
Moody, Mr. Crave, and Mr. White. Uh,
that motion fails. We're back on the
main motion.
Comments from members of the governing
body.
Hearing none. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed?
The collective bargaining agreement is
approved as amended.
>> Next item is number 27D on page six.
Consideration of bid number S--22-26
for a contract between the city of
Cheyenne and Legacy Construction Group
for the Christensen Road Detention
erosion mitigation project.
>> All right, we'll go out to the audience
on this. Is anybody
Mr. Miller
>> um would you [clears throat] would you
guys be able to explain this one? um
a little better.
>> Uh Mr. Miller, we have a situation where
we have uh um the Christensen Road. Um
there's some erosion going on and we're
going to do a project to mitigate the
erosion and improve the situation out
there. That be fair,
>> mayor? Yes, sir. That's exactly what it
is.
>> The motion is from the committee is
actually to postpone this for two weeks,
though. So, um,
have at it, Mr. Miller.
>> Oh, um, and
um I guess, uh, I don't really have
anything on this one, so just wondering
if you guys could provide more details.
>> Anybody else in the audience?
>> Hearing none. Mr. Escobel, may we have a
motion, please?
>> Mr. Mr. Mayor, the recommendation of the
finance committee is to accept the bid
in the amount not to exceed $314,950.
And I so move.
>> Second.
>> That was seconded by Dr. Aldridge.
Comments from Yes.
>> Mr. Mayor. I I move to postpone until
July 27th 26 meeting of the governing
body.
>> Second.
>> Seconded by Mr. White. um postponement
is so that we can work with the railroad
to talk about um some of the the
conditions they might have on this
particular item. Um yes, ma'am.
>> Jennifer,
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
>> Mr. Miller,
>> can you hear me?
>> Yes.
Um, oh, so this is Charles Miller for
the record. Um,
so you you were saying something about
that this is to to handle some erosion.
Is that correct?
>> No, sir. We're on the motion to postpone
now.
>> Um, and you said that you need more time
to talk to the railroad. Is that
correct?
>> I believe that's correct, sir.
And so what exactly uh do you guys need
to I'm just wondering what what do you
guys need to talk to the railroad in
regards like specifically
>> Mr. Cotton
>> mayor through through you to Mr. Miller.
Sir, the the issue is related to the
railroad after our bid requested that we
went full steel pipe through their
rideway. Um I am looking at other
alternatives simply to repair that area
rather than uh steel pipe it to
significantly save the taxpayer quite a
bit of money.
>> Oh, and uh which which railroad is it?
>> Mayor through you to Mr. Miller. Mr.
Miller, you can come up to my office
anytime and discuss any of these issues
if like at any time, but it's the Union
Pacific Railroad, sir.
>> Oh, very nice.
Okay, thank you. That's all I have.
>> All right, we have a motion to postpone.
Anybody else in um in the audience want
to speak to that? How about from the
governing body?
Hearing none. All those in favor of the
twoe postponement signify by saying I.
>> I. Those opposed. This postponement is
approved.
>> Next item is number 28A on page eight.
Appointment of Jennifer Pasqua to the
community action of Laram County Board.
>> Um I don't get to vote on these
appointments, but um I'll run the the
vote.
>> I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Moved by Dr. Aldridge, seconded by Mr.
Caggrave. Um, all those in favor of the
appointment, please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Those opposed, this appointment is
approved.
>> Voucher report.
>> Is there anybody in the governing body
or on the audience that would like to
speak to the vouchers?
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> All right, let me just pull this up.
Um,
mayor, members of the council, Charles
Miller.
[snorts]
Um, let me see here.
Okay, here we go.
Um, this is for the permanent
administrative record. Um, this is the
for the voucher report. Um, and I'm here
to perform a systemic audit of tonight's
discretionary discretionary spending
against the city's statutory and
environmental obligations. In recent
weeks, this administration has cried
poverty. You have forced water and sewer
rate hikes onto the citizens of
Cheyenne, claiming you must beg for
federal handouts to address the $100
million or double possibly toxic lead
million tox dollar toxic, sorry, lead
pipe remediation mandate. You have used
this manufactured fiscal insolveny to
justify bypassing the statemandated
environmental oversight of the
industrial sighting act for the 3500
acre Microsoft expansion, claiming the
city city desperately needs the
corporate revenue.
Yet tonight's
uh $3.7 million voucher report exposes
that narrative as a calculated illusion.
Right now, buried in your itemized
receipts, you're hemorrhaging taxpayer
funds on a commercial aesthetics and
luxury event subsidies while our
underground infrastructure actively
degrades.
Tonight, you are rubber [clears throat]
stamping $70,000 to Suitcase Town Music
for a concert show advance.
$41,500
to Black 11 Touring for a Friday's on
the Plaza headliner. $34,725
to Colorado Jumps Incorporated for Super
Day Bouncy House attractions.
$8,148
to the Cognitive Behavioral Theater for
a Tim Meadows comedy show settlement and
over 200 $2,000 to Lotus Engineering for
cosmetic climate action consulting. This
is the definition of fiduciary satism.
You cannot legally claim a state of
fiscal emergency regarding the toxic
lead pipes in our community or evade
your duty to properly map the heavy
industrial hazards of trillion dollar
tech monopolies while simultaneously
authorizing hundreds of thousands of
dollars in concert advances and
inflatable bounce houses. This
establishes the evidentiary foundation
for a man now liability claim. A
municipal budget is a mathematical
expression of intent. Tonight's voucher
report proves this administration has a
documented custom of prioritizing
commercial aesthetics over public health
and safety. This financial contradiction
is now permanently logged into the
administrative record.
>> And Mr. Miller, your time is up. Thank
you. Anybody else?
All right. Hearing none other business
jumped on it for you. Anybody in the
audience want to speak to us under other
business?
Of course.
Mr. Miller, you can go ahead.
Can you hear me?
Yes.
>> Um, Charles Miller, for the record,
uh, I had thought that the revenue
document was going to be coming up here.
Um,
so I didn't have my other business in
front of me. Um,
>> however,
[snorts]
uh, Mayor Collins, members of the city
council, this is, uh, Charles Miller for
the permanent administrative record. Um,
this is the final constructive notice of
the evening before you adjourn. Uh, m
Mr. Collins. Earlier tonight, you
attempted to defend your lack of
transparency regarding these data
centers by stating on the live
microphone that you only signed
non-disclosure agreements with Cheyenne
Leadeds. You dismissed Leads as a mere
private nonprofit and claimed that
contracting with them does not make them
a quasi governmental agency.
Let the appellet record reflect the
legal reality. Delegating the
orchestration of a 3,500 acre municipal
annexation and heavy industrial zoning
strategy to a private entity shrouded in
NDAs is an unlawful delegation of
municipal police powers. You cannot
launder public zoning decisions through
a private 501c6 to hide the details from
the taxpayers who will bear the
infrastructure liabilities. Furthermore,
the structural conflict of interest in
this chamber is now permanently sealed.
Tonight, you accepted sight specific
zoning map amendments and urban service
boundary expansions prepared by Brad
Emmens, the acting agent for AVI
engineering. you allowed him to submit
these applications on an absolute
evidentiary void. Yet, if you look at
the voucher report you just rubber
stamped, this governing body,
excuse me, [clears throat] authorized a
$10,548
payment from the 1% construction fund
and a $9,859
payment under public works contract 8325
directly to AVI engineering. You are
systematically allowing a private firm
to act as the zoning agent for a
multi-billion dollar industrial
developer while simultaneously funding
municipal taxpayer funds to that exact
same firm on the same very same docket.
From the Tonga doctrine violations in
the industrial sighting act bypassed to
the destruction of residential housing
to the Manila liability of your luxury
voucher spending. This entire proceeding
is structurally defective and void abio.
You have chosen corporate compliance
over municipal law. The administrative
record is now closed. The trap is
sprung. See you in district court.
govern yourselves according accordingly.
>> See district court.
>> Anybody else in the audience want to
speak to us under other business?
Okay. How about from on the governing
body? Dr. Aldridge.
>> Mayor Collins for you. I just wanted to
um remind everyone, anybody that's still
awake that we will be having council and
coffee this Saturday on the 18th of July
from 9 to 11 at Dosbog in Ward 3. Um,
even though there is a there is a parade
going on, but we will still maintain our
commitment to our constituents.
>> Anybody else?
>> Mr. Mayor,
>> Mr. Wolf.
>> Thank you, sir. Um,
I just want to note uh that
um
we ought to thank our city engineer who
is I mean people ask, you know, who
really controls the city? Well,
I think in the summertime, Mr. Cobb
controls the city. Uh, and he is um
uh with uh incredible attention to
detail, managing something like 148
contracts. Um and uh we see the effects
of his work all over town. And um while
some people like my wife complain about
it, um I think it's actually a measure
of a a really successful um set of uh
programs that the city manages and I
just wanted to express my appreciation
to him for that.
>> Thank you, Mr. Wolf. Agreed. Anyone
else?
>> Folks, it's 1:41 in the morning. We are
adjourned.